<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_allPlus.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_allPlus.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Student-Focused Digital Projects in Short-Term Study Abroad
                    Experiences</title>
                <author n="ApplegateMattAPPLEGATE_Matt_Student_Focused_Digital_Projects_in_Short_Ter.xml"><persName n="ApplegateMatt">
                        <surname>Applegate</surname>
                        <forename>Matt</forename>
                    </persName><affiliation>Molloy University, United States of America</affiliation><email>mapplegate@molloy.edu</email></author><meeting><date from-iso="2023-07-10" to-iso="2023-07-14"/><title>Digital Humanities 2023. Collaboration as Opportunity</title><placeName>Graz</placeName></meeting>
                <author n="EvansSarahAPPLEGATE_Matt_Student_Focused_Digital_Projects_in_Short_Ter.xml"><persName n="EvansSarah">
                        <surname>Evans</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName><affiliation>Molloy University, United States of America</affiliation><email>sevans@molloy.edu</email></author><meeting><date from-iso="2023-07-10" to-iso="2023-07-14"/><title>Digital Humanities 2023. Collaboration as Opportunity</title><placeName>Graz</placeName></meeting>
                <author n="SchmidtKatherineAPPLEGATE_Matt_Student_Focused_Digital_Projects_in_Short_Ter.xml"><persName n="SchmidtKatherine">
                        <surname>Schmidt</surname>
                        <forename>Katherine</forename>
                    </persName><affiliation>Molloy University, United States of America</affiliation><email>kschmidt@molloy.edu</email></author><meeting><date from-iso="2023-07-10" to-iso="2023-07-14"/><title>Digital Humanities 2023. Collaboration as Opportunity</title><placeName>Graz</placeName></meeting>
            </titleStmt>
            
            <publicationStmt><publisher><orgName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1137284463">Zentrum für Informationsmodellierung
                    - Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities, Karl-Franzens-Universität
                    Graz</orgName></publisher><date when="2023">2023</date><pubPlace>Graz</pubPlace><availability><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">Creative Commons BY
                    4.0</licence></availability></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title>Digital Humanities 2023: Book of Abstracts</title><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-9256-0958"><forename>Walter</forename><surname>Scholger</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>University of Graz</orgName><placeName>Graz, Austria</placeName></affiliation><email>walter.scholger@uni-graz.at</email></editor><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-1726-1712"><forename>Georg</forename><surname>Vogeler</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>University of Graz</orgName><placeName>Graz, Austria</placeName></affiliation><email>georg.vogeler@uni-graz.at</email></editor><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-3919-993X"><forename>Toma</forename><surname>Tasovac</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>Belgrade Center for Digital Humanities</orgName><placeName>Belgrade, Serbia</placeName></affiliation><email>ttasovac@humanistika.org</email></editor><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-4593-059X"><forename>Anne</forename><surname>Baillot</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>Le Mans Université</orgName><placeName>Le Mans, France</placeName></affiliation><email>anne.baillot@univ-lemans.fr</email></editor><respStmt><resp>Data Management</resp><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0009-0007-9019-8215"><forename>Elisabeth</forename><surname>Raunig</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Management</resp><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-1438-3236"><forename>Martina</forename><surname>Scholger</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Management</resp><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-9116-0402"><forename>Elisabeth</forename><surname>Steiner</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Curation</resp><persName><forename>Johanna</forename><surname>Ofenauer</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Curation</resp><persName><forename>Christina</forename><surname>Burgstaller</surname></persName></respStmt><idno type="DOI">10.5281/zenodo.7961822</idno></seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="DHCONVALIDATOR" version="1.22">
                    <label>DHConvalidator</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc><abstract><p>This paper reflects on three interdisciplinary undergraduate digital humanities courses that featured study abroad trips to Rome, Italy and collaborative approaches to student-focused digital projects. Faculty presenters are housed in Digital Humanities, New Media, and Religious Studies, and co-developed courses that prioritize methods for researching, documenting, and visualizing placed-based discourse.</p></abstract><langUsage><language ident="en">English</language></langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="category">
                    <term>Paper</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="subcategory">
                    <term>Long Presentation</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="keywords">
                    <term>Digital Maps</term>
                    <term>Omeka</term>
                    <term>Relgious Studies</term>
                    <term>Study Abroad</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="topics">
                    <term>curricular and pedagogical development and analysis</term>
                    <term>digitization (2D &amp; 3D)</term>
                    <term>project design</term>
                    <term>organization</term>
                    <term>management</term>
                    <term>rhetorical analysis</term>
                    <term>Education/ pedagogy</term>
                    <term>Media studies</term>
                    <term>Theology and religious studies</term>
                    
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <head>Summary</head>
                <p>This paper outlines a brief history of three
                    interdisciplinary undergraduate digital humanities courses that featured study
                    abroad trips to Rome, Italy and collaborative approaches to  student-focused
                    digital projects. Faculty presenters are housed in Digital Humanities, New
                    Media, and Religious Studies, and co-developed courses and study abroad
                    experiences that prioritize methods for researching, documenting, and
                    visualizing placed-based discourse. In our latest iteration, our course
                    showcases narrative geospatial humanities work, media production skills, and
                    critical analytical methods for our students’ analysis of place and religious
                    history/culture. Our goal is to showcase the evolution of our interdisciplinary
                    collaboration so that others might emulate it, critically reflect on our
                    progress, and provide faculty with examples of DH work that is both
                    student-focused and participatory.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Context &amp; Background</head>
                <p>Critical GIS work in the humanities, especially
                    geospatial work in DH, is often mobilized to visualize and reflect on
                    minoritarian perspectives and discourse. To name a few, the Torn Apart /
                    Separados team visualized the effects of the US’s 2018 “zero tolerance” policy
                    for asylum seekers. DH scholar-practitioners at the University of Richmond have
                    visualized events leading to slavery’s end during the American Civil War via
                    “Visualizing Emancipation.” Further, mapping projects like “Artists in Paris” or
                    “Gathering Places: Religion &amp; Community in Milwaukee,” take a historical
                    view while thinking critically about their sense of place and subjects
                    therein–maps like these visualize historical differences and comment on cultural
                    change. </p>
                <p>Our courses and each iteration of our project explore
                    similar tensions, but we utilize methods that showcase students’ first hand
                    experience. In the past, we explored themes like ‘locating absence,’ asking
                    students to consider what it means to map something that is no longer present,
                    or, inversely, what it means  to visualize something that has been co-opted and
                    ideologically obscured. We focused specifically on issues of ethnic diversity in
                    Italy alongside the rise of ethno-nationalist ideologies. A second iteration
                    asked students to map contemporary cultural spaces in contrast to historical
                    ruins. In our most current iteration, we focus on religious history and
                    culture. </p>
                <p>Like many other disciplines, religious studies has
                    experienced a “material turn” in the past decade, with fresh interest on the
                    subject of place and material objects in the study of religion (see Plate,
                    <hi rend="italic"> Key Terms in Material Religion</hi>;
                    McDannell, <hi rend="italic">Material Christianity</hi>). Our collaboration with
                    religious studies faculty allows students to examine the material mediation of
                    historical narratives, particularly theological concepts (broadly conceived to
                    include Jewish, Christian, and pre-Christian Roman traditions) that are
                    site-specific in Rome, Italy. Practically speaking, students work to visualize
                    the complexities of religious narrative and archive their place-based
                    experiences via digital maps, VR video, social media projects, and an Omeka
                    repository. The collaboration also brings students to Ostia Antica, the ancient
                    port of Rome, to compare and analyze the relationship of the built
                    environment–both reconstructed and in ruin–to the historical narration of the
                    Roman and Italian past. While the project focuses mostly on art and
                    architecture, students also encounter and consider the mediation of relics in
                    the Catholic tradition, analyzing sites such as the Capuchin Crypt’s religious
                    tradition of curating human bones. While Christianity dominates much of Roman
                    art and architecture, students also examine the subculture of Jewish Rome,
                    analyzing both the Great Synagogue of Rome, its adjacent Jewish museum, and the
                    Jewish Quarter. This site allows for an important exercise in analysis of Roman
                    identity outside of the dominant culture of Catholic Christianity.  </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Skills &amp; Methods</head>
                <p>Student-focused projects demonstrate competence in
                    three areas: basic knowledge of HTML and GeoJSON deployed via the MapBox Studio,
                    media production in the form of still images and vlogs, and archival processes
                    than span popular social media platforms to a unified Omeka build out of the
                    trip. As students engage with various forms of curated religious culture, they
                    consider questions like: how is religion presented in museum and museum-like
                    settings around Rome? How are religious sites presented as museums or
                    museum-like sites? How are codes of behavior mediated and enforced to
                    non-religious visitors of these sites? Further, students focus on three
                    methodological areas of focus that serve as modules for our collaborative
                    course. For ease, we refer to each method by its essential function in the
                    project’s evolution: </p>
                <list type="ordered">
                    <item>Built Environment: Student training and historical work begins months
                        prior to our departure for Rome. Students are introduced to historical
                        texts, maps, and virtual exhibits of the locations we eventually
                        visit. </item>
                    <item>Narrative: Students are introduced to narrative concepts and theological
                        concepts that correspond to mediating structures–architecture, statuary,
                        art, texts--around Rome. We rely specifically on mobile storytelling
                        practices that prioritize the “location, including its histories, cultural
                        conflicts, communities, and architectures (to name only a few) and make
                        these aspects foundational for the experience of the space” (Farman
                        3).</item>
                    <item>Site-Specific Media Practice: Our final area of focus is an outgrowth of
                        combining site-specific media assignments in Rome with digital archival and
                        mapping technologies. Prior to our departure, students learn best practices
                        for organizing and archiving content on three platforms: Google Drive,
                        cPanel, and Omeka. Students are also introduced to video production and
                        editing technologies, while more advanced students focus on the production
                        of immersive 360º video. </item>
                </list>
                <p>On site, students collect data (geolocation, historical
                    information, images, and video) that are later archived and visualized. The
                    guiding questions above provide context in the media that students create and in
                    the archival descriptions of each object. Finally, the map acts as an
                    alternative visualization and interactive site that places student-made media in
                    its geographical location. Upon our return, editing our media and aggregating
                    our media objects into our Omeka archive allows students to critically reflect
                    on their experiences as they also contextualize those experiences for the
                    viewer/user.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Outcomes</head>
                <p>As part of our presentation, we will make our syllabi,
                    methods, and projects available to our audience and discuss the importance of
                    digital documentation projects that prioritize student-focused collaboration.
                    Our goal in this presentation is to outline our methodology and describe the
                    pedagogical situation in which the project is deployed. We will not only provide
                    examples of student-made media housed on our various maps, but demonstrate how
                    they work to synthesize site-specific cultural heritage experiences with
                    critical investigations of place and the materiality of religion in Rome as
                    expressed via digital narrative projects. Our work underscores how religious
                    studies, media production, and simple mapping techniques lead undergraduates to
                    view the importance of material mediation in the construction of narrative,
                    especially regarding history and theology.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliogr">
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <bibl>
                        <hi rend="bold">Ahmed, Manan, et al </hi>(25 June 2018): “Torn Apart /
                            Separados.” 
                        <hi rend="italic">Xpmethod</hi>
                        <ref target="https://xpmethod.columbia.edu/torn-apart/volume/2/">https://xpmethod.columbia.edu/torn-apart/volume/2/</ref>.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <hi rend="bold">Cantwell, Christopher D. </hi>“Gathering
                            Places.” 
                        <hi rend="italic">Gathering Places</hi>
                        , Golda Meir Library, 
                        <ref target="https://liblamp.uwm.edu/omeka/gatheringplaces/">https://liblamp.uwm.edu/omeka/gatheringplaces/</ref>.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <hi rend="bold">Clark, Emily Suzanne / Rachel McBride Lindsey</hi>
                            (2022): 
                        <hi rend="italic">Digital Humanities and Material
                            Religion: An Introduction.</hi>
                         De Gruyter.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <hi rend="bold">Farman, Jason </hi>(2014): 
                        <hi rend="italic">Mobile Story: Narrative Practices
                            with Locative Technologies</hi>
                        . Routledge. 
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <hi rend="bold">King, E. Frances </hi>(2009). 
                        <hi rend="italic">Material Religion and Popular
                            Culture.</hi>
                         Routledge.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <hi rend="bold">Nesbit, Scott / Edward L Ayers</hi>. “Visualizing
                            Emancipation.” 
                        <hi rend="italic">Visualizing Emancipation Archive
                            Site</hi>
                        , University of Richmond 
                        <ref target="https://dsl.richmond.edu/emancipation/">https://dsl.richmond.edu/emancipation/</ref>.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <hi rend="bold">Plate, S. Brent </hi>(2015). 
                        <hi rend="italic">Key Terms in Material Religion</hi>
                        . Bloomsbury.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <hi rend="bold">Williams, Hannah.</hi> 
                        <hi rend="italic">Artists in Paris</hi>
                        , The Leverhulme Trust and Queen Mary University
                            of London 
                        <ref target="https://www.artistsinparis.org/#@261848.15527273554,6250566.718238154&amp;z=13.00&amp;y=1675&amp;g=s,hp,p,gp,l,slp,e,o&amp;o=people-263">https://www.artistsinparis.org/#@261848.15527273554,6250566.718238154&amp;z=13.00&amp;y=1675&amp;g=s,hp,p,gp,l,slp,e,o&amp;o=people-263</ref>.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <hi rend="bold">Williams, Rowan, ed </hi>(2015): 
                        <hi rend="italic">Seeing Religion: Toward a Visual
                            Sociology of Religion.</hi>
                         Routledge.
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text></TEI>