<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_allPlus.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_allPlus.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Digital Edition of Complete Tolstoy's Heritage: OCR Crowd
                        Sourcing Initiative, Literary Scholarship and User Scenarios</title>
                <author n="BonchOsmolovskayaAnastasiaBONCH_OSMOLOVSKAYA_Anastasia_DIGITAL_EDITION_OF_COMPLETE_TOL.xml"><persName n="BonchOsmolovskayaAnastasia">
                        <surname>Bonch-Osmolovskaya</surname>
                        <forename>Anastasia</forename>
                    </persName><affiliation>DH CLOUD; TOLSTOY DIGITAL</affiliation><email>abonch@gmail.com</email></author><meeting><date from-iso="2023-07-10" to-iso="2023-07-14"/><title>Digital Humanities 2023. Collaboration as Opportunity</title><placeName>Graz</placeName></meeting>
                <author n="OrekhovBorisBONCH_OSMOLOVSKAYA_Anastasia_DIGITAL_EDITION_OF_COMPLETE_TOL.xml"><persName n="OrekhovBoris">
                        <surname>Orekhov</surname>
                        <forename>Boris</forename>
                    </persName><affiliation>DH CLOUD; Institute of Russian Literature (Pushkin House),
                        Russia</affiliation><email>nevmenandr@gmail.com</email></author><meeting><date from-iso="2023-07-10" to-iso="2023-07-14"/><title>Digital Humanities 2023. Collaboration as Opportunity</title><placeName>Graz</placeName></meeting>
                <author n="TolstayaFeklaBONCH_OSMOLOVSKAYA_Anastasia_DIGITAL_EDITION_OF_COMPLETE_TOL.xml"><persName n="TolstayaFekla">
                        <surname>Tolstaya</surname>
                        <forename>Fekla</forename>
                    </persName><affiliation>TOLSTOY DIGITAL</affiliation><email>6975991@gmail.com</email></author><meeting><date from-iso="2023-07-10" to-iso="2023-07-14"/><title>Digital Humanities 2023. Collaboration as Opportunity</title><placeName>Graz</placeName></meeting>
            </titleStmt>
            
            <publicationStmt><publisher><orgName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1137284463">Zentrum für Informationsmodellierung
                    - Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities, Karl-Franzens-Universität
                    Graz</orgName></publisher><date when="2023">2023</date><pubPlace>Graz</pubPlace><availability><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">Creative Commons BY
                    4.0</licence></availability></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title>Digital Humanities 2023: Book of Abstracts</title><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-9256-0958"><forename>Walter</forename><surname>Scholger</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>University of Graz</orgName><placeName>Graz, Austria</placeName></affiliation><email>walter.scholger@uni-graz.at</email></editor><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-1726-1712"><forename>Georg</forename><surname>Vogeler</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>University of Graz</orgName><placeName>Graz, Austria</placeName></affiliation><email>georg.vogeler@uni-graz.at</email></editor><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-3919-993X"><forename>Toma</forename><surname>Tasovac</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>Belgrade Center for Digital Humanities</orgName><placeName>Belgrade, Serbia</placeName></affiliation><email>ttasovac@humanistika.org</email></editor><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-4593-059X"><forename>Anne</forename><surname>Baillot</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>Le Mans Université</orgName><placeName>Le Mans, France</placeName></affiliation><email>anne.baillot@univ-lemans.fr</email></editor><respStmt><resp>Data Management</resp><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0009-0007-9019-8215"><forename>Elisabeth</forename><surname>Raunig</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Management</resp><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-1438-3236"><forename>Martina</forename><surname>Scholger</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Management</resp><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-9116-0402"><forename>Elisabeth</forename><surname>Steiner</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Curation</resp><persName><forename>Johanna</forename><surname>Ofenauer</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Curation</resp><persName><forename>Christina</forename><surname>Burgstaller</surname></persName></respStmt><idno type="DOI">10.5281/zenodo.7961822</idno></seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from an OASIS Open Document</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="DHCONVALIDATOR" version="1.22">
                    <label>DHConvalidator</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc><abstract><p>The paper presents digital edition of Tolstoy's heritage based on 90
                    complete edition, printed in mid 20th century. The paper describes the workflow
                    that has been chosen to deal with this immense cultural heritage and defines a
                    compromise between three objectives: presevation of Tolstoy's heritage,
                    preservation of literary scholar edition and digital user scenarios</p></abstract><langUsage><language ident="en">English</language></langUsage>
            <abstract>
                <p>The paper presents digital edition of Tolstoy's heritage based on 90
                    complete edition, printed in mid 20th century. The paper describes the workflow
                    that has been chosen to deal with this immense cultural heritage and defines a
                    compromise between three objectives: presevation of Tolstoy's heritage,
                    preservation of literary scholar edition and digital user scenarios</p>
            </abstract>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="category">
                    <term>Paper</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="subcategory">
                    <term>Long Presentation</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="keywords">
                    <term>Tolstoy</term>
                    <term>TEI</term>
                    <term>digital scholar edition</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="topics">
                    <term>crowdsourcing</term>
                    <term>scholarly editing and editions development</term>
                    <term>analysis</term>
                    <term>and methods</term>
                    <term>text encoding and markup language creation</term>
                    <term>deployment</term>
                    <term>and analysis</term>
                    <term>Literary studies</term>
                    
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <p>The publication of the 90-volume complete Tolstoy’s edition took thirty years
                (1928-1958). Despite the great effort put into the collection, the print run was
                small, making it a bibliographic rarity today. The edition contains more than 7.8
                mln words, or 44,350 pages of extraordinarily diverse text, and consists of three
                parts: Fiction and Essays, including previously unpublished versions and drafts
                (volumes 1-45), Tolstoy's Diaries (volumes 46-58), Tolstoy's Correspondence (59-90).
                In 2014 the Tolstoy Museum in Moscow and IT company, ABBYY, a leader in OCR
                technology launched a unique crowdsourcing project "All Tolstoy in one click". The
                90-volume edition was digitized using ABBYY's OCR technology and then proofread by
                thousands of volunteers from forty-nine countries within two weeks. The xml files
                that emerged from the crowdsourcing project gave birth to the idea of developing a
                fully-fledged digital edition of Tolstoy's heritage.</p>
            <p>The crucial conceptual decision we had to start was whether we stick with the
                90-volume publication as the material source, and create the digital version of the
                book, or we create a new digital edition of Tolstoy's heritage (Bonch-Osmolovskaya
                Skorinkin et al 2019). In this respect, digital output can pursue three goals, each
                of which has a direct influence on the final product:</p>
            <list type="ordered">
                <item>Preservation of Tolstoy's heritage, freed from the editorial construct of the
                    90-volume complete edition and open to further expansion by other
                    sources.</item>
                <item>Preservation of the enormous literary scholarship heritage, contained in the
                    90-volume edition in various critical apparatuses.</item>
                <item>Accessibility of Tolstoy's heritage to the digital user, which ultimately
                    means other scenarios of interaction with texts and their
                    interpretations.</item>
            </list>
            <p>These same three goals were set by the creators of the "91st volume" application,
                which implements in electronic form one part of the complete works of Tolstoy, an
                index to the edition (Orekhov et al. 2018, Orekhov 2020).</p>
            <p>The three goals are in fact in conflict, i.e. choosing only one of them would make it
                more difficult to fulfill the others. The first goal can be achieved, for example,
                by extracting only Tolstoy's text from the recognized OCR files. The second goal can
                best be achieved by creating a digital diplomatic edition (Pierazzo 2011). To
                achieve the third goal, one could, for example, skip the time-consuming phase of TEI
                preparation.</p>
            <p>We have worked out a compromise that strikes a balance between the three goals and so
                far protects each of them through a series of specific conceptual choices. </p>
            <list type="ordered">
                <item>We focus on Tolstoy’s digital heritage with 90-volume edition being the
                    primary, but not the only source. This means that we work with texts and not
                    with volumes. We extract all of Tolstoy's text and provide each document with
                    detailed metadata. We introduce the concept of a “family” of works, an abstract
                    unit that groups together all variants of a text (Robinson 2013) and
                    commentaries and other related works. The titles of all members of the family
                    are converted into a machine-readable format, to between Tolstoy’s original
                    titles from those assigned that have been given by the editors of a volume. Each
                    work in a family has a status tag that is used to create a hierarchy between the
                    main work and the different types of its variants. Finally, families themselves
                    can be linked if there is an important connection between them. The screenshot
                    below shows an example. <figure>
                        <graphic url="Pictures/c58f48f718325e25290190f520aa095a.png"/>
                        
                    </figure></item>
                <item>We carefully include all critical apparatus, presented in the 90-volume
                    edition. The printing practices of the mid-20th century involve certain reader
                    scenarios that should be transformed into digital scenarios. For example, the
                    index, which occupies a separate additional 91 volume, needs to be transformed
                    into a database linked to a text span rather than the pages of a volume
                    (Iglesia, Göbel 2015). The value of the index should not be underestimated: it
                    cannot be replaced by a NER algorithm. The index reflects years of thorough
                    editorial work aimed to clarify indirect mentions of people (Orekhov 2020). The
                    91 volume had not been proofread by volunteers and was, above all, full of OCR
                    errors. So first we parsed and corrected the index, converted it to a database,
                    assigned identifiers to each person entry and linked them to wikidata if
                    possible. Secondly, we used SpaCy NER to extract all the persons mentioned in
                    the documents and then automatically picked out the best candidates from the
                    database. We ranked the candidates with similarity weights and then manually
                    checked those whose weight was not 100%. </item>
                <item>We have developed user scenarios to navigate the vast Tolstoy heritage. For
                    example, we have simplified the genre system to 8 basic categories out of 28 in
                    the 90-volume edition, classified all persons from our index database with four
                    parameters: Occupation, Lifetime (ancient time, Tolstoy's predecessor, Tolstoy's
                    contemporary), Member of Tolstoy's family, Tolstoy's correspondent. We have
                    developed a web interface with a full-search in Tolstoy works, databases, and a
                    dictionary of rare words.</item>
            </list>
            <p>The essential idea that has guided our approaches and decisions is the idea of
                stages. The potential scope of the digital edition is so immense that we have been
                urged to plan our work so that each stage would lead to a finished product. The
                whole project consists of three stages: Digitalization, Creation of a digital
                scholarly edition, Creation an extended digital edition. The table below shows
                phases.</p>
            <table xml:id="d39e237">
                <head>Table 1:</head>
                <row>
                    <cell>Phase</cell>
                    <cell>Stage name</cell>
                    <cell>Goal: Tolstoy’s heritage</cell>
                    <cell>Goal: Literary scholarship</cell>
                    <cell>Goal: Digital scenarios</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>1</cell>
                    <cell>Digitalization of 90 volumes</cell>
                    <cell>
                        <p>-  volumes to docs;</p>
                        <p>-  extract all metadata</p>
                        <p>-  basic tei markup,</p>
                        <p> </p>
                    </cell>
                    <cell>- notes linking</cell>
                    <cell/>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>2</cell>
                    <cell>Digital scholarly edition</cell>
                    <cell>
                        <p>-complete tei mark-up</p>
                        <p>-families of works</p>
                    </cell>
                    <cell>
                        <p>- index parsing</p>
                        <p>- critical apparatus</p>
                    </cell>
                    <cell>
                        <p>- texts and person clasification</p>
                        <p>- web-portal for search and navigation in texts and reference lists</p>
                        <p> </p>
                    </cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>We are here</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>3</cell>
                    <cell>Digital edition of Tolstoy’s heritage</cell>
                    <cell>
                        <p>Introduction of new documents from other sources: manuscripts from
                            Tolstoy’s museums and archives, audiofiles, images etc.</p>
                        <p> </p>
                    </cell>
                    <cell>Extension of Tolstoy’s bibliography from other sources  </cell>
                    <cell>Development of new apps and websites on the basis of digitalized Tolstoy’s
                        heritage</cell>
                </row>
            </table>
            <p>All the tei documents are open access and can be found here <ref target="https://github.com/tolstoydigital/TEI">https://github.com/tolstoydigital/TEI</ref></p>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliogr">
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Bonch-Osmolovskaya, Anastasia, et al</author>
                        . (2019): 
                        “
                        Tolstoy semanticized:
                            Constructing a digital edition for knowledge discovery
                        ”, in: 
                        <hi rend="italic">Journal of Web
                            Semantics</hi>
                         59: 100483.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Iglesia, Martin de la</author> / <author>Göbel, Mathias</author> 
                        (2015): 
                        “
                        From entity description
                            to semantic analysis: The case of Theodor Fontane’s notebooks
                        ”, in: 
                        <hi rend="italic">The Linked TEI:
                            Text Encoding in the Web</hi>
                         21.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Orekhov Boris</author> / <author>Fischer, Frank</author> 
                        (2018):
                         The 91st Volume-How the
                            Digitised Index for the Collected Works of Leo Tolstoy Adds A New Angle
                            for Research
                        ”, in:
                        
                        <hi rend="italic">Digital Humanities
                            2018</hi>
                        . Puentes-Bridges. Book
                            of Abstracts: 465-466.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Orekhov, Boris </author>
                        (2020): 
                        “
                        "
                        Volume 91
                        "
                        : An electronic index to the complete works of Leo
                            Tolstoy
                        ”, in:
                        
                        <hi rend="italic">Journal of Siberian Federal University.
                            Humanities and social sciences.</hi>
                         12: 2049-2055. 
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Pierazzo, Elena</author>
                         (2011): 
                        “
                        A rationale of digital documentary editions
                        ”, in:
                        
                        <hi rend="italic">Literary and linguistic computing</hi>
                         26.4: 463-477.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Robinson, Peter</author>
                        
                        (2013): 
                        “
                        Towards a theory of
                            digital editions
                        ”, in:
                         
                        <hi rend="italic">The Journal of the
                            European Society for Textual Scholarship</hi>
                        : 105-131.
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text></TEI>