<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_allPlus.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_allPlus.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Exploring the Evolution of Curatorial Diversity: a Methodological Framework
                    with a Case Study of Book Reviews</title>
                <author n="CalderonReyesEmilioCALDERON_REYES_Emilio_Exploring_the_Evolution_of_Curatorial_.xml"><persName n="CalderonReyesEmilio">
                        <surname>Calderon Reyes</surname>
                        <forename>Emilio</forename>
                    </persName><affiliation>CulturePlex, Western University, Canada</affiliation><email>ecaldern@uwo.ca</email></author><meeting><date from-iso="2023-07-10" to-iso="2023-07-14"/><title>Digital Humanities 2023. Collaboration as Opportunity</title><placeName>Graz</placeName></meeting>
            </titleStmt>
            
            <publicationStmt><publisher><orgName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1137284463">Zentrum für Informationsmodellierung
                    - Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities, Karl-Franzens-Universität
                    Graz</orgName></publisher><date when="2023">2023</date><pubPlace>Graz</pubPlace><availability><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">Creative Commons BY
                    4.0</licence></availability></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title>Digital Humanities 2023: Book of Abstracts</title><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-9256-0958"><forename>Walter</forename><surname>Scholger</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>University of Graz</orgName><placeName>Graz, Austria</placeName></affiliation><email>walter.scholger@uni-graz.at</email></editor><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-1726-1712"><forename>Georg</forename><surname>Vogeler</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>University of Graz</orgName><placeName>Graz, Austria</placeName></affiliation><email>georg.vogeler@uni-graz.at</email></editor><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-3919-993X"><forename>Toma</forename><surname>Tasovac</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>Belgrade Center for Digital Humanities</orgName><placeName>Belgrade, Serbia</placeName></affiliation><email>ttasovac@humanistika.org</email></editor><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-4593-059X"><forename>Anne</forename><surname>Baillot</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>Le Mans Université</orgName><placeName>Le Mans, France</placeName></affiliation><email>anne.baillot@univ-lemans.fr</email></editor><respStmt><resp>Data Management</resp><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0009-0007-9019-8215"><forename>Elisabeth</forename><surname>Raunig</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Management</resp><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-1438-3236"><forename>Martina</forename><surname>Scholger</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Management</resp><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-9116-0402"><forename>Elisabeth</forename><surname>Steiner</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Curation</resp><persName><forename>Johanna</forename><surname>Ofenauer</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Curation</resp><persName><forename>Christina</forename><surname>Burgstaller</surname></persName></respStmt><idno type="DOI">10.5281/zenodo.7961822</idno></seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="DHCONVALIDATOR" version="1.22">
                    <label>DHConvalidator</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc><abstract><p>This presentation will define curational diversity based on cultural networks and a methodology to assess it. Additionally, the proposed methodology will be applied to conduct a longitudinal analysis of Boletín Cultural y Bibliográfico, a cultural magazine published by the Office of Cultural Affairs of Banco de la República de Colombia.</p></abstract><langUsage><language ident="en">English</language></langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="category">
                    <term>Paper</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="subcategory">
                    <term>Long Presentation</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="keywords">
                    <term>cultural networks</term>
                    <term>cultural diversity</term>
                    <term>content diversity</term>
                    <term>curated networks</term>
                    <term>cultural institutions</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="topics">
                    <term>cultural analytics</term>
                    <term>data modeling</term>
                    <term>network analysis and graphs theory and application</term>
                    <term>public humanities collaborations and methods</term>
                    <term>Chicano/a/x</term>
                    <term>Latino/a/x studies</term>
                    <term>Cultural studies</term>
                    <term>Humanities computing</term>
                    <term>Literary studies</term>
                    
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>Diversity, Equity, and Inclusion (DEI) as an organizational framework is on the rise and in Latin America it has permeated cultural institutions and public policies. In terms of the theory of cultural networks, curatorial diversity may be defined as the presence of variety, manifested in several dimensions, with respect to its actors, cultural objects, and connections. The proposed chapter presents a new cultural analytics methodology to examine curatorial diversity and exemplifies it with an analysis of 3,382 reviews of the <hi rend="italic">Cultural and Bibliographical Bulletin, </hi>a cultural magazine published by the Cultural Affairs
                        Department of the Bank of the Republic of Colombia (BanRepCultural).</p>
                <p>This research responds to the challenge of measuring diversity from a file when
                    it is not feasible to survey or interview the people involved, as is standard
                    practice in DEI's organizational culture methodologies (Romansky et al., 2021).
                    The proposal argues that, in the case of cultural institutions, curatorial
                    diversity can be valued both in deontological terms, in the sense that the offer
                    of a cultural institution must resemble the diversity of the society that
                    supports it, and utilitarian, since that a diverse cultural program helps
                    broaden cultural horizons and promotes cross-pollination in the arts.</p>
                <div>
                    <head>Methodology</head>
                    <p>This research proposes a cultural analytics methodology to analyze the
                        evolution, in the sense of change over time, of the curatorial diversity of
                        a cultural network. The methodology consists of five stages: (i) generate a
                        scheme of the network, (ii) select the dependent and independent variables,
                        (iii) acquire, process, and describe the dimensions of diversity, (iv)
                        analyze the correlations between the variables, (v) discuss the results.</p>
                    <p>The first phase of the methodology consists of conceiving a scheme of the
                        cultural network in which curatorial diversity will be analyzed. In this
                        phase, the context of the network is examined, its specific cultural domain
                        is delimited, the relationships that form its general structure are
                        described, and the information is consolidated in an ontology of a network
                        of cultural actors and objects (Suárez et al, 2015; Brown et al, 2016).</p>
                    <p>The second stage of the methodology is the
                            selection of variables. The independent variable is necessarily the unit
                            of time that delimits the periods in which the state or composition of
                            the network will be compared. Meanwhile, the dependent variables are the
                            dimensions of curatorial diversity that are of most interest considering
                            the context of the network and data availability. Typically, the
                            attributes of cultural objects refer to predominant themes, metadata, or
                            the medium, or technique of artistic expression, while the attributes of
                            actors identify them in demographic or professional terms. When
                            selecting attributes, the potential risks to actors of having their data
                            collected should be weighed, especially when the data identifies members
                            of groups that have been subjected to systematic discrimination
                            (D'Ignazio and Klein, 2020, p 112).</p>
                    <p>In the third phase a network database is created by extracting, cleaning and
                        preprocessing data. The obtained data is then examined for completeness and
                        reliability, and the diversity of each attribute is described in terms of
                        variety and balance using statistics such as proportion, standard deviation,
                        mean, Shannon entropy, and Simpson's index of diversity (Budescu and
                        Budescu, 2012).</p>
                    <p>The fourth phase of the methodology focuses on analyzing whether the
                        evolution of the dimensions of the network's curatorial diversity has been a
                        stationary process or not stationary. This involves establishing the
                        regression that best fits the temporal distribution of each of the diversity
                        dimensions, deciding how to evaluate whether the distribution is stationary
                        or not stationary, and formulating the respective null and alternative
                        hypotheses.</p>
                    <p>The proposed methodology closes with a discussion of the results focused on
                        their interpretation considering the historical context and representative
                        examples. It is especially important that the discussion raises the
                        identified limitations, especially in relation to the dimensions of
                        diversity of interest excluded due to lack of data, ethical considerations,
                        or other reasons.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Case study: Cultural and Bibliographic Bulletin</head>
                <p>Established in 1958, the Cultural and Bibliographic Bulletin is a magazine focused on investigating and disseminating Colombian cultural heritage. The complete digital archive of the magazine is available, and it reached more than 180,000 visits in 2021. This case was chosen to exemplify the methodology because BanRepCultural is a well-recognized cultural institution in Latin America that mentions diversity in its mission statement. This case focuses on the <hi rend="italic">Boletín Cultural y Bibliográfico</hi> book reviews because they are an intuitive starting point for generating a base network scheme that consistently involves more actors and cultural objects (Figure 1).</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic n="1001" width="16.002cm" height="3.6671222222222224cm" url="Pictures/22e4a3685e1127315b96f42f2750196d.png" rend="inline"/>
                </figure>
                <p>Preliminary results suggest that the dimensions of curatorial diversity
                    considered have followed different processes. The diversity in terms of the
                    place of publication of the reviewed works is the clearest example of a
                    stationary process, and every year more than half of the books reviewed were
                    published in Bogotá. On the other hand, the gender distribution of the authors
                    of the reviewed works more clearly follows a non-stationary process. While in no
                    year has the gender diversity of authors approached parity, this gap has been
                    narrowing over time.</p>
                <p>In a rapidly digitizing world, the relevance of cultural institutions depends on
                    their ability to cater to the changing needs and preferences of users and adapt
                    to a dynamic cultural ecosystem. Building on Scott Page's (2008, 2011) research
                    on the value of diversity in complex adaptive systems, it would be especially
                    relevant for cultural institutions that are adopting networked models of
                    organization to develop systems to account for the specific ways in which
                    diversity is related to its main mission.</p>
                <p>Measuring curatorial diversity will allow new
                        explorations of the connections between cultural objects and the actors that
                        make up a cultural network. The proposed methodology could be adapted to
                        account for the curatorial diversity of future publications, providing
                        managers, curators, and the public with measures to check whether
                        institutions are offering programming. culture aligned with its diversity
                        statements.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliogr">
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <bibl><author>Brown D., Soto, A., Suárez, J.S., de la Rosa, J. Overview</author>: The Social
                        Media Data Processing Pipeline. Chapter in The Sage Handbook of Social Media
                        Research Methods. Sage, pp. 125-147.</bibl>
                    <bibl><author>Budescu, D. V., &amp; Budescu, M. </author>(2012). How to measure diversity when
                        you must. Psychological Methods, 17(2), 215-227.</bibl>
                    <bibl><author>D’Ignazio, C., Klein, L. F. </author>(2020). Data feminism. The MIT Press.</bibl>
                    <bibl><author>Page, S.</author> (2008). The Difference: How the Power of Diversity Creates Better
                        Groups, Firms, Schools, and Societies. Princeton University Press,
                        https://doi.org/10.1515/9781400830282</bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Page, S. </author>(2011). 
                        <hi rend="italic">Diversity and
                            complexity</hi>
                        . Princeton University
                            Press. https://doi.org/10.1515/9
                        781400835140
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <hi rend="bold">Suárez, J.S., McArthur, 
                            B.,Soto-Corominas, A.</hi>. Cultural Networks and the Future of Cultural
                            Analytics. Proceedings of the 2015 International Conference on Culture
                            and Computing. Kyoto University. 
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl><author>Romansky, L., Garrod, M., Brown, K., Deo, K.</author> (2021). How to Measure
                        Inclusion in the Workplace. Harvard Business Review. </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text></TEI>