<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_allPlus.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_allPlus.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Visualizing and Analyzing Voting Records from Historical Documents</title>
                <author n="CantareiraGabrielDiasCANTAREIRA_Gabriel_Visualizing_and_Analyzing_Voting_Records_.xml"><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-5257-4925" n="CantareiraGabrielDias">
                        <surname>Cantareira</surname>
                        <forename>Gabriel Dias</forename>
                    </persName><affiliation>King's College London, United Kingdom</affiliation><email>gabriel.dias_cantareira@kcl.ac.uk</email></author><meeting><date from-iso="2023-07-10" to-iso="2023-07-14"/><title>Digital Humanities 2023. Collaboration as Opportunity</title><placeName>Graz</placeName></meeting>
                <author n="ColeNicholasCANTAREIRA_Gabriel_Visualizing_and_Analyzing_Voting_Records_.xml"><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-6676-5343" n="ColeNicholas">
                        <surname>Cole</surname>
                        <forename>Nicholas</forename>
                    </persName><affiliation>Oxford University</affiliation><email>nicholas.cole@history.ox.ac.uk</email></author><meeting><date from-iso="2023-07-10" to-iso="2023-07-14"/><title>Digital Humanities 2023. Collaboration as Opportunity</title><placeName>Graz</placeName></meeting>
                <author n="AbdulRahmanAlfieCANTAREIRA_Gabriel_Visualizing_and_Analyzing_Voting_Records_.xml"><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-6257-876X" n="AbdulRahmanAlfie">
                        <surname>Abdul-Rahman</surname>
                        <forename>Alfie</forename>
                    </persName><affiliation>King's College London, United Kingdom</affiliation><email>alfie.abdulrahman@kcl.ac.uk</email></author><meeting><date from-iso="2023-07-10" to-iso="2023-07-14"/><title>Digital Humanities 2023. Collaboration as Opportunity</title><placeName>Graz</placeName></meeting>
            </titleStmt>
            
            <publicationStmt><publisher><orgName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1137284463">Zentrum für Informationsmodellierung
                    - Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities, Karl-Franzens-Universität
                    Graz</orgName></publisher><date when="2023">2023</date><pubPlace>Graz</pubPlace><availability><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">Creative Commons BY
                    4.0</licence></availability></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title>Digital Humanities 2023: Book of Abstracts</title><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-9256-0958"><forename>Walter</forename><surname>Scholger</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>University of Graz</orgName><placeName>Graz, Austria</placeName></affiliation><email>walter.scholger@uni-graz.at</email></editor><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-1726-1712"><forename>Georg</forename><surname>Vogeler</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>University of Graz</orgName><placeName>Graz, Austria</placeName></affiliation><email>georg.vogeler@uni-graz.at</email></editor><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-3919-993X"><forename>Toma</forename><surname>Tasovac</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>Belgrade Center for Digital Humanities</orgName><placeName>Belgrade, Serbia</placeName></affiliation><email>ttasovac@humanistika.org</email></editor><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-4593-059X"><forename>Anne</forename><surname>Baillot</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>Le Mans Université</orgName><placeName>Le Mans, France</placeName></affiliation><email>anne.baillot@univ-lemans.fr</email></editor><respStmt><resp>Data Management</resp><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0009-0007-9019-8215"><forename>Elisabeth</forename><surname>Raunig</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Management</resp><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-1438-3236"><forename>Martina</forename><surname>Scholger</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Management</resp><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-9116-0402"><forename>Elisabeth</forename><surname>Steiner</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Curation</resp><persName><forename>Johanna</forename><surname>Ofenauer</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Curation</resp><persName><forename>Christina</forename><surname>Burgstaller</surname></persName></respStmt><idno type="DOI">10.5281/zenodo.7961822</idno></seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="DHCONVALIDATOR" version="1.22">
                    <label>DHConvalidator</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc><abstract><p>In this submission, we present a set of tools for analyzing voting historical records for consitutional conventions extending the Quill research platform and discuss challenges in interacting with this data, focusing on selecting appropriate sampling, dealing with incomplete data, and building an analytical model.</p></abstract><langUsage><language ident="en">English</language></langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="category">
                    <term>Paper</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="subcategory">
                    <term>Long Presentation</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="keywords">
                    <term>Voting</term>
                    <term>Dimensionality Reduction</term>
                    <term>Timelines</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="topics">
                    <term>Interface design</term>
                    <term>development</term>
                    <term>and analysis</term>
                    <term>History</term>
                    <term>Humanities computing</term>
                    
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div type="div1">
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <p>The Quill Project (Cole et al. 2017) is a research initiative that investigates
                    text analysis and data visualization with the aim of assisting users in
                    understanding modern foundational legal texts and constitutional conventions.
                    Quill contains multiple well-organized datasets built on an event-based
                    structure, representing the negotiation of legal texts during legislative
                    drafting for constitutional conventions - processes that can last for several
                    months or years. As each discussed text is the result of hundreds of amendments
                    proposed by several actors over an extended period of time, visual presentation
                    and navigation can become quite difficult.</p>
                <p>In this submission, we expand the Quill platform to add features focused on
                    extracting meaningful knowledge from what Quill classifies as decisions: changes
                    or additions that required voting by the attending participants, to which votes
                    and outcome are documented. For each decision, it is possible to track people
                    involved, how they voted, and which other events are related to it. This
                    information can be used to explore the historical context for behavior observed
                    in voting data. We can subdivide our course of action and challenges into three
                    tasks: finding appropriate time windows for observation, dealing with missing or
                    incomplete data, and building an analytical model to observe relevant features
                    and draw conclusions.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="div1">
                <head>Finding Appropriate Time Windows</head>
                <p>While the use of visualization techniques to observe voting behavior and
                    political positioning is relatively well-established (da Silva et al. 2018),
                    most existing approaches assume there is a semantically appropriate temporal
                    sampling structure available, i.e., time windows to observe and compare voting
                    records are already well defined by historical context. We argue that it is
                    important for a visualization system to be able to work in both directions:
                    users can employ their expertise to select historically relevant dates to
                    observe, but should also be able to use the system to identify noteworthy
                    behavior that could then be traced back to historical events. In the same
                    manner, the size and number of samples to visualize is also important: when
                    visualizing relationships between voters, the entire timespan of the dataset
                    could be viewed as a single sample, but changes that occur inside this timespan
                    will not be easily observable; alternatively, using every single decision as an
                    individual sample would result in hundreds of visualizations to be compared,
                    which is impractical. Therefore, our aim is to aid users in selecting a low
                    number of samples that contain a high amount of variance to one another.</p>
                <p>We navigate through this matter using two approaches: the first is to generate a
                    summarized representation of the whole timeline as to when decisions occur and
                    which type they belong to. Users may interact with them and obtain further
                    details, which can also be used to filter the data to be visualized. The second
                    approach is to estimate overall behavior changes over time: groups of people
                    that voted in agreement but started to vote in opposition, and vice-versa. This
                    is done by comparing the differences in pairwise relationships between each
                    voter, using the decisions within the selected time windows as multiple
                    dimensions.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic n="1001" width="16.002cm" height="6.69925cm" url="Pictures/8ad0278246511da18b35093a0846f715.png" rend="inline"/>
                    
                </figure>
                <figure>
                    <graphic n="1002" width="16.002cm" height="12.855222222222222cm" url="Pictures/575a2908a9caa2235e10cd8b26620a6f.png" rend="inline"/>
                    
                </figure>
                <figure>
                    <graphic n="1003" width="16.002cm" height="13.096875cm" url="Pictures/2fa161a51ba034ab5cd801aa21371528.png" rend="inline"/>
                    
                </figure>
            </div>
            <div type="div1">
                <head>Dealing With Missing or Incomplete Data</head>
                <p>A fundamental challenge in working with historical records is data inconsistency.
                    Records can be incomplete or noisy, either due to being lost to time, damaged,
                    or never being kept in the first place. In Quill voting records, not all
                    decisions contain recorded votes. Many of them are identified as anonymous, to
                    which no votes were publicly cast. For others, minutes and drafted documents may
                    reveal causes for such absence, such as a decision being an unanimous agreement
                    without a need for casting individual votes.</p>
                <p>In the sense of observing relationships between voters, decisions with no
                    recorded votes offer no data for visualization. However, we can still use their
                    metadata and related information to provide context and insights to users.
                    Showing the distribution between anonymous and non-anonymous voting can provide
                    insights into periods of contention; cross-referencing decision outcomes to the
                    person that made the proposal can hint at the overall popularity of different
                    people. There is also relevant information in outliers: a vote may look atypical
                    for a person or group for a variety of reasons, and data errors are a
                    possibility.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic n="1004" width="16.002cm" height="5.254625cm" url="Pictures/4318283b2eaf1477ed362eb84cc78cdc.png" rend="inline"/>
                    
                </figure>
            </div>
            <div type="div1">
                <head>Building an Analytical Model</head>
                <p>Once time windows of interest are found and samples are defined, we can then
                    observe them further using computational methods. For this application, we use
                    Principal Component Analysis (PCA) to display all voters as dots in a
                    scatterplot. A PCA projection aims to encode the maximum possible amount of
                    covariance within each dimension without distortion, showing trends and
                    correlation between data points as explicitly as possible. This means voters
                    with similar behavior during the selected time window will be shown close
                    together, while dissimilar voters will be shown far apart.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic n="1005" width="16.002cm" height="7.395986111111111cm" url="Pictures/7ad144d017b258674beb731ec484dbd4.png" rend="inline"/>
                    
                </figure>
                <p>There are other projection techniques that can be used in this application –
                    particularly, non-linear methods such as t-SNE and UMAP (Espadoto et al. 2019)
                    can generate accurate neighborhood representations from complex data. However,
                    as PCA is a linear transformation, we can use its features to gather information
                    on the actual meaning of geometric positioning for data: coefficients from PCA
                    analysis inform the influence of each decision on the visualization’s axes, and
                    an explanation can be given for the position of voters in the scatterplot.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic n="1006" width="16.002cm" height="4.690180555555555cm" url="Pictures/3482de0dc619e577fda16012e7c08cd9.png" rend="inline"/>
                    
                </figure>
                <p>To enhance this visualization, we can superpose another projection from a
                    different time window and observe changes between the two. Voters with the most
                    expressive changes can be quickly identified, and details on their behavior can
                    be further explored. Normally, two distinct PCA projections do not have
                    comparable spaces; we employ Procrustes analysis to adapt the second projection
                    to the first as much as possible, aiming to highlight differences between the
                    two.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic n="1007" width="16.002cm" height="13.954125cm" url="Pictures/6dd989c813a6ef3d296145e80ee814b0.png" rend="inline"/>
                    
                </figure>
            </div>
            <div type="div1">
                <head>Conclusion</head>
                <p>Voting records may offer important knowledge on relationships and trends among
                    people or organizations in historical data, and visualization tools provide
                    powerful means to navigate through their features. In this submission, we
                    present tools to be used in this context and discuss their application in the
                    Quill platform, discussing sampling, data availability and presentation.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliogr">
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Cole, Nicholas</author> / <author>Abdul-Rahman, Alfie</author> / <author>Mallon, Grace</author> 
                        (2017): “Quill: A framework for constructing negotiated texts-with a case
                        study on the us constitutional convention of 1787”. <hi rend="italic">2017
                            ACM/IEEE Joint Conference on Digital Libraries</hi> (JCDL): 1-10. IEEE. </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>da Silva, Rodrigo N. M.</author> / <author>Spritzer, André S.</author> / <author>Freitas, Carla M. D. S.</author> (2018):
                        “Visualization of roll call data for supporting analyses of political
                        profiles”.
                        <hi rend="italic"> 31st SIBGRAPI Conference on Graphics, Patterns and Images</hi>
                        (SIBGRAPI): 150-157. IEEE. </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Espadoto, Matheus</author> / <author>Martins, Rafael M.</author> / <author>Kerren, Andreas</author> / <author>Hirata, Nina S. T.</author> / <author>Telea, Alexandru C.</author>  (2019): “Toward a
                        quantitative survey of dimension reduction techniques”.
                        <hi rend="italic">IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics </hi>27,
                        3: 2153-2173. IEEE. </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text></TEI>