<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_allPlus.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_allPlus.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Link Visions Together: Visualizing Geographies of Late Qing and Republican
                    China</title>
                <author n="CheQunCHE_Qun_Link_Visions_Together__Visualizing_Geographies_of_La.xml"><persName n="CheQun">
                        <surname>Che</surname>
                        <forename>Qun</forename>
                    </persName><affiliation>Shanghai Jiao Tong University, China, People's Republic
                        of</affiliation><email>chequn@sjtu.edu.cn</email></author><meeting><date from-iso="2023-07-10" to-iso="2023-07-14"/><title>Digital Humanities 2023. Collaboration as Opportunity</title><placeName>Graz</placeName></meeting>
                <author n="LinNungyaoCHE_Qun_Link_Visions_Together__Visualizing_Geographies_of_La.xml"><persName n="LinNungyao">
                        <surname>Lin</surname>
                        <forename>Nungyao</forename>
                    </persName><affiliation>Taipei Palace Museum, Taiwan</affiliation><email>nungyao@gmail.com</email></author><meeting><date from-iso="2023-07-10" to-iso="2023-07-14"/><title>Digital Humanities 2023. Collaboration as Opportunity</title><placeName>Graz</placeName></meeting>
                <author n="ChenShihPeiCHE_Qun_Link_Visions_Together__Visualizing_Geographies_of_La.xml"><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-5930-4736" n="ChenShihPei">
                        <surname>Chen</surname>
                        <forename>Shih-Pei</forename>
                    </persName><affiliation>Max Planck Institute for the History of Science</affiliation><email>schen@mpiwg-berlin.mpg.de</email></author><meeting><date from-iso="2023-07-10" to-iso="2023-07-14"/><title>Digital Humanities 2023. Collaboration as Opportunity</title><placeName>Graz</placeName></meeting>
                <author n="YehCalvinCHE_Qun_Link_Visions_Together__Visualizing_Geographies_of_La.xml"><persName n="YehCalvin">
                        <surname>Yeh</surname>
                        <forename>Calvin</forename>
                    </persName><affiliation>Max Planck Institute for the History of Science</affiliation><email>cyeh@mpiwg-berlin.mpg.de</email></author><meeting><date from-iso="2023-07-10" to-iso="2023-07-14"/><title>Digital Humanities 2023. Collaboration as Opportunity</title><placeName>Graz</placeName></meeting>
            </titleStmt>
            
            <publicationStmt><publisher><orgName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1137284463">Zentrum für Informationsmodellierung
                    - Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities, Karl-Franzens-Universität
                    Graz</orgName></publisher><date when="2023">2023</date><pubPlace>Graz</pubPlace><availability><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">Creative Commons BY
                    4.0</licence></availability></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title>Digital Humanities 2023: Book of Abstracts</title><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-9256-0958"><forename>Walter</forename><surname>Scholger</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>University of Graz</orgName><placeName>Graz, Austria</placeName></affiliation><email>walter.scholger@uni-graz.at</email></editor><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-1726-1712"><forename>Georg</forename><surname>Vogeler</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>University of Graz</orgName><placeName>Graz, Austria</placeName></affiliation><email>georg.vogeler@uni-graz.at</email></editor><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-3919-993X"><forename>Toma</forename><surname>Tasovac</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>Belgrade Center for Digital Humanities</orgName><placeName>Belgrade, Serbia</placeName></affiliation><email>ttasovac@humanistika.org</email></editor><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-4593-059X"><forename>Anne</forename><surname>Baillot</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>Le Mans Université</orgName><placeName>Le Mans, France</placeName></affiliation><email>anne.baillot@univ-lemans.fr</email></editor><respStmt><resp>Data Management</resp><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0009-0007-9019-8215"><forename>Elisabeth</forename><surname>Raunig</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Management</resp><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-1438-3236"><forename>Martina</forename><surname>Scholger</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Management</resp><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-9116-0402"><forename>Elisabeth</forename><surname>Steiner</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Curation</resp><persName><forename>Johanna</forename><surname>Ofenauer</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Curation</resp><persName><forename>Christina</forename><surname>Burgstaller</surname></persName></respStmt><idno type="DOI">10.5281/zenodo.7961822</idno></seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="DHCONVALIDATOR" version="1.22">
                    <label>DHConvalidator</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc><abstract><p>This paper aims to elucidate the origin and metadata of land surveying maps, which meticulously document the landforms and features of various regions across mainland China between 1895 and 1944. Additionally, the digitization process of this research will be outlined. Furthermore, this paper will introduce the user interface of CHMap from two perspectives: firstly, CHMap as a platform for land survey maps, and secondly, CHMap as a tool for linking maps and images from disparate eras and sources.</p></abstract><langUsage><language ident="en">English</language></langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="category">
                    <term>Paper</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="subcategory">
                    <term>Long Presentation</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="keywords">
                    <term>Historical Maps; WMTS; IIIF; Land Survey Maps</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="topics">
                    <term>digital publishing projects</term>
                    <term>systems</term>
                    <term>and methods</term>
                    <term>digital research infrastructures development and analysis</term>
                    <term>Interface design</term>
                    <term>development</term>
                    <term>and analysis</term>
                    <term>spatial &amp; spatio-temporal analysis</term>
                    <term>modeling and visualization</term>
                    <term>Geography and geo-humanities</term>
                    <term>History</term>
                    <term>History of science</term>
                    <term>Humanities computing</term>
                    
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p> Since the late 19th century, the Qing, the Beiyang, and the subsequent Nanjing
                    Nationalist government of China began systematically conducting land surveying
                    and mapping across the state. The land surveying was based on the triangular
                    projection, a western imported technology. It was conducted on a large scale
                    (1/50,000 &amp; 1/25,000) that provides in detail the street outlines of towns
                    and cities. Around the same time, Japan used similar methods to carry out
                    cartographic work in the Far East, including China, resulting in the first known
                    set of systematic, large-scale coverage, high-precision maps of significant
                    China territory.</p>
                <p> This paper will explain the origin and metadata, and digitization of this set of
                    maps. Then introduce the user interface of CHMap from two aspects: CHMap as a
                    carrier of land survey maps and as a tool for linking maps and images from
                    different eras and sources. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>The origin and digitization process of land surveying maps</head>
                <p> According to the <hi rend="italic">Comprehensive Index of Chinese Mainland
                        Atlases</hi>, it is currently known that this set of land surveying maps
                    contains four parts: 4,088 1/50,000 maps of mainland China, 754 1/25,000 maps of
                    Manchuria, 1689 1/25,000 and 2295 1/50,000 maps of mainland China. The former
                    three parts have been published by Kagakusion. The last set collected by
                    Academia Sinica has been partially digitized and released through WMTS (Web Map
                    Tile Service) for users to load and read from GIS software. </p>
                <p> So far, what has been digitized is the <hi rend="italic">Chinese Mainland
                        Atlases (1:50,000).</hi> From 1986 to 1998, this atlas was published with
                    black and white photocopies and contains 4088 maps with metadata including when
                    and who conducted the survey and platemaking. This set of maps records in detail
                    the landforms and features of parts of mainland China from 1895 to 1944,
                    including mountains and lakes, traffic routes, administrative division
                    boundaries, crops, windmills, watermills, soil worship, ancestral halls,
                    temples, and cultural relics. The map’s content is very informative and makes it
                    precious historical material for studying natural and social changes during
                    Republican China. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>CHMap as the Carrier of Land Survey Maps</head>
                <p> CHMap is developed based on leaflet.js, an open-source JavaScript library of web
                    map applications, eligible for the long-term operation of this project. Leaflet
                    allows for essential map display functions, such as dragging, zooming,
                    referencing third-party resources, etc. We published the georeferenced digital
                    maps through WMTS and then loaded them into the CHMap user interface, thus
                    forming the prototype of CHMap.</p>
                <p>The architecture of CHMap provides data-to-software and data-to-web connectivity,
                    distinguished from API’s software-to-software model. It breaks the traditional
                    user-to-software model while lowering the threshold for user participation and
                    has good scalability, which prompts us to consider the possibility of
                    incorporating more image ontologies into CHMap for comparative research. We
                    expect that CHMap can not only achieve efficient, cross-platform, and
                    barrier-free sharing of these maps but also provide a digital ecosystem to help
                    users connect to more external data and share the data served or processed by
                    the CHMap platform with third-party platforms or software, to realize the use of
                    geography as a bridge to communicate images and data of different sources.</p>
                <p>For this purpose, we have collected many external open map layers published in
                    the form of WMTS, such as the land survey maps released by Academia Sinica,
                    historical maps of China's dynasties, the CHGIS historical maps, etc. In
                    addition, we have developed a "query by location" function for CHMap. It allows
                    users to place a marker, search for if any external open maps exist according to
                    the marker’s location, and reference them to the CHMap interface.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>CHMap as a Tool for Linking Visions</head>
                <p>We expect CHMap can promote the sharing and interoperability of geographic data
                    and image resources, connect more external data, and meet the needs of
                    personalized and customized spatial cognition. For geographic data, we have
                    adopted the WMTS; and in the area of image resources, we have seen IIIF 's
                    Emergence. With the framework, images can be referenced and interoperable across
                    platforms.</p>
                <p> Images of the IIIF standard can be referenced to the CHMap platform. With IIIF
                    Viewer, users can view metadata and spatially process them. We divide IIIF
                    images into two categories: maps and pictures other than maps, such as books,
                    manuscripts, newspapers, paintings, etc., which may have spatial geographic
                    information but cannot be georeferenced like maps. For the former, CHMap
                    provides a georeferencing tool; for the latter, the tool also supports setting
                    them in the place their spatial attributes claim. The spatially processed images
                    on the CHMap platform can be saved locally in the format of GeoIIIF JSON, sent
                    to the third party’s server, or shared with other software and platforms that
                    support the standard. </p>
                <p>By opening up to mainstream standard images, maps, and application
                    interoperability frameworks, CHMap enables users to place images, maps, and
                    personal data scattered in various collection institutions worldwide on one
                    platform for comparative research. At the same time, CHMap supports data
                    transfer and seamless connection with other software or related platforms. In
                    this way, we expect CHMap to serve as a link in the interoperability of
                    distributed image and geographic information data.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Spatial Epistemology: A Case of the Application of CHMap</head>
                <p> Since 2014, Dep. III of MPIWG has developed a set of research tools, “LoGaRT,”
                    for Chinese local gazetteers, which can assist scholars in using these materials
                    through a holistic lens. In 2018, MPIWG invited four scholars to jointly
                    participate in a research project—using LoGaRT to explore image materials in
                    local gazetteers, including cityscapes, rituals, artifacts, astrological charts,
                    hydrology, and modern surveying maps to explore specific topics of indigenous
                    knowledge in history.</p>
                <p> CHMap’s incorporation of local gazetteer images differs from the typical
                    historical image display method. First, due to the inherent regional
                    characteristics of local gazetteers, these images naturally have coordinates
                    information so that they can be geolocated and generate geographic
                    visualization. CHMap is equipped with 4088 Maps, which can serve as a control
                    group or baseline for scholars to comparatively observe these images of
                    different periods and social and cultural backgrounds and explore people's
                    understanding and presentation of their own living spaces in different periods.
                    It can be conveniently found on CHMap that the spatial description of Shaoxing
                    City in the 17 <hi rend="superscript">th</hi>-century local gazetteer and the
                    land survey map in the early 20th century. Comparing the two can deepen the
                    researchers' cognition and understanding of diachronic locality. It can be
                    combined with personalized spatial geographic data applicable to CHMap and image
                    data from other sources to better understand research objects' spatial
                    commonality or heterogeneity. </p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliogr">
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <bibl>
                        <hi rend="SimSun">张晓虹,王均.中国近代测绘机构与地图管理</hi>[M].<hi rend="SimSun">历史地理</hi>:18<hi rend="SimSun">辑,上海:上海人民出版社</hi>,2002. </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <hi rend="SimSun">任玉雪,邓发晖.《中国大陆五万分之一地图集成》所收地图来源分析</hi>[J].<hi rend="SimSun">历史地理研究</hi>,2020,40(3):132-142+156. </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <hi rend="SimSun">中国地図資料研究会,陸地測量部.中国大陸五万分の一地図集成</hi>:8<hi rend="SimSun">巻</hi>[M]<hi rend="SimSun">東京:科学書院</hi>, 1986-1998. </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <hi rend="SimSun">中国地図資料研究会,陸地測量部.中国大陸二万五千分の一地図集成</hi>[M].<hi rend="SimSun">東京:科学書院</hi>,1989-1993. </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <hi rend="SimSun">中国地図資料研究会,陸地測量部.旧満州五万分の一地図集成</hi>[M].<hi rend="SimSun">東京:科学書院</hi>,1985. </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <hi rend="SimSun">科学書院.中国大陸五万分の一地図集成総合索引</hi>[M]. <hi rend="SimSun">東京:科学書院</hi>,1994. </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <hi rend="SimSun">外邦図について</hi>[EB/OL].[2021-03-15].
                        https://www.lib.ocha.ac.jp/gaihouzu/gaihozuocha.html. </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Tanak A.</author> Imperial Japanese army map collection at
                        University of Washington [EB/OL]. The 26th annual conference of the EAJRS,
                            <ref target="https://www.google.com/maps/place/%E3%82%AA%E3%83%A9%E3%83%B3%E3%83%80+%E3%83%A9%E3%82%A4%E3%83%87%E3%83%B3/@52.109718,4.4356216,10z/data=%214m2%213m1%211s0x47c5c68b88c9d753:0x74076352baf3fe49?hl=ja"> Leiden </ref> , The Netherlands, 16–19 September 2015.
                        [2021-03-15].https://www.eajrs.net/files/happyo/tanaka_azusa_15.pdf. </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Kobayashi S.</author> Japanese mapping of Asia-Pacific areas,
                        1873-1945: an overview [J]. <hi rend="italic">Cross-currents: East Asian
                            history and culture review</hi> 1, 2012(1): 137-171. </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Stuart S, Sanderson R, Cramer T.</author> The International
                        Image Interoperability Framework (IIIF): a community &amp; technology
                        approach for web-based images[J]. <hi rend="italic">Archiving
                            conference</hi> , 2015(1): 16-21. </bibl>
                    <bibl> Explore illuminated manuscripts from the national libraries of the UK and
                        France[EB/OL].[2021-03-15].
                        https://www.bl.uk/medieval-english-french-manuscripts. </bibl>
                    <bibl> Explore 800 medieval manuscripts of France and
                        England[EB/OL]. [2021-03-15]. https://manuscrits-france-angleterre.org/polonsky/en/content/accueil-en?mode=desktop. </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Fleet C, Kimberly C K, Přidal Petr</author>. Georeferencer:
                        crowdsourced georeferencing for map library collections[J]. D-Lib
                        magazine,2012,18: 52. </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Marx K, Engels F.</author> Selected works in three
                        volumes：Vol.1[M]. Moscow: Progress, 1969:32. </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <hi rend="SimSun">盛宁.人文困惑与反思——西方后现代主义思潮批判</hi>[M].<hi rend="SimSun">北京:三联书店</hi>,1997:75. </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Warf B.</author> Space and Social Theory in Geography[M].
                        Smelser N J, Baltes P B. International encyclopedia of the social &amp;
                        behavioral sciences, Amsterdam,New York: Elsevier, 2001:82-88. </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Lefebvre, H. Nicholson-Smith D</author>,trans.. The production
                        of space[M]. Oxford: Blackwell, 1991:117. </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Bruno B.</author> Nonplaces: an anecdoted topography of
                        contemporary French theory[J]. Diacritics, 2003,33:117-139. </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Bleakly D R</author>. Long-term spatial data preservation and
                        archiving: what are the issues[R].SAND report,2002:107. </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>LoGaRT</author>: Local Gazetteers Research Tools[EB/OL].
                        [2021-03-15].https://www.mpiwg-berlin.mpg.de/research/projects/logart-local-gazetteers-research-tools。
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text></TEI>