<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_allPlus.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_allPlus.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>AudiAnnotate Workshop with Radio Venceremos, Rebel Radio Station and
                    SpokenWeb: Using IIIF with AV to Build Editions and Exhibits.</title>
                <author n="ClementTanyaCLEMENT_Tanya_AudiAnnotate_Workshop_with_Radio_Venceremos__R.xml"><persName n="ClementTanya">
                        <surname>Clement</surname>
                        <forename>Tanya</forename>
                    </persName><affiliation>University of Texas, United States of America</affiliation><email>tclement@utexas.edu</email></author><meeting><date from-iso="2023-07-10" to-iso="2023-07-14"/><title>Digital Humanities 2023. Collaboration as Opportunity</title><placeName>Graz</placeName></meeting>
                <author n="BursztajnIllingworthZoeCLEMENT_Tanya_AudiAnnotate_Workshop_with_Radio_Venceremos__R.xml"><persName n="BursztajnIllingworthZoe">
                        <surname>Bursztajn-Illingworth</surname>
                        <forename>Zoe</forename>
                    </persName><affiliation>University of Texas, United States of America</affiliation><email>zbi@utexas.edu</email></author><meeting><date from-iso="2023-07-10" to-iso="2023-07-14"/><title>Digital Humanities 2023. Collaboration as Opportunity</title><placeName>Graz</placeName></meeting>
                <author n="WintermeierTrentCLEMENT_Tanya_AudiAnnotate_Workshop_with_Radio_Venceremos__R.xml"><persName n="WintermeierTrent">
                        <surname>Wintermeier</surname>
                        <forename>Trent</forename>
                    </persName><affiliation>University of Texas, United States of America</affiliation><email>trentwintermeier@utexas.edu</email></author><meeting><date from-iso="2023-07-10" to-iso="2023-07-14"/><title>Digital Humanities 2023. Collaboration as Opportunity</title><placeName>Graz</placeName></meeting>
                <author n="BurrowsVeraCLEMENT_Tanya_AudiAnnotate_Workshop_with_Radio_Venceremos__R.xml"><persName n="BurrowsVera">
                        <surname>Burrows</surname>
                        <forename>Vera</forename>
                    </persName><affiliation>University of Texas, United States of America</affiliation><email>Ververapatricia@utexas.edu</email></author><meeting><date from-iso="2023-07-10" to-iso="2023-07-14"/><title>Digital Humanities 2023. Collaboration as Opportunity</title><placeName>Graz</placeName></meeting>
            </titleStmt>
            
            <publicationStmt><publisher><orgName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1137284463">Zentrum für Informationsmodellierung
                    - Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities, Karl-Franzens-Universität
                    Graz</orgName></publisher><date when="2023">2023</date><pubPlace>Graz</pubPlace><availability><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">Creative Commons BY
                    4.0</licence></availability></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title>Digital Humanities 2023: Book of Abstracts</title><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-9256-0958"><forename>Walter</forename><surname>Scholger</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>University of Graz</orgName><placeName>Graz, Austria</placeName></affiliation><email>walter.scholger@uni-graz.at</email></editor><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-1726-1712"><forename>Georg</forename><surname>Vogeler</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>University of Graz</orgName><placeName>Graz, Austria</placeName></affiliation><email>georg.vogeler@uni-graz.at</email></editor><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-3919-993X"><forename>Toma</forename><surname>Tasovac</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>Belgrade Center for Digital Humanities</orgName><placeName>Belgrade, Serbia</placeName></affiliation><email>ttasovac@humanistika.org</email></editor><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-4593-059X"><forename>Anne</forename><surname>Baillot</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>Le Mans Université</orgName><placeName>Le Mans, France</placeName></affiliation><email>anne.baillot@univ-lemans.fr</email></editor><respStmt><resp>Data Management</resp><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0009-0007-9019-8215"><forename>Elisabeth</forename><surname>Raunig</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Management</resp><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-1438-3236"><forename>Martina</forename><surname>Scholger</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Management</resp><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-9116-0402"><forename>Elisabeth</forename><surname>Steiner</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Curation</resp><persName><forename>Johanna</forename><surname>Ofenauer</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Curation</resp><persName><forename>Christina</forename><surname>Burgstaller</surname></persName></respStmt><idno type="DOI">10.5281/zenodo.7961822</idno></seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="DHCONVALIDATOR" version="1.22">
                    <label>DHConvalidator</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc><abstract><p>This workshop will help participants make audio, video, and its interpretations more discoverable and usable through the use of the IIIF (International Image Interoperability Framework) standard for audio and video to produce, publish, and sustain W3C Web Annotations for individual and collaborative audiovisual editions, exhibits, and playlists. The workshop format will include introductions to IIIF, AudiAnnotate, Audacity, and GitHub using model, collaborative AudiAnnotate projects called the "SpokenWeb Anthology," made from recordings from the SpokenWeb Consortium and “Radio Venceremos, the Rebel’s Radio Station," which features recordings from Radio Venceremos (“Radio We Will Overcome”), a popular, clandestine radio station that the Farabundo Martí National Liberation Front (FMLN) created to broadcast news and analysis from the mountains of Morazán, El Salvador during the eleven year Salvadoran Civil War (1981-1992).</p></abstract><langUsage><language ident="en">English</language></langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="category">
                    <term>Paper</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="subcategory">
                    <term>Pre-Conference Workshop and Tutorial</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="keywords">
                    <term>Sound Studies</term>
                    <term>Media Studies</term>
                    <term>Archives</term>
                    <term>Latin American Studies</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="topics">
                    <term>metadata standards</term>
                    <term>systems</term>
                    <term>and methods</term>
                    <term>music and sound digitization</term>
                    <term>encoding</term>
                    <term>and analysis</term>
                    <term>open access methods</term>
                    <term>scholarly editing and editions development</term>
                    <term>analysis</term>
                    <term>and methods</term>
                    <term>Chicano/a/x</term>
                    <term>Latino/a/x studies</term>
                    <term>Cultural studies</term>
                    <term>Library &amp; information science</term>
                    <term>Media studies</term>
                    
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>This AudiAnnotate half-day workshop will help
                    participants make audio, video, and their interpretations more discoverable and
                    usable by teaching them to extend the use of the newest IIIF (International
                    Image Interoperability Framework) standard for audio and video through the
                    AudiAnnotate web application and documented workflows. These workflows include
                    the use of existing best-of-breed, open-source tools for annotation (Audacity),
                    for public code and document repositories and collaboration (GitHub), and audio
                    and video presentation (the Aviary player) to produce, publish, and sustain
                    shareable W3C Web Annotations for individual and collaborative audiovisual
                    editions, exhibits, and playlists. </p>
                <p>In recent years, increased concern over media
                        degradation and obsolescence combined with the decreasing cost of digital
                        storage has led libraries, archives, and museums (LAMs) to digitize
                        audiovisual (AV) materials for improved access and long-term preservation.
                        Yet, improving preservation and access must go far beyond digitization. AV
                        collections often include lectures, panels, and speeches; performances such
                        as story-telling, oral histories, and poetry or dance performances; and
                        other documentary AV historical artifacts. Yet, even while they are
                        sometimes the only record of an event or an aural, visual, or performance
                        tradition, AV digital artifacts remain underused and understudied. The fact
                        that digital AV collections are not well- represented in our national and
                        international digital platforms, such as Europeana and the Digital Public
                        Library of America (DPLA), demonstrates complicated factors surrounding how
                        LAM institutions manage and facilitate access to digital surrogates. As of
                        July 2020, Europeana comprised 55% images and 42% text objects, but only 1%
                        sound objects and .5% video objects (Europeana). DPLA included 67% images
                        and 32% text, with less than 1% sound objects, and moving image objects
                        (Digital Public Library of America). The goal of the AudiAnnotate project is
                        to accelerate access to, promote scholarship and teaching with, and extend
                        understanding of significant digital AV collections in the humanities. </p>
                <p>Annotating is only one of a list of scholarly methods
                        including discovering, comparing, referring, sampling, illustrating, and
                        representing (Unsworth 2000). IIIF (International Image Interoperability
                        Framework) is one standardized solution that LAMs have adopted to give users
                        the ability to perform these primitives with images held in cultural
                        heritage institutions. Comprising 56 global members including major research
                        universities, national libraries, and world-renowned museums, archives,
                        software companies, and other organizations, the IIIF Consortium has worked
                        together since Fall 2011 to create, test, refine, implement, and promote the
                        IIIF specifications for interoperable functionality and collaboration across
                        repositories. IIIF uses linked data and W3C web standards to facilitate
                        sharing digital image data, migrating across technology systems, and using
                        third-party software to enhance access to images, allowing for viewing,
                        zooming, comparing, manipulating, and working with annotated images on the
                        Web. With IIIF, users can reference images linked from LAMs into software
                        that allows them to manipulate the images in new ways without impacting the
                        institution’s presentation of the item. </p>
                <p>As of June 2020, the IIIF-AV Technical Specification
                        Group has extended the existing IIIF Presentation API (version 3) to
                        accommodate rendering AV in a web browser. The AV group is actively
                        welcoming contributions to their collection of AV user stories, mockups, and
                        prototypes in order to make sure IIIF-AV is used by a broad audience. While
                        IIIF has shared use cases for different kinds of AV manifests, including for
                        album covers, oral histories, multi-track recordings, and AV with sign
                        language, tools for exposing and playing these manifests are still under
                        development. Freely available, Universal Viewer displays annotations as
                        captions on AV materials, but the annotations cannot be used to navigate the
                        object or be shown separately from the AV object, a necessity for
                        oft-restricted AV materials.</p>
                <p>The AudiAnnotate project builds on these IIIF
                        accomplishments, addressing the gaps in engaging with AV by developing a
                        solution to bring together free AV annotation tools and the Web as a
                        standardized collaboration and presentation platform. </p>
                <p>In response to the need for a workflow that supports
                        IIIF manifest creation, collaborative editing, flexible modes of
                        presentation, and permissions control, the AudiAnnotate extensible workflow
                        connects open source tools for annotation (such as Audacity), public code
                        and document repositories (GitHub), and the AudiAnnotate web application for
                        creating and sharing IIIF manifests and annotations. Usually limited by
                        proprietary software and LAM systems with restricted access to AV,
                        researchers can use AudiAnnotate as a complete sequence of tools and
                        transformations for accessing, identifying, annotating, and sharing
                        annotations. LAMs will benefit from AudiAnnotate as it facilitates metadata
                        generation, is built on W3C web standards in IIIF for sharing online
                        scholarship, and generates static web pages that are lightweight and easy to
                        preserve and harvest. Audiannotate represents a new kind of AV ecosystem
                        where the exchange is opened between institutional repositories, annotation
                        software, online repositories and publication platforms, and
                        researchers. </p>
                <p>The workshop format will include introductions to
                        IIIF, AudiAnnotate, Audacity, and GitHub using two model AudiAnnotate
                        projects across languages, Spanish and English, and disciplines, History and
                        Literature. The first project, “Radio Venceremos, the Rebel’s Radio
                        Station,” features recordings from Radio Venceremos (“Radio We Will
                        Overcome”), a popular, clandestine radio station that the Farabundo
                        MartíNational Liberation Front (FMLN) created to broadcast news and
                        analysis from the mountains of Morazán, El Salvador during the eleven year
                        Salvadoran Civil War (1981-1992). The recordings, which contain significant
                        voices on human rights violations during an era of social revolution in
                        Central America, are currently archived at the Nettie Lee Benson Latin
                        American Collection at the University of Texas in Austin. The second
                        project– “The SpokenWeb Digital Anthology”--serves as a collaborative use
                        case for AudiAnnotate, bringing together multiple projects and contributors;
                        it was also edited using the digital annotation software, Hypothes.is. “The
                        SpokenWeb Digital Anthology” is a digital edition curates and contextualizes
                        audio and video recordings of literary events from archives at Canadian
                        universities that have cooperated to digitize and make accessible these
                        recordings through the SpokenWeb consortium, a SSHRC funded digital
                        humanities project to promote the use of literary a/v artifacts in
                        scholarship.</p>
                <p>Workshop participants will be invited to learn how we created “Radio Venceremos, the Rebel’s Radio Station,” a scholarly exhibit led by PhD candidate Vera Burrows, and “The SpokenWeb Digital Anthology,” a collaborative digital edition edited by Postdoctoral Fellow, Dr. Zoe Bursztajn-Illingworth; they will also hear from a contributing writer, Trent Wintermeier, about the essay, “Annotating a Duality of Spaces in Muriel Rukeyser’s <hi rend="italic">The Speed of Darkness</hi>,” and annotated SpokenWeb recording he contributed
                        to the project. The workshop participants will also hear about AudiAnnotate
                        partner and SSHRC-funded SpokenWeb, a collaborative effort to promote
                        diverse engagement with audiovisual materials through the support of these
                        projects. This will include an overview of SpokenWeb’s public collections,
                        ongoing research, and future events. </p>
                <p>Participants are encouraged to build their own AV
                        exhibits or editions either with the Radio Venceremos collection, audio from
                        SpokenWeb, or with other collections of their interest. </p>
                <p>We invite AV and DH experts and beginners to
                    participate. No experience or equipment beyond a laptop and an interest in AV is
                    needed. During the workshop, participants will be encouraged to work with any
                    audiovisual collection in any language that is freely available online. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Brief half-day workshop agenda</head>
                <list type="ordered">
                    <item>Introduction to AudiAnnotate, IIIF, and sample
                            projects including the “Radio Venceremos, the Rebel’s Radio Station”
                            project and “The SpokenWeb Digital Anthology” </item>
                    <item>Hands-on training in creating annotations and setting up collaborative
                        workflows using GitHub and AudiAnnotate </item>
                    <item>Break out sessions to guide participants on
                            starting their own projects and exhibits. </item>
                </list>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliogr">
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <bibl><author>Digital Public Library of America</author>:
                        <ref target="https://dp.la/">https://dp.la/</ref> [21.04.2023].</bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <hi rend="bold">Europeana</hi>: <ref target="https://www.europeana.eu/en">https://www.europeana.eu/en</ref>
                            [21.04.2023]
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <hi rend="bold">Unsworth, John</hi> (2000): “ Scholarly Primitives:
                            What methods do humanities researchers have in common, and how might our
                            tools reflect this”, in: Symposium on Humanities Computing: Formal
                            Methods, Experimental Practice 13: King’s College, London:
                            <ref target="https://people.brandeis.edu/~unsworth/Kings.5-00/primitives.html">https://people.brandeis.edu/~unsworth/Kings.5-00/primitives.html</ref>
                            [21.04.2023].
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <hi rend="bold">Europeana</hi>: <ref target="https://www.europeana.eu/en">https://www.europeana.eu/en</ref>
                            [21.04.2023]
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text></TEI>