<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_allPlus.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_allPlus.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Research Software Engineer Careers and Project Involvement in DH</title>
                <author n="DamerowJuliaDAMEROW_Julia_Research_Software_Engineer_Careers_and_Project.xml"><persName n="DamerowJulia">
                        <surname>Damerow</surname>
                        <forename>Julia</forename>
                    </persName><affiliation>Arizona State University, United States of America</affiliation><email>jdamerow@asu.edu</email></author><meeting><date from-iso="2023-07-10" to-iso="2023-07-14"/><title>Digital Humanities 2023. Collaboration as Opportunity</title><placeName>Graz</placeName></meeting>
                <author n="VoglMalteDAMEROW_Julia_Research_Software_Engineer_Careers_and_Project.xml"><persName n="VoglMalte">
                        <surname>Vogl</surname>
                        <forename>Malte</forename>
                    </persName><affiliation>MPI for the History of Science</affiliation><email>mvogl@mpiwg-berlin.mpg.de</email></author><meeting><date from-iso="2023-07-10" to-iso="2023-07-14"/><title>Digital Humanities 2023. Collaboration as Opportunity</title><placeName>Graz</placeName></meeting>
                <author n="TharsenJeffreyDAMEROW_Julia_Research_Software_Engineer_Careers_and_Project.xml"><persName n="TharsenJeffrey">
                        <surname>Tharsen</surname>
                        <forename>Jeffrey</forename>
                    </persName><affiliation>University of Chicago</affiliation><email>tharsen@uchicago.edu</email></author><meeting><date from-iso="2023-07-10" to-iso="2023-07-14"/><title>Digital Humanities 2023. Collaboration as Opportunity</title><placeName>Graz</placeName></meeting>
                <author n="CastiesRobertDAMEROW_Julia_Research_Software_Engineer_Careers_and_Project.xml"><persName n="CastiesRobert">
                        <surname>Casties</surname>
                        <forename>Robert</forename>
                    </persName><affiliation>MPI for the History of Science</affiliation><email>casties@mpiwg-berlin.mpg.de</email></author><meeting><date from-iso="2023-07-10" to-iso="2023-07-14"/><title>Digital Humanities 2023. Collaboration as Opportunity</title><placeName>Graz</placeName></meeting>
                <author n="KoeserRebeccaSuttonDAMEROW_Julia_Research_Software_Engineer_Careers_and_Project.xml"><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-8762-8057" n="KoeserRebeccaSutton">
                        <surname>Koeser</surname>
                        <forename>Rebecca Sutton</forename>
                    </persName><affiliation>Princeton University</affiliation><email>rkoeser@princeton.edu</email></author><meeting><date from-iso="2023-07-10" to-iso="2023-07-14"/><title>Digital Humanities 2023. Collaboration as Opportunity</title><placeName>Graz</placeName></meeting>
                <author n="LeBlancZoeDAMEROW_Julia_Research_Software_Engineer_Careers_and_Project.xml"><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2012-8805" n="LeBlancZoe">
                        <surname>LeBlanc</surname>
                        <forename>Zoe</forename>
                    </persName><affiliation>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</affiliation><email>zleblanc@illinois.edu</email></author><meeting><date from-iso="2023-07-10" to-iso="2023-07-14"/><title>Digital Humanities 2023. Collaboration as Opportunity</title><placeName>Graz</placeName></meeting>
                <author n="SiqueiraDiegoDAMEROW_Julia_Research_Software_Engineer_Careers_and_Project.xml"><persName n="SiqueiraDiego">
                        <surname>Siqueira</surname>
                        <forename>Diego</forename>
                    </persName><affiliation>Ruhr University Bochum</affiliation><email>diego.siqueira@rub.de</email></author><meeting><date from-iso="2023-07-10" to-iso="2023-07-14"/><title>Digital Humanities 2023. Collaboration as Opportunity</title><placeName>Graz</placeName></meeting>
                <author n="CrawfordColeDAMEROW_Julia_Research_Software_Engineer_Careers_and_Project.xml"><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-8347-0096" n="CrawfordCole">
                        <surname>Crawford</surname>
                        <forename>Cole</forename>
                    </persName><affiliation>Humanities Research Computing - Harvard University</affiliation><email>cole_crawford@fas.harvard.edu</email></author><meeting><date from-iso="2023-07-10" to-iso="2023-07-14"/><title>Digital Humanities 2023. Collaboration as Opportunity</title><placeName>Graz</placeName></meeting>
            </titleStmt>
            
            <publicationStmt><publisher><orgName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1137284463">Zentrum für Informationsmodellierung
                    - Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities, Karl-Franzens-Universität
                    Graz</orgName></publisher><date when="2023">2023</date><pubPlace>Graz</pubPlace><availability><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">Creative Commons BY
                    4.0</licence></availability></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title>Digital Humanities 2023: Book of Abstracts</title><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-9256-0958"><forename>Walter</forename><surname>Scholger</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>University of Graz</orgName><placeName>Graz, Austria</placeName></affiliation><email>walter.scholger@uni-graz.at</email></editor><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-1726-1712"><forename>Georg</forename><surname>Vogeler</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>University of Graz</orgName><placeName>Graz, Austria</placeName></affiliation><email>georg.vogeler@uni-graz.at</email></editor><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-3919-993X"><forename>Toma</forename><surname>Tasovac</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>Belgrade Center for Digital Humanities</orgName><placeName>Belgrade, Serbia</placeName></affiliation><email>ttasovac@humanistika.org</email></editor><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-4593-059X"><forename>Anne</forename><surname>Baillot</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>Le Mans Université</orgName><placeName>Le Mans, France</placeName></affiliation><email>anne.baillot@univ-lemans.fr</email></editor><respStmt><resp>Data Management</resp><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0009-0007-9019-8215"><forename>Elisabeth</forename><surname>Raunig</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Management</resp><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-1438-3236"><forename>Martina</forename><surname>Scholger</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Management</resp><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-9116-0402"><forename>Elisabeth</forename><surname>Steiner</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Curation</resp><persName><forename>Johanna</forename><surname>Ofenauer</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Curation</resp><persName><forename>Christina</forename><surname>Burgstaller</surname></persName></respStmt><idno type="DOI">10.5281/zenodo.7961822</idno></seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="DHCONVALIDATOR" version="1.22">
                    <label>DHConvalidator</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc><abstract><p>This panel will discuss career path opportunities and challenges for people doing coding work in DH. The panelists are a diverse group of people with different backgrounds and interests in terms of career path and recognition. Short presentations from each panelist about their experiences will be followed by an open discussion with the audience.</p></abstract><langUsage><language ident="en">English</language></langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="category">
                    <term>Paper</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="subcategory">
                    <term>Panel</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="keywords">
                    <term>research software engineering</term>
                    <term>career path</term>
                    <term>software quality</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="topics">
                    <term>software development</term>
                    <term>systems</term>
                    <term>analysis and methods</term>
                    <term>Humanities computing</term>
                    
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <p>In 2012, Ramsay and Rockwell wrote that “[t]here is [...]
                a large group in digital humanities that experiences this anxiety about credit and
                what counts in a way that is far more serious and consequential. These are the
                people [...] who have turned to building, hacking, and coding as part of their
                normal research activity” (Ramsay and Rockwell 2012, p. 75). They continue to
                discuss the question whether writing code counts as scholarship. In 2017, Dombrowski
                et al. discussed in a panel at DH2017 the role of digital humanists at the
                intersection of the humanities and research computing (Dombrowski et al. 2017). What
                both of these discussions have in common are that they are closely intertwined with
                the discussion about career path options and opportunities of recognition for people
                doing coding work in the digital humanities. In a survey by DHTech conducted in
                2020, 67% of the respondents said that they did not have a career path at their
                current employer (DHTech 2020). This poses a problem as missing career path
                opportunities often result in highly qualified people leaving the field for a more
                stable career leading to a lack in code maintenance and quality. Without permanent
                positions for research software engineers, how can the DH community ensure code
                quality and sustainability beyond the limited and often temporary funding of DH
                projects? How do career structures have to change to accommodate people doing coding
                work?</p>
            <p>To discuss the question of career paths for people doing
                coding and technical work in digital humanities, we propose a panel at DH2023. The
                panelists are a diverse group of people with different backgrounds and interests in
                terms of career path and recognition. The goal of this panel is to develop an
                understanding of what opportunities exist and what is still missing for anyone
                interested in a career in DH that involves writing code. We will ask the panelists
                to give a short account of their background and career path (5-10 minutes) answering
                a list of questions we provide ahead of time. These questions will include for
                example how they were trained, what formal education they have, what their current
                position is, and how they get recognized for their coding work. We will then invite
                the audience to participate in a discussion with the panelists. We aim to write up
                the discussion after the conference as a white paper.</p>
            <div>
                <head>Panelists</head>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Jose Hernandez Perez</hi> is currently the Digital Humanities
                    Technology Specialist for the Research Computing Center at Florida State
                    University. There he works in the Interdisciplinary Data Humanities Initiative,
                    which instructs and assists humanities faculty and students in the use of
                    High-Performance Computing tools. In addition, he assists in the development of
                    DH projects that require further technical assistance with data analysis,
                    database creation, TEI-XML, etc. Before joining FSU, he earned a BA in History
                    and an MA in Digital Studies of Language, Culture, and History from the
                    University of Chicago. His current focus is to advance the integration of HPC
                    tools within DH while developing effective methods for standardizing computer
                    science education, particularly in specialized fields, (ex. HPC; quantum
                    computing) into humanities curricula. With respect to the panel, some of the
                    topics he would like to discuss are how to start the learning of code outside
                    and inside the classroom; how to create a space for RSEs within DH
                    infrastructure at higher education institutions; and the creation of educational
                    standards or formalized paths for the RSE career field, which is today
                    self-guided by the interested student, career switcher, or project needs. </p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Max Ionov</hi> is a research assistant at the Cologne Center for
                    eHumanities, University of Cologne. Currently, he is involved in the project
                    Classic Mayan Dictionary and Postil Time Machine. He is also actively involved
                    in the W3C OntoLex community and is a COST action NexusLinguarum, devoted to
                    promoting and developing the field of Web-centric Linguistic Data Science. </p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Rebecca Sutton Koeser</hi> double majored in English Literature
                    and Computer Science, and then decided to pursue a Ph.D. in English Literature.
                    In grad school, she quickly got involved with the Electronic Text Center and
                    Digital Library work at Emory University Libraries. After completing a
                    traditional (non-digital) dissertation, she took a position working as a
                    software engineer at Emory University Libraries, where she worked on a variety
                    of research infrastructure and digital scholarship projects. Working on a small
                    software team there taught her real-world software engineering skills and best
                    practices, project management, and Agile methodology. Rebecca was recruited to
                    be the first Lead Developer for the Center for Digital Humanities at Princeton
                    University, where she leads a small team of software engineers and one designer
                    who partner with faculty to develop innovative digital humanities research
                    projects, and also has some time to pursue her own research. She is excited
                    about the growing Research Software Engineer community, RSE career path options,
                    overlap between DH and RSE communities, and increased opportunities for
                    researchers with technical expertise to contribute and co-author innovative
                    work. </p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Zoe LeBlanc</hi> is currently an Assistant Professor in the
                    School of Information Sciences at Urbana-Champaign where she does full-stack DH
                    (web development to data science to historical research), but she will detail
                    how getting this point was far from straightforward or even expected. Unlike
                    many programmers, she had zero programming experience growing up, and was only
                    introduced to computers in-between her undergraduate and graduate degrees. Her
                    timing was fortunate, since when she entered her PhD program in History at
                    Vanderbilt University, it was when a new field called digital humanities was
                    first taking off. While she was able to learn more about DH through fellowships
                    and workshops, she eventually went beyond the ‘established’ DH path to a coding
                    bootcamp. LeBlanc will detail how this experience led her to new career options
                    (DH developer for example), but also how in turn those lead to reconsidering
                    faculty positions. She will also discuss her current experiences in an iSchool,
                    which is both relatively supportive of programming as scholarship, but also
                    raises questions around what types of coding work are more visible, and
                    therefore valued. </p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Kalle Westerling</hi> pursued a PhD in Theatre and Performance
                    at CUNY Graduate Center in New York City. During his time there, he got engaged
                    with interdisciplinary digital initiatives like creating a digital archive for
                    the Center for LGBTQ Studies, helping set up the Futures Initiative, directing
                    HASTAC Scholars, and eventually as a project manager and technical lead for the
                    Digital Humanities Research Institutes. After graduating in February 2022, he
                    started in the position as Research Software Engineer in Living with Machines
                    project, co-hosted at the British Library and the Alan Turing Institute. As part
                    of the project, he has been an embedded part of the research team and worked on
                    developing codebases for metadata management, crowdsourced human-in-the-loop
                    workflows for machine learning models, and parsing XML standards for historical
                    newspapers. Westerling will discuss how the skills built during his PhD have
                    opened him up to a field of Research Software Engineering, developer education,
                    professional development, and technical leadership. One of the challenges he
                    wants to discuss as part of the panel is the necessity to develop language to
                    translate one's experiences to outside traditional academic contexts. </p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliogr">
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <bibl><author>DHTech</author> (2020): “DH RSE
                        Survey Results.” DHTech
                        <ref target="https://dh-tech.github.io/survey-results-2020">https://dh-tech.github.io/survey-results-2020</ref> [30.04.2023]</bibl>
                    <bibl><author>Dombrowski, Quinn</author> / <author>Gniady, Tassie</author> / <author>Meredith-Lobay, Megan</author> / <author>Tharsen, Jeffrey</author> / <author>Zickel, Lee</author> 
                        (2017): “Research Computing’s Demand for Humanists , and Vice Versa”, in
                        Digital Humanities 2017.</bibl>
                    <bibl><author>Ramsay, Stephen</author> / <author>Rockwell, Geoffrey</author>  (2012): “Developing Things: Notes toward an Epistemology
                        of Building in the Digital Humanities”, in Debates in the Digital
                        Humanities, edited by Matthew K. Gold, 75–84. University of Minnesota
                        Press.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text></TEI>