<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_allPlus.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_allPlus.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Readers, Tropes, and Translations: Directions for Digital Research into Youth
                    Literature</title>
                <author n="BackmanAgnieszkaDOMBROWSKI_Quinn_Readers__Tropes__and_Translations__Directio.xml"><persName n="BackmanAgnieszka">
                        <surname>Backman</surname>
                        <forename>Agnieszka</forename>
                    </persName><affiliation>Uppsala University, Sweden</affiliation><email>agnieszka.backman@nordiska.uu.se</email></author><meeting><date from-iso="2023-07-10" to-iso="2023-07-14"/><title>Digital Humanities 2023. Collaboration as Opportunity</title><placeName>Graz</placeName></meeting>
                <author n="ByszukJoannaDOMBROWSKI_Quinn_Readers__Tropes__and_Translations__Directio.xml"><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2850-2996" n="ByszukJoanna">
                        <surname>Byszuk</surname>
                        <forename>Joanna</forename>
                    </persName><affiliation>Institute of Polish Language of the Polish Academy of Sciences,
                        Poland</affiliation><email>joanna.byszuk@ijp.pan.pl</email></author><meeting><date from-iso="2023-07-10" to-iso="2023-07-14"/><title>Digital Humanities 2023. Collaboration as Opportunity</title><placeName>Graz</placeName></meeting>
                <author n="DombrowskiQuinnDOMBROWSKI_Quinn_Readers__Tropes__and_Translations__Directio.xml"><persName n="DombrowskiQuinn">
                        <surname>Dombrowski</surname>
                        <forename>Quinn</forename>
                    </persName><affiliation>Stanford University, United States of America</affiliation><email>qad@stanford.edu</email></author><meeting><date from-iso="2023-07-10" to-iso="2023-07-14"/><title>Digital Humanities 2023. Collaboration as Opportunity</title><placeName>Graz</placeName></meeting>
                <author n="LangAnoukDOMBROWSKI_Quinn_Readers__Tropes__and_Translations__Directio.xml"><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-9597-1026" n="LangAnouk">
                        <surname>Lang</surname>
                        <forename>Anouk</forename>
                    </persName><affiliation>School of Literatures, Languages and Cultures, University of
                        Edinburgh</affiliation><email>anouk.lang@ed.ac.uk</email></author><meeting><date from-iso="2023-07-10" to-iso="2023-07-14"/><title>Digital Humanities 2023. Collaboration as Opportunity</title><placeName>Graz</placeName></meeting>
                <author n="MurathAntoniaDOMBROWSKI_Quinn_Readers__Tropes__and_Translations__Directio.xml"><persName n="MurathAntonia">
                        <surname>Murath</surname>
                        <forename>Antonia</forename>
                    </persName><affiliation>Freie Universität, Department of German and Dutch
                        Philology</affiliation><email>amurath@zedat.fu-berlin.de</email></author><meeting><date from-iso="2023-07-10" to-iso="2023-07-14"/><title>Digital Humanities 2023. Collaboration as Opportunity</title><placeName>Graz</placeName></meeting>
                <author n="NomuraNicholeDOMBROWSKI_Quinn_Readers__Tropes__and_Translations__Directio.xml"><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-5624-9011" n="NomuraNichole">
                        <surname>Nomura</surname>
                        <forename>Nichole</forename>
                    </persName><affiliation>Department of English, Stanford University, United States of
                        America</affiliation><email>nnomura@stanford.edu</email></author><meeting><date from-iso="2023-07-10" to-iso="2023-07-14"/><title>Digital Humanities 2023. Collaboration as Opportunity</title><placeName>Graz</placeName></meeting>
            </titleStmt>
            
            <publicationStmt><publisher><orgName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1137284463">Zentrum für Informationsmodellierung
                    - Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities, Karl-Franzens-Universität
                    Graz</orgName></publisher><date when="2023">2023</date><pubPlace>Graz</pubPlace><availability><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">Creative Commons BY
                    4.0</licence></availability></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title>Digital Humanities 2023: Book of Abstracts</title><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-9256-0958"><forename>Walter</forename><surname>Scholger</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>University of Graz</orgName><placeName>Graz, Austria</placeName></affiliation><email>walter.scholger@uni-graz.at</email></editor><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-1726-1712"><forename>Georg</forename><surname>Vogeler</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>University of Graz</orgName><placeName>Graz, Austria</placeName></affiliation><email>georg.vogeler@uni-graz.at</email></editor><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-3919-993X"><forename>Toma</forename><surname>Tasovac</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>Belgrade Center for Digital Humanities</orgName><placeName>Belgrade, Serbia</placeName></affiliation><email>ttasovac@humanistika.org</email></editor><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-4593-059X"><forename>Anne</forename><surname>Baillot</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>Le Mans Université</orgName><placeName>Le Mans, France</placeName></affiliation><email>anne.baillot@univ-lemans.fr</email></editor><respStmt><resp>Data Management</resp><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0009-0007-9019-8215"><forename>Elisabeth</forename><surname>Raunig</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Management</resp><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-1438-3236"><forename>Martina</forename><surname>Scholger</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Management</resp><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-9116-0402"><forename>Elisabeth</forename><surname>Steiner</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Curation</resp><persName><forename>Johanna</forename><surname>Ofenauer</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Curation</resp><persName><forename>Christina</forename><surname>Burgstaller</surname></persName></respStmt><idno type="DOI">10.5281/zenodo.7961822</idno></seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="DHCONVALIDATOR" version="1.22">
                    <label>DHConvalidator</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc><abstract><p>This panel brings together a number of projects which apply computational approaches to the study of youth literature, including translations of popular girls’ series, adaptations of the canon, books with well-trodden themes, and medieval texts with young female protagonists, to capture emerging research questions and methodological challenges facing the field.</p></abstract><langUsage><language ident="en">English</language></langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="category">
                    <term>Paper</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="subcategory">
                    <term>Panel</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="keywords">
                    <term>youth literature</term>
                    <term>medieval</term>
                    <term>readability metrics</term>
                    <term>stylometry</term>
                    <term>visualization</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="topics">
                    <term>attribution studies and stylometric analysis</term>
                    <term>digital libraries creation</term>
                    <term>management</term>
                    <term>and analysis</term>
                    <term>rhetorical analysis</term>
                    <term>text mining and analysis</term>
                    <term>Education/ pedagogy</term>
                    <term>Literary studies</term>
                    <term>Translation studies</term>
                    
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <p>As Wouter Haverals and Vanessa Joosen note in a recent
                article on the Dutch children’s author Guus Kuijer, there has been little work done
                at the intersection of digital humanities and children’s literature, despite the
                presence of digitized collections such as the Baldwin Library of Historical
                Children’s Literature, the Auslit digital collection of storytelling, and the
                Digital Library for Dutch Literature (25). Putting distant reading into the section
                headed “Unmapped Territories”, <hi rend="italic">The Edinburgh Companion to
                    Children’s Literature</hi> (2017) begins the short chapter it devotes to the
                subject with the tension between the expectation that research into children’s
                literature will situate individual authors within a broad view of the field, and the
                absence of methodological ways with which to do so (Giddens 305-6).  </p>
            <p>This panel addresses this gap by bringing together a
                number of projects which apply computational approaches to the study of youth
                literature, ranging from translations of popular girls’ series, adaptations of the
                canon, books with well-trodden themes, and medieval texts with young female
                protagonists. It encompasses a range of approaches to corpus construction, from
                small-scale studies of the work of a single author with several hundred thousand
                words, medium-scale projects with corpora spanning multiple languages, to a corpus
                containing over 30,000 texts. It considers the opportunities made possible by
                collaboration across different languages, explores what may be learnt by engaging
                with common metrics from the field of education, considers the challenges of tracing
                well-known tropes and patterns across versions and reimaginings of texts, and takes
                up questions of popularity and prestige which bear on the configuration of what
                Pierre Bourdieu terms the field of cultural production. Bringing together scholars
                from PhD students to established researchers, and including those who support
                digital humanities work, the panel surveys how scholars are currently using corpora
                and computational tools in a subfield of literature in which to date there has not
                been sustained work in digital literary directions, and to capture the emerging
                research questions and methodological challenges facing the field. </p>
            <div>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Stylometric outlook on The Baby-Sitters Club and its translations</hi></p>
                <p>Joanna Byszuk</p>
                <p>The concept of “the translator’s invisibility”, i.e.
                    preference of "absence of any linguistic or stylistic peculiarities" (Venuti
                    1995:1) in translation, has been the cause of much debate, and despite criticism
                    by some translation scholars, it is now considered a core element of translation
                    studies curricula. The concept of authorship in translation is controversial as
                    well - until recently, translators have rarely been recognized on book covers or
                    mentioned in book promotions, and have often struggled to obtain copyright (cf.
                    ibidem: 8-9 and further) or significant profit. Furthermore, on an intellectual
                    level, they have not necessarily been considered creators.</p>
                <p>In this talk, we examine the corpus of translations of
                    the Baby-Sitters Club into 11 language versions (distinguishing three French
                    versions, next to e.g. Catalan and Polish) with stylometry, a method of
                    quantitative text analysis based on comparison of texts using differences in
                    word (or other features) frequency distributions, and network analysis. The
                    presentation follows and extends our work on a corpus of 6 language versions
                    (Byszuk &amp; Dombrowski 2022), in which we discovered significant stylometric
                    visibility of ghostwriters, and found that many of the BSC translators have
                    clearly distinguishing styles, although some also had their stylistic impact
                    appear “invisible”, evidenced by the same distribution of similarities between
                    texts in the original and translated corpus. The results of this study led us to
                    an observation that translators tend to be more invisible in some language
                    circles, possibly relating to a specific translation tradition, a hypothesis
                    that we further pursue in this paper.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Does paratextual framing lead you right in the translation of the Swedish
                    Baby-Sitters Club books?</hi></p>
                <p>Agnieszka Backman</p>
                <p>The Swedish Baby-Sitters Club books consist of 17
                    books, translated by five translators working in three discrete phases over ten
                    years for two publishers. While having many different translators for a series
                    isn’t unusual for a children’s book series, the change in publishers presents a
                    slightly chaotic history of the translations: from B. Wahlströms förlag for the
                    first six books, to Sabenfeldt/tl*klubben for a reissue of the first book as
                    well as the next five (books 7–11), and then going back to B. Wahlströms for six
                    books from later in the English series’ run (books 50, 54, 55, 58, 60, and 63).
                    All three with different series names: Våran klubb, Barnvaktsklubben and The
                    Baby-Sitters Club. </p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>The low status of the translations of girls’ books can
                    often be seen in the paratext: out of order translations of series, titles not
                    semantically close to the source text equivalent, and authors’ names less
                    faithfully reproduced (Axelsson 2020), of which the first to fit the Swedish
                    Baby-Sitters Club books. Because of their lower status, publishers often allow
                    for bigger changes to the translations of popular literature and children’s
                    literature, e.g., extensive shortening and freer translations. This study uses
                    the Bleualign algorithm for text alignment with English, along with the Swedish
                    spacCy NLP model to investigate if markers of low status literature translation
                    can be seen in the texts of both publishers as it does in the paratexts or if
                    translator practices influence the end product more. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Ambivalence, Ambiguity and Allusion: Getting Beyond ‘Bias’ in the Chronicles
                    of Narnia</hi></p>
                <p>Anouk Lang</p>
                <p>Despite impressive advances in text generation, the
                    ability of machine learning to distinguish ‘bias’— racist or other forms of
                    prejudiced language—continues to raise concerns. Contending that literary
                    studies has something to teach computer science in this regard, I use the
                    seven-book Chronicles of Narnia (1950-1956) by C.S. Lewis to investigate the way
                    whiteness and nationalism are figured in the texts, and to demonstrate how
                    computational text analysis can identify these aspects. Lewis’s widely-read
                    books have considerable resonance with the contemporary moment: as Maria Cecire
                    observes, medievalist children’s fantasies such as the Narnia series “helped to
                    establish Britain as a seat of global enchantment and associate ‘white’ (good)
                    magic with racial whiteness in the minds of young people across the
                    Anglo-American world and beyond” (10). They are also interesting
                    methodologically because, at around 300,000 words, they are too small for
                    machine learning approaches and so must be tackled with less powerful tools,
                    albeit ones more accessible to humanities scholars. What might seem a fairly
                    simple task of searching for patterning around terms like black and white is not
                    as straightforward as it seems, given the ambiguities around whiteness in the
                    books as seen in figures such as the White Witch. Similarly, British nationalism
                    is encoded in the books in ways not easily retrievable by text search. By
                    investigating how these categories can be understood through the metaphorical
                    and figurative relations in the book, I suggest some ways that larger-scale
                    computational approaches might be better equipped to understand and identify
                    bias.</p>
                <p> </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Young Readers, Textual Difficulty, and Genre</hi></p>
                <p>Nichole Nomura</p>
                <p>In the United States specifically, and Anglophone
                    contexts more broadly, the idea of textual difficulty has been used and abused
                    in a wide range of educational contexts, from underwriting racially-biased
                    tracking to rewarding the kinds of reading educators, parents, and textbook
                    companies designate as valuable and worthwhile. It makes possible quantified
                    comparisons between readers, schools, and districts, and for digital humanists,
                    quantified comparisons between texts. </p>
                <p>In this talk, I argue that not only should digital
                    humanists be wary of difficulty metrics like Lexile scores (Smith 1989), the
                    SMOG index (Mc Laughlin 1969), or the Dale-Chall Formula (Dawkins et al 1956),
                    but that digital humanists are perhaps best-positioned to examine what textual
                    difficulty metrics actually capture. This talk uses the task of distinguishing
                    between Children’s, Middle-Grade, and Young Adult literature in the Young
                    Readers Database of Literature as a basis for comparison between different
                    difficulty metrics. The various and competing performances of these metrics
                    provides an opportunity to examine their biases and what they actually measure,
                    as well as an opportunity to think about the relationship between assumed
                    audience and assumed skill. Examining the performance of these difficulty
                    metrics across assumed age groups also invites conversations about how other
                    digital humanities methods that depend on similar assumptions about text might
                    or might not perform on literature for young readers. And finally, this task
                    invites critical reflection on the way genres defined by audiences and their
                    assumed abilities can and cannot be defined by proxies for those abilities. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Wherefore Art Thou Shakespeare: How Identifiable are Shakespeare Adaptations
                    for Young Readers?</hi></p>
                <p>Quinn Dombrowski</p>
                <p>The focus on young people's experiences in many of
                    Shakespeare's plays is one major thread connecting Shakespeare -- arguably the
                    most canonical of the Anglophone literary canon -- to youth literature, a field
                    often siloed from other forms of literary studies. Debates over whether, when,
                    and how youth should read Shakespeare in school have led to an extreme
                    proliferation of adaptations: some simply to facilitate reading, others to make
                    the content more relatable, and yet others to reimagine Shakespearean characters
                    and narratives with a twist on gender, race, or sexuality (Miller 2003). These
                    books are explicit about their Shakespearean origins, which are a non-trivial
                    part of their selling point. But would we be able to recognize them if they did
                    not tell us?</p>
                <p>This talk will take a collection of self-identified
                    Shakespeare adaptations for middle-grade and YA audiences -- including
                    adaptations created for students who struggle with reading, modernizations that
                    are intended to retain the original plot and character information, and creative
                    retellings -- as well as a set of texts at similar reading levels with similar
                    topics, and use a variety of text analysis methods (including distance metrics,
                    topic modeling, and stepwise variable selection) to explore the question of how
                    computationally identifiable Shakespearean adaptations actually are, compared to
                    other youth literature that engages with the themes of adolescence. How much of
                    the Shakespearean connection comes out of the use of recognizable character
                    names, compared to  a standard group of plot points that can be reduced to a
                    reliable set of vocabulary, or are there other factors at play? </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <p><hi rend="bold">The Handless Queen and Philological Bias: Visualizing a Medieval
                    Euro-Mediterranean Narrative Tradition</hi></p>
                <p>Antonia Murath</p>
                <p>A girl on the brink of adulthood narrowly escapes her
                    father’s sexual advances; she marries a prince, is slandered, re-exiled and
                    ultimately reinstated into a position of power. This is the basic plotline of
                    one of the medieval West’s most successful narratives, the <hi rend="italic">maiden-without-hands</hi>-type. Versions exist across languages, genres and
                    reading communities (noble, mercantile, Christian, Muslim) with surviving
                    manuscripts from the Balkans to North Africa. </p>
                <p>Yet, the tradition remains understudied. This might be
                    a corollary of gender and philological bias. The twice-exiled protagonist
                    ultimately triumphs while transitioning from the status of daughter/ child to
                    that of empress/ woman/ saint, without ever fitting the mold of the male knight
                    errant. Meanwhile, the narrative’s circulation defies the category of the nation
                    which still demarcates discrete disciplines of literary study; it also defies
                    modern notions of the text as a contained entity. Motif-combinations across
                    versions frustrate efforts to establish a stemma, the most persistent model of
                    textual transmission which indicates a constructed ‘original’ and its lineage of
                    translated or copied, increasingly ‘corrupted’ ‘derivatives’. Taking seriously
                    Ríkharðsdóttir’s proposition to define medieval textuality as “a dynamic corpus
                    […] in constant flux, being refashioned and reshaped” (2012, 8), I propose using
                    multivariate plot analysis to visualize textual relationships differently. My
                    database of more than 120 motifs across 26 versions (Aljemiado, Castilian,
                    Catalan, English, French, German, Italian, Latin) however draws in part on early
                    philologists’ data. How, then, does data visualization contribute to generating
                    different insights, opening up new avenues of inquiry, and how might it thus
                    deepen the understanding of the narrative tradition as a whole?</p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliogr">
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <bibl><author>Axelsson, Marcus</author> (2020). Cherry Ames och Vicki
                        Barr kommer till Skandinavien: Utgivningen av två amerikanska
                        flickboksserier ur ett översättningssociologiskt perspektiv. In: <hi rend="italic">Översättningsvetenskap i praktiken: Om översättningar,
                            översättare och översättande</hi>, eds. Elin Svahn &amp; Lova Meister. </bibl>
                    <bibl><author>Bourdieu, Pierre.</author> (1993) <hi rend="italic">The
                            Field of Cultural Production: Essays on Art and Literature</hi>.
                        Translated by Randal Johnson, Columbia University Press. </bibl>
                    <bibl><author>Bruijn, Elisabeth de, and Mike Kestemont</author>.
                        (2013) “Contrastive Multivariate Analyses of the Middle Low German Flos Unde
                        Blankeflos Tradition.” Neuphilologische Mitteilungen, 13, 2: 171–205</bibl>
                    <bibl><author>Byszuk, Joanna</author> / <author>Dombrowski, Quinn</author> . (2022).
                        Stylometric investigations into translationese: The Baby-Sitters Club across
                        languages. In <hi rend="italic">16th International Conference on Statistical
                            Analysis of Textual Data Proceedings.</hi>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl><author>Cecire, Maria Sachiko.</author> (2019) <hi rend="italic">Re-Enchanted: The Rise of Children’s Fantasy Literature in the
                            Twentieth Century</hi>. University of Minnesota Press. </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Dawkins, John</author> / <author>Dale, Edgar</author> / <author>Chall, Jeanne S.</author>  (1956). A Reconsideration of the Dale-Chall Formula [with Reply].
                        <hi rend="italic">Elementary English</hi>
                        , 
                        <hi rend="italic">33</hi>
                        (8), 515-522.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl><author>Edlich-Muth, Miriam.</author> Digitally Mapping Floire
                        et Blanchefleur’, blog post <ref target="https://digitalphilologist.com/digitally-mapping-floire-et-blancheflor/">https://digitalphilologist.com/digitally-mapping-floire-et-blancheflor/</ref>
                        [04.11.2022] </bibl>
                    <bibl><author>Giddens, Eugene.</author> (2022) "Distant Reading and
                        Children’s Literature", in: <hi rend="italic">The Edinburgh Companion to
                            Children’s Literature</hi>, edited by Clémentine Beauvais and Maria
                        Nikolajeva, Edinburgh University Press, pp. 305–13. </bibl>
                    <bibl><author>Hagby, Maryvonne.</author> (2017) 'Die Königstochter von
                        Frankreich' des Hans von Bühel: Untersuchung und Edition nach dem
                        Straßburger Druck von 1500. Waxmann.</bibl>
                    <bibl><author>Haverals, Wouter, and Vanessa Joosen.</author> (2021)
                        "Constructing Age in Children’s Literature: A Digital Approach to Guus
                        Kuijer’s Oeuvre", in: The Lion and the Unicorn 45, 1: 25–45.</bibl>
                    <bibl><author>Kiening, Christian</author>. (2000) “Genealogie-Mirakel:
                        Erzählungen vom ‘Mädchen ohne Hände’. Mit Edition zweier deutscher
                        Prosafassungen.” Geistliches in weltlicher und Weltliches in geistlicher
                        Literatur des Mittelalters, ed. by Christoph Huber et al., De Gruyter, pp.
                        237–72.</bibl>
                    <bibl><author>Kinoshita, Sharon</author>. (2014) „Chapter Twenty:
                        Mediterranean Literature.“ A Companion to Mediterranean History, ed. by
                        Peregrine Horden and Sharon Kinoshita, Wiley Blackwell, pp. 314–329.</bibl>
                    <bibl><author>Kunkel, Nico.</author> (2023) Modulares Erzählen:
                        Serialität und Mouvance in der Erzähltradition Der „Sieben Weisen Meister“.
                        De Gruyter.</bibl>
                    <bibl><author>Mc Laughlin, G. H.</author> (1969). SMOG grading-a new
                        readability formula. <hi rend="italic">Journal of reading</hi>, <hi rend="italic">12</hi>(8), 639-646. </bibl>
                    <bibl><author>Miller, Naomi</author>, ed. (2003) <hi rend="italic">Reimagining Shakespeare for Children and Young Adults</hi>. New York:
                        Routledge, </bibl>
                    <bibl><author>Ott, Michael R.</author> (2022) Die Germanistik und ihre
                        Mittelalter: Textwissenschaftliche Interventionen. De Gruyter.</bibl>
                    <bibl><author>Popović, Pavle.</author> (1908) “Die Manekine in Der
                        Südslavischen Literatur.” Zeitschrift für Romanische Philologie 12,
                        3:312–22.</bibl>
                    <bibl><author>Ríkharðsdóttir, Sif.</author> (2012) Medieval
                        Translations and Cultural Discourse: The Movement of Texts in England,
                        France and Scandinavia. Boydell &amp; Brewer.</bibl>
                    <bibl><author>Smith, Dean R.</author> (1989). The Lexile Scale in
                        Theory and Practice. Final Report.</bibl>
                    <bibl><author>Stein, Robert M.</author> (2009) „Multilingualism“
                        Middle English, ed. by Paul Strohm, Oxford Univ. pp. 23–37</bibl>
                    <bibl><author>Venuti, Lawrence.</author> (2008). <hi rend="italic">The
                            Translator's Invisibility: A History of Translation</hi> (2nd ed.).
                        Abingdon, Oxon, U.K.: Routledge. </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text></TEI>