<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_allPlus.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_allPlus.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Transforming the Pietist Tradition: Disciplinary Innovation through Linked
                    Digital Engagement</title>
                <author n="FaullKatherineMaryFAULL_Katherine_Mary_Transforming_the_Pietist_Tradition__Dis.xml"><persName n="FaullKatherineMary">
                        <surname>Faull</surname>
                        <forename>Katherine Mary</forename>
                    </persName><affiliation>Bucknell University, United States of America</affiliation><email>faull@bucknell.edu</email></author><meeting><date from-iso="2023-07-10" to-iso="2023-07-14"/><title>Digital Humanities 2023. Collaboration as Opportunity</title><placeName>Graz</placeName></meeting>
                <author n="PrellMartinFAULL_Katherine_Mary_Transforming_the_Pietist_Tradition__Dis.xml"><persName n="PrellMartin">
                        <surname>Prell</surname>
                        <forename>Martin</forename>
                    </persName><affiliation>Klassik Stiftung Weimar, Germany</affiliation><email>martin.prell@klassik-stiftung.de</email></author><meeting><date from-iso="2023-07-10" to-iso="2023-07-14"/><title>Digital Humanities 2023. Collaboration as Opportunity</title><placeName>Graz</placeName></meeting>
                <author n="TgelPhilippFAULL_Katherine_Mary_Transforming_the_Pietist_Tradition__Dis.xml"><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-1791-0268" n="TgelPhilipp">
                        <surname>Tögel</surname>
                        <forename>Philipp</forename>
                    </persName><affiliation>Karlsruhe Institute of Technology, Germany</affiliation><email>philipp.toegel@kit.edu</email></author><meeting><date from-iso="2023-07-10" to-iso="2023-07-14"/><title>Digital Humanities 2023. Collaboration as Opportunity</title><placeName>Graz</placeName></meeting>
                <author n="LaschAlexanderFAULL_Katherine_Mary_Transforming_the_Pietist_Tradition__Dis.xml"><persName n="LaschAlexander">
                        <surname>Lasch</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                    </persName><affiliation>Technical University Dresden, Germany</affiliation><email>alexander.lasch@tu-dresden.de</email></author><meeting><date from-iso="2023-07-10" to-iso="2023-07-14"/><title>Digital Humanities 2023. Collaboration as Opportunity</title><placeName>Graz</placeName></meeting>
                <author n="GarcesJuanFAULL_Katherine_Mary_Transforming_the_Pietist_Tradition__Dis.xml"><persName n="GarcesJuan">
                        <surname>Garces</surname>
                        <forename>Juan</forename>
                    </persName><affiliation>SLUB Dresden, Germany</affiliation><email>juan.garces@slub-dresden.de</email></author><meeting><date from-iso="2023-07-10" to-iso="2023-07-14"/><title>Digital Humanities 2023. Collaboration as Opportunity</title><placeName>Graz</placeName></meeting>
            </titleStmt>
            
            <publicationStmt><publisher><orgName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1137284463">Zentrum für Informationsmodellierung
                    - Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities, Karl-Franzens-Universität
                    Graz</orgName></publisher><date when="2023">2023</date><pubPlace>Graz</pubPlace><availability><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">Creative Commons BY
                    4.0</licence></availability></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title>Digital Humanities 2023: Book of Abstracts</title><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-9256-0958"><forename>Walter</forename><surname>Scholger</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>University of Graz</orgName><placeName>Graz, Austria</placeName></affiliation><email>walter.scholger@uni-graz.at</email></editor><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-1726-1712"><forename>Georg</forename><surname>Vogeler</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>University of Graz</orgName><placeName>Graz, Austria</placeName></affiliation><email>georg.vogeler@uni-graz.at</email></editor><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-3919-993X"><forename>Toma</forename><surname>Tasovac</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>Belgrade Center for Digital Humanities</orgName><placeName>Belgrade, Serbia</placeName></affiliation><email>ttasovac@humanistika.org</email></editor><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-4593-059X"><forename>Anne</forename><surname>Baillot</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>Le Mans Université</orgName><placeName>Le Mans, France</placeName></affiliation><email>anne.baillot@univ-lemans.fr</email></editor><respStmt><resp>Data Management</resp><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0009-0007-9019-8215"><forename>Elisabeth</forename><surname>Raunig</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Management</resp><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-1438-3236"><forename>Martina</forename><surname>Scholger</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Management</resp><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-9116-0402"><forename>Elisabeth</forename><surname>Steiner</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Curation</resp><persName><forename>Johanna</forename><surname>Ofenauer</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Curation</resp><persName><forename>Christina</forename><surname>Burgstaller</surname></persName></respStmt><idno type="DOI">10.5281/zenodo.7961822</idno></seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="DHCONVALIDATOR" version="1.22">
                    <label>DHConvalidator</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc><abstract><p>The panel has as its focus how collaboration in and implementation of DH methods has opened up a) new knowledge networks in the (conservative) field of Pietism and Religious History and b) transformed understandings of traditional disciplinary structures and hierarchies.</p></abstract><langUsage><language ident="en">English</language></langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="category">
                    <term>Paper</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="subcategory">
                    <term>Panel</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="keywords">
                    <term>collaboration</term>
                    <term>pietism</term>
                    <term>networks</term>
                    <term>knowledge transfer</term>
                    <term>LOD</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="topics">
                    <term>linked (open) data</term>
                    <term>manuscripts description</term>
                    <term>representation</term>
                    <term>and analysis</term>
                    <term>network analysis and graphs theory and application</term>
                    <term>text encoding and markup language creation</term>
                    <term>deployment</term>
                    <term>and analysis</term>
                    <term>Indigenous studies</term>
                    <term>History</term>
                    <term>Linguistics</term>
                    <term>Theology and religious studies</term>
                    
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div type="div1">
                <head> Introduction</head>
                <p>The panel has as its focus how collaboration in and
                    implementation of DH methods has opened up a) new knowledge networks in the
                    (traditionally conservative) field of Pietism and Religious History and b)
                    transformed understandings of traditional disciplinary structures and
                    hierarchies. In the field of the history of religion, especially the subfield of
                    the study of pietism, traditional disciplinary hierarchies in Europe and the US
                    very much have determined the shape and breadth of scholarship, viewing with
                    distrust the forays into DH that some, usually younger, scholars have pursued.
                    (Hutchings / Clivaz 2021) Although the demand for developers with a deep
                    understanding of the needs of humanistic thinking is great, the number of
                    practitioners of DH in the area of Pietism is woefully small. Furthermore, often
                    when DH approaches have been accepted, they have been firmly inscribed in the
                    realm of the archive and the library. Breaking with this conservative tradition
                    in Pietist Studies, the recently published <hi rend="italic">Pietismus
                        Handbuch</hi> includes as its second entry an essay on the potential and
                    practice of Digital Humanities in the study of Pietism. (Faull 2021) Following
                    this impetus, this panel will focus on how the process of opening up the
                    discipline, despite resistance, is moving forward and fostering innovation
                    through active links of collaboration. In the field of textual scholarship,
                    network analysis, sonic analysis, mapping, and cultural heritage, the methods of
                    digital humanities have been very successful in fostering new directions of
                    critical inquiry. (Eyerly 2022, Faull 2022, Sciutti, 2022) The separate papers
                    in this panel will echo the question posed in the latest issue of the <hi rend="italic">Journal of Moravian History</hi>, by the scholar of religion
                    Dr Rachel Wheeler who introduces the Forum on “Digital Moravians” claiming that
                    although digital scholarship invites collaboration, it does not necessarily
                    entail equal access to collaborative relationships. (Wheeler 2022) How can we
                    change this? To attempt to model collaborative partnerships across disciplines,
                    ranks, and expertises this panel brings together a senior US scholar whose
                    institutional support has allowed her to teach US undergraduate students DH
                    approaches to Pietistic materials; two younger scholars from Germany whose work
                    opens up new ways of accessing and analyzing archival materials and the networks
                    of their writers; and an established academic and library professional from a
                    technical university and state library whose work revolutionizes approaches to
                    mission history, historical linguistics, and cultural heritage. All four papers
                    examine individual projects that focus on aspects of Pietist research and DH
                    methodologies and that are also collaborative partners in a transatlantic
                    knowledge exchange network. The hope is that this panel will open up discussions
                    of the paths towards collaboration between scholars across the ranks, across
                    disciplines and languages, and across the Atlantic. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Linking Pietists and Moravians: Building and Sharing Knowledge
                        Networks</hi></p>
                <p>Katherine Faull </p>
                <p>As DH projects are developed around the globe, how can
                    we connect digital collections of historical documents across continents? Given
                    the geographically but not necessarily theologically close relationship in the
                    18th century between the Pietists in Halle and the Moravian Church based in
                    Herrnhut, Saxony and in the expansive transatlantic missions it is extremely
                    desirable to examine the connections between the two movements and their
                    adherents. Linking these sources would allow comparative studies in the various
                    fields and debates in which Halle Pietists and Moravians were active, such as
                    missions, ecclesiology, questions of race and gender, sexuality, or educational
                    practice. The field of Linked Open Data offers a set of design principles for
                    sharing machine-readable interlinked data on the web; but to what extent are we
                    able to effect data integration?</p>
                <p>To some extent, geo-data sharing has already occurred
                    between some projects that focus on geographically adjacent areas, such as
                    “moravian soundscapes” (https://moraviansoundscapes.music.fsu.edu) and Moravian
                    Lives (https://moravian.bucknell.edu), or projects where person data can be
                    linked (Moravians at Sea (https://www.moravians-at-sea.uni-jena.de) and Moravian
                    Lives). However, the ability to link Moravian manuscript sources and documents
                    from repositories of other Pietist and Anabaptist movements would provide a
                    powerful example of LOD in the field of Pietism.</p>
                <p>Examining the data structures behind the Digital
                    Francke portal (https://digital.francke-halle.de) and Moravian Lives, this paper
                    will investigate how such a knowledge network might be established, what
                    beginnings have already been made, and what obstacles lie in the way.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Collaboration through reuse: Analyzing letters explored by
                        others</hi></p>
                <p>Philipp Tögel </p>
                <p>August Hermann Francke was an integral figure in
                    Pietism. After coming to Glaucha, a suburb of Halle (Saale), in 1695, he founded
                    an orphanage and a school for the poor. In the subsequent years, the so-called
                    "Glauchasche Anstalten" (today "Francke Foundations") flourished and were
                    complemented by the addition of multiple schools and business ventures.
                    Following Francke’s death in 1727 his son Gotthilf August Francke and Johann
                    Anastasius Freylinghausen became the directors of the Anstalten. (Breul 2021:
                    126–130, Drese 2021: 174f.) How this transition of power affected the structure
                    and composition of the correspondence network of the Anstalten is investigated
                    based on the sources available in the Foundations archive
                    (http://archiv.francke-halle.de) through historical network analysis.</p>
                <p>This analysis is made possible by the past
                    explorations of others. Nearly 80,000 letters have been analyzed for form and
                    content by multiple DFG-funded projects as well as the Foundations archive,
                    which is making the sources available and is collaborating with scholars.
                    Although this corpus is available, the use of digital methods is an as-yet
                    unbeaten, but promising path. As letters have been of great importance for male
                    and female Pietists from almost every social class – because Pietists were part
                    of their local community and an international society of believers – the
                    analysis of these letters promises fruitful results to complement prior
                    research. (Jakubowski-Tiessen 2004: 203)</p>
                <p>The paper analyzes the vast amount of sources
                    available in Pietist archives in an unprecedented way in the field. Furthermore,
                    it addresses the advantages of collaboration between scholars and archives as
                    well as making research data openly accessible for analysis.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Moravians@Sea: Collaboration as a Chance and Risk Factor for
                        smaller DH Projects</hi></p>
                <p>Martin Prell </p>
                <p>During or after the transatlantic voyages of members
                    of the Moravian Church in the 18th century, travel diaries were written to
                    “document the experiences made on the voyage and the signs of divine activity on
                    the high seas for the community leadership and the brothers and sisters in
                    faith.“ (Mettele 2021: 406, trans. Martin Prell) The diaries form the basis for
                    the reproduction and visualizations of the transatlantic voyages of the
                    Moravians in the portal Moravians@Sea
                    (https://www.moravians-at-sea.uni-jena.de). One main principle of the ongoing
                    pilot project is the reuse and integration of a lot of online accessible
                    resources and services, to build a meta-portal that brings together distributed
                    research on Pietism and spatiotemporal visualization techniques to reimagine
                    scholarly editions of source materials as deeply collaborative and evolving,
                    rather than fixed.</p>
                <p>The paper will discuss, taking into account one’s own
                    project experiences as well as those of others, (see Carius et al. 2021) the
                    opportunities on the one hand, but also the dangers on the other hand, of the
                    predominant re-use of already available tools instead of developing one’s own
                    tools and the integration of online resources. In a second part, it will be
                    outlined, which conditions must be served for a still more fitting merging of
                    the data of the individual providers, in order to generate the greatest possible
                    benefit for the users and under the condition that the independent projects
                    involved are able to work together with as little effort as possible.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Exploring Moravian (Text) Worlds</hi></p>
                <p>Alexander Lasch, Juan Garcés </p>
                <p>This paper combines (1) the indexing of manuscript
                    sources (e.g., the <hi rend="italic">Gemein-Nachrichten</hi> from 1765 or
                    holdings from the Moravian Archives (Bethlehem)) with a focus on the North
                    American mission and (2) the creation of virtual excursions for teaching and
                    research contexts in order to make the worldwide network of the Moravian Church
                    accessible on a textual basis and to make it possible to experience it at the
                    virtual, historical location. First, among the most important sources for our
                    research field in the 18th century are the handwritten <hi rend="italic">Gemein-Nachrichten</hi> ( <hi rend="italic">Moravian Congregational
                        Accounts</hi>) which now constitute part of an agile and multimodal
                    next-generation reference corpus (N-ARC) being built in cooperation with the
                    Sächsische Landesbibliothek – Staats- und Universitätsbibliothek Dresden (SLUB)
                    in the Moravian Knowledge Network (MKN) (https://dhh.hypotheses.org/). This
                    corpus (N-ARC1) will comprise textual, cartographic, and audiovisual sources as
                    well as other artefacts, which will be interconnected, continuously (partially)
                    machine-enriched as open research data, and made publicly available and reusable
                    in a virtual research environment. </p>
                <p>Virtual excursions provide access to our multimedia
                    and multimodal data with which we are progressively enriching 3D-models.
                    (https://my.matterport.com/show/?m=WjbW5bc3FCj) In cooperation with our
                    colleagues at Bucknell University, PA, we plan to expand the virtual excursions
                    into virtual paths, creating connectivity between sites, buildings, gardens,
                    interior furnishings, and our textual sources. The documents and traces of the
                    Moravian Church offer the ideal starting point for this. They give
                    interdisciplinary research access to research subjects from the most diverse
                    scientific perspectives – linguistic, geo-informatic, cultural-historical,
                    land-historical, landscape-architectural, botanical, theological, etc. – and to
                    understand the global effects of European expansionism.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliogr">
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Breul, Wolfgang</author> (2021): “August Hermann Francke
                        (1663–1727)“, in: Breul, Wolfgang / Hahn-Bruckart, Thomas (eds.): <hi rend="italic">Pietismus Handbuch</hi>. Tübingen: Mohr-Siebeck 122–137. </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Carius, Hendrikje</author> / <author>Prell, Martin</author> / <author>Smolarski, René</author> 
                        (eds.) (2020): <hi rend="italic">Kooperationen in den digitalen
                            Geisteswissenschaften gestalten: Herausforderungen, Erfahrungen und
                            Perspektiven</hi>. Göttingen: Vandenhoeck &amp; Ruprecht. </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Drese, Claudia</author> (2021): “Gotthilf August Francke
                        (1696–1769)”, in: Breul, Wolfgang / Hahn-Bruckart, Thomas (eds.): <hi rend="italic">Pietismus Handbuch</hi>. Tübingen: Mohr-Siebeck 173–177. </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Eyerly, Sarah</author> (2022): “Reconstructing the Intangible
                        Cultural Heritage of the Moravian Missions”, in: <hi rend="italic">Journal
                            of Moravian History</hi> 22, 2: 187–193. URL:
                        https://www.muse.jhu.edu/article/868375. </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Faull, Katherine</author> (2021): “Digital Humanities“, in:
                        Breul, Wolfgang / Hahn-Bruckart, Thomas (eds.): <hi rend="italic">Pietismus
                            Handbuch</hi>. Tübingen: Mohr-Siebeck 11–17. </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Hetjens, Dominik</author> / <author>Lasch, Alexander</author> / <author>Schuppe, Robert C.</author>  (2022): “DigitalHerrnhut: Neue Zugänge zur historischen
                        Linguistik durch digital gestützte Lernumgebungen – ein Werkstattbericht“,
                        in: Meier, Jörg (ed.): <hi rend="italic">Sprachgeschichte und Bildung</hi>.
                        Berlin / Boston: De Gruyter (Jahrbuch für Germanistische Sprachgeschichte
                        13) 129–146. </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Hetjens, Dominik</author> / <author>Lasch, Alexander</author> / <author>Rummel, Marlene</author> / <author>Schuppe, Robert C.</author>  (2022): “Virtuelle Exkursion Kleinwelka“, in:
                            <hi rend="italic">Lessons Learned</hi> 2, 1: 39-1–39-11. DOI:
                        https://doi.org/10.25369/ll.v2i1.39. </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Hutchings, T.</author> / <author>Clivaz, C.</author>  (2021) (eds.): “Digital
                        humanities and christianity: an introduction“, in: <hi rend="italic">Introductions to digital humanities - religion</hi>, vol. 4. Berlin: De
                        Gruyter. </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Jakubowski-Tiessen, Manfred</author> (2004): “Eigenkultur und
                        Traditionsbildung“, in: Lehmann, Hartmut (ed.): <hi rend="italic">Glaubenswelten und Lebenswelten</hi>. Göttingen: Vandenhoeck &amp;
                        Ruprecht 195–210. </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Lasch, Alexander</author> (2023): “Multimodale und agile
                        Korpora: Perspektiven für Digital Herrnhut (N-ARC1)“, in: Deppermann, Arnulf
                        / Fandrych, Christian / Marc, Kupietz / Schmidt, Thomas (eds.): <hi rend="italic">Korpora in der germanistischen Sprachwissenschaft:
                            Mündlich, schriftlich, multimedial</hi>. Berlin / Boston: De Gruyter
                        (Jahrbuch des Instituts für Deutsche Sprache 2022) 225-250. DOI:
                        https://doi.org/10.1515/9783111085708-011. </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Lasch, Alexander</author> [accepted]: “’who called them, Sunday
                        *Indians or Shwannaks, that is, white people, the most opprobrious name they
                        could invent.’ Powerful constructions in the service of verbal devaluation”,
                        in: Meier-Vieracker, Simon (ed.): <hi rend="italic">Diskurs invektiv</hi>. </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Mettele, Gisela</author> (2021): “Gemeine auf hoher See:
                        Meeresüberfahrten der Herrnhuter Brüdergemeine im 18. Jahrhundert“, in:
                        Burschel, Peter / Juterczenka, Sünne (eds.): <hi rend="italic">Das Meer:
                            Maritime Welten in der Frühen Neuzeit</hi>. Wien: Böhlau 405–426. </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Prell, Martin</author> (2022): “Moravians@Sea: A Website for
                        Exploring and Experiencing Moravian Sea Voyages of the Eighteenth Century”,
                        in: <hi rend="italic">Journal of Moravian History</hi> 22, 2: 178–186. URL:
                        https://www.muse.jhu.edu/article/868374. </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Sciuchetti, Mark J. Jr</author>. (2022): “Mapping, Fieldwork,
                        and the Moravian Archives”, in:
                        <hi rend="italic">Journal of Moravian History </hi>22,
                        2: 194–205. URL: https://www.muse.jhu.edu/article/868376. </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Wheeler, Rachel</author> (2022): “Digital Moravians”, in: <hi rend="italic">Journal of Moravian History</hi> 22, 2: 150–156. URL:
                        https://www.muse.jhu.edu/article/868370. </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text></TEI>