<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_allPlus.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_allPlus.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Community-centric factors in sustaining digital scholarship</title>
                <author n="FenlonKatrinaFENLON_Katrina_Community_centric_factors_in_sustaining_digit.xml"><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-1483-5335" n="FenlonKatrina">
                        <surname>Fenlon</surname>
                        <forename>Katrina</forename>
                    </persName><affiliation>University of Maryland, College Park, United States of America</affiliation><email>kfenlon@umd.edu</email></author><meeting><date from-iso="2023-07-10" to-iso="2023-07-14"/><title>Digital Humanities 2023. Collaboration as Opportunity</title><placeName>Graz</placeName></meeting>
                <author n="RezaAliaFENLON_Katrina_Community_centric_factors_in_sustaining_digit.xml"><persName n="RezaAlia">
                        <surname>Reza</surname>
                        <forename>Alia</forename>
                    </persName><affiliation>University of Maryland, College Park, United States of America</affiliation><email>areza@umd.edu</email></author><meeting><date from-iso="2023-07-10" to-iso="2023-07-14"/><title>Digital Humanities 2023. Collaboration as Opportunity</title><placeName>Graz</placeName></meeting>
                <author n="GrimmerJessicaFENLON_Katrina_Community_centric_factors_in_sustaining_digit.xml"><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-0320-1812" n="GrimmerJessica">
                        <surname>Grimmer</surname>
                        <forename>Jessica</forename>
                    </persName><affiliation>University of Maryland, College Park, United States of America</affiliation><email>jgrimmer@umd.edu</email></author><meeting><date from-iso="2023-07-10" to-iso="2023-07-14"/><title>Digital Humanities 2023. Collaboration as Opportunity</title><placeName>Graz</placeName></meeting>
                <author n="WagnerTravisFENLON_Katrina_Community_centric_factors_in_sustaining_digit.xml"><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-6000-157X" n="WagnerTravis">
                        <surname>Wagner</surname>
                        <forename>Travis</forename>
                    </persName><affiliation>University of Maryland, College Park, United States of America</affiliation><email>twagner@umd.edu</email></author><meeting><date from-iso="2023-07-10" to-iso="2023-07-14"/><title>Digital Humanities 2023. Collaboration as Opportunity</title><placeName>Graz</placeName></meeting>
            </titleStmt>
            
            <publicationStmt><publisher><orgName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1137284463">Zentrum für Informationsmodellierung
                    - Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities, Karl-Franzens-Universität
                    Graz</orgName></publisher><date when="2023">2023</date><pubPlace>Graz</pubPlace><availability><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">Creative Commons BY
                    4.0</licence></availability></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title>Digital Humanities 2023: Book of Abstracts</title><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-9256-0958"><forename>Walter</forename><surname>Scholger</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>University of Graz</orgName><placeName>Graz, Austria</placeName></affiliation><email>walter.scholger@uni-graz.at</email></editor><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-1726-1712"><forename>Georg</forename><surname>Vogeler</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>University of Graz</orgName><placeName>Graz, Austria</placeName></affiliation><email>georg.vogeler@uni-graz.at</email></editor><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-3919-993X"><forename>Toma</forename><surname>Tasovac</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>Belgrade Center for Digital Humanities</orgName><placeName>Belgrade, Serbia</placeName></affiliation><email>ttasovac@humanistika.org</email></editor><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-4593-059X"><forename>Anne</forename><surname>Baillot</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>Le Mans Université</orgName><placeName>Le Mans, France</placeName></affiliation><email>anne.baillot@univ-lemans.fr</email></editor><respStmt><resp>Data Management</resp><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0009-0007-9019-8215"><forename>Elisabeth</forename><surname>Raunig</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Management</resp><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-1438-3236"><forename>Martina</forename><surname>Scholger</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Management</resp><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-9116-0402"><forename>Elisabeth</forename><surname>Steiner</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Curation</resp><persName><forename>Johanna</forename><surname>Ofenauer</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Curation</resp><persName><forename>Christina</forename><surname>Burgstaller</surname></persName></respStmt><idno type="DOI">10.5281/zenodo.7961822</idno></seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="DHCONVALIDATOR" version="1.22">
                    <label>DHConvalidator</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc><abstract><p>Based on comparative case studies of four digital humanities projects, this paper identifies six community-centric factors in the sustainability of digital scholarship: factors that transcend organizational, technical, or financial considerations, and which relate to and rely upon the communities that support and surround digital humanties projects.</p></abstract><langUsage><language ident="en">English</language></langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="category">
                    <term>Paper</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="subcategory">
                    <term>Long Presentation</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="keywords">
                    <term>sustainability</term>
                    <term>community</term>
                    <term>community-centered sustainability</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="topics">
                    <term>data</term>
                    <term>object</term>
                    <term>and artefact preservation</term>
                    <term>digital archiving</term>
                    <term>digital research infrastructures development and analysis</term>
                    <term>sustainable procedures</term>
                    <term>systems</term>
                    <term>and methods</term>
                    <term>Library &amp; information science</term>
                    
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <p>While the term 
                <hi rend="italic">sustainability</hi> has proliferated across the discourse of the digital humanities over the past two decades, the meaning and implications of the concept vary significantly across different projects, communities, and organizations. What it means to sustain digital scholarship is necessarily context-dependent (Edmond / Morselli 2020; Drucker 2021). Yet many projects face common, interrelated obstacles to remaining viable over time—whether technically, intellectually, effectively, etc.) These common challenges include resource-scarcity, vagaries of institutional support (e.g., Maron / Pickle 2014), reliance on volunteer labor (e.g., Risam 2018), impediments to shared technical infrastructure (Smithies et al. 2019; Dombrowski 2014), disconnect from broader systems of scholarly communication, and systemic instability and inequity across the humanities, cultural heritage, and higher education sectors more generally. The prevailing paradigm of institutional stewardship, in which digital humanities projects ultimately fall back on the preservation or maintenance resources and expertise of digital humanities centers, academic units, and libraries, has so far failed to adequately accommodate the diversity, complexity, and community-centeredness of digital humanities scholarship. 
            </p>
            <p>A widespread challenge is that many digital humanities resources resist institutional stewardship because communities wish to retain control over the resources they have created. Digital humanities scholarship, whether public-oriented or not, is often community-centered. Collaborative teams of technologists and researchers create and maintain digital resources to meet their own research needs, for example, or to fill gaps in the mainstream cultural record with new forms of evidence about underrepresented communities. These teams are surrounded by wider communities, including research communities within specific domains or disciplines, communities of practice organized around shared methods or other topics, and groups unified by shared identity, place, memory, and other shared interests. These teams and communities build shared resources—from digital editions to databases, from software to data models, from corpora to digital archives—to serve their constituents (Poole 2017; Cooper / Rieger 2018; Palmer et al. 2009). Digital humanities projects are active, generative, dynamic hubs for collaboration and communication. Such resources are sustained not by transfer from communities to preservation institutions, but through continued life and development.</p>
            <p>The digital humanities discourse about the sustainability of digital scholarship focuses on financial, organizational, and technical factors in the longevity of digital resources. These factors are vitally important, but our collective conversation about sustainability has often elided the roles of communities themselves—as nebulous entities that transcend institutions, individuals, and teams. There are important exceptions. Prior work has considered, for example, how research on community needs factors into sustainability planning (Edmond / Morselli 2020; Smithies et al. 2019; Langmead et al. 2018; Warwick et al. 2008), community-building practices (Mahony 2017; Skinner 2018; Arthur 2014; Clement et al. 2013), and how cultural knowledge serves communities themselves (Cifor et al. 2018; Caswell et al. 2018; Stevens et al. 2010, etc.). Nevertheless, there is little empirical research on how communities of different shapes and sizes surround and support digital humanities scholarship and digital community archives. We need a foundational understanding of how research communities affect the sustainability of digital scholarship. In our definition of 
                <hi rend="italic">community-centered sustainability</hi>, a digital humanities resource is sustained as long as it responsively supports the endurance of the communities it serves—as a locus of memory, communication, and knowledge production—for as long as useful, and in whatever forms are useful (Fenlon / Muñoz 2020). 
            </p>
            <p>This paper describes the outcomes of the “Communities sustaining digital scholarship” project, a qualitative study of how communities interpret, impact, and implement the sustainability of their own projects and resources. Through case studies of four digital humanities projects, conducted from 2019 to 2021, we sought to understand how communities define 
                <hi rend="italic">sustainability</hi> for themselves, and how their emergent approaches to sustainability centered or relied upon various invested communities. Each of our four case studies serves a different core community by gathering and providing access to evidence in new forms, to support research, collaboration, and community-building: 
            </p>
            <list type="unordered">
                <item><hi rend="italic">Enslaved: Peoples of the Historical Slave Trade</hi> (https://enslaved.org/) is an online, open-source linked data hub focused on the history of enslaved people.
                </item>
                <item>The 
                    <hi rend="italic">Lakeland Digital Archive</hi> (https://lakelandchp.com/) is an effort to document a 130-year-old African American community adjacent to the University of Maryland through a digital community archive.
                </item>
                <item>The 
                    <hi rend="italic">Music Encoding Initiative</hi> (https://music-encoding.org/) is a community-driven, open-source effort to define a system for encoding musical documents in a machine-readable structure.
                </item>
                <item>The 
                    <hi rend="italic">Open Islamicate Texts Initiative</hi> (http://kitab-project.org/openiti/) is a multi-institutional effort to construct a machine-actionable corpus of premodern Islamicate texts. 
                </item>
            </list>
            <p>These cases diverge in topic, discipline, size, and geographic distribution—and in how they relate to various communities and institutions. Through interviews with members of each project and surrounding communities, along with participant-observation and analysis of project documentation, our case studies have identified community-driven factors in sustaining digital scholarship.</p>
            <p>We offer a framework of six factors that affect the community-centered sustainability of digital scholarship. How communities interpret, plan for, and implement each of these factors provide alternative models for community-centered sustainability of digital scholarship. The factors are:</p>
            <list type="unordered">
                <item>How communities engage wider interested and affected communities;</item>
                <item>How communities factor in the wellbeing of their members and of the community as a whole;</item>
                <item>How communities reify their values in the organization and design of their projects and outcomes;</item>
                <item>How communities navigate issues of ownership and control;</item>
                <item>How communities implement an ecosystem perspective; and</item>
                <item>How communities embrace disruption and change.</item>
            </list>
            <p>This paper elaborates each of these factors and delves into specific examples of how these factors arose in our different cases. In addition, we offer a preliminary set of implications of these factors for the creators of digital humanities projects and the communities that contextualize them. </p>
            <p>The community-centered sustainability framework is intended to help communities think holistically about sustainability—and, in line with the conference theme, about their collaborative potentials in sustaining digital scholarship within and despite a context of broader instability. This framework complements the wide and growing body of digital humanities literature on technical, organizational, and financial approaches to digital sustainability and preservation, to provide a more complete and nuanced picture of how communities envision sustainability for themselves.</p>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliogr">
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Arthur, Paul Longley</author> (2014): “Knowledge networks in the humanities”, in: 
                        <hi rend="italic">Proceedings of the Digital Humanities Congress</hi>, 4-6 September 2014, The University of Sheffield, U.K.
                        <ref target="https://researchdirect.westernsydney.edu.au/islandora/object/uws%3A36293/">https://researchdirect.westernsydney.edu.au/islandora/object/uws%3A36293/</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Caswell, Michelle</author> / <author>Gabiola, Joyce</author> / <author>Zavala, Jimmy</author> / <author>Brilmyer, Gracen</author> / <author>Cifor, Marika</author>  (2018): “Imagining transformative spaces: The personal–political sites of community archives”, in: 
                        <hi rend="italic">Archival Science</hi> 18, 1: 73–93 <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1007/s10502-018-9286-7">https://doi.org/10.1007/s10502-018-9286-7</ref>.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Cifor, Marika</author> / <author>Caswell, Michelle</author> / <author>Migoni, Alda Allina</author> / <author>Geraci Noah</author>  (2018): “‘What We Do Crosses over to Activism’: The Politics and Practice of Community Archives”, in: 
                        <hi rend="italic">The Public Historian</hi> 40, 2: 69–95 
                        <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1525/tph.2018.40.2.69">https://doi.org/10.1525/tph.2018.40.2.69</ref>.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Clement, Tanya</author> / <author>Hagenmaier, Wendy</author> / <author>Knies, Jennie Levine</author>  (2013): “Toward a Notion of the Archive of the Future: Impressions of Practice by Librarians, Archivists, and Digital Humanities Scholars”, in: 
                        <hi rend="italic">The Library Quarterly</hi> 83, 2: 112–30 
                        <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1086/669550">https://doi.org/10.1086/669550</ref>.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Cooper, Danielle Miriam</author> / <author>Rieger, Oya Y.</author>  (2018): 
                        <hi rend="italic">Scholars ARE Collectors: A Proposal for Re-Thinking Research Support</hi>: Ithaka S+R, 28 November 
                        <ref target="https://doi.org/10.18665/sr.310702">https://doi.org/10.18665/sr.310702</ref>.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Dombrowski, Quinn</author> (2014): “What Ever Happened to Project Bamboo?”, in: 
                        <hi rend="italic">Literary and Linguistic Computing</hi> 29, 3: 326–39 
                        <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1093/llc/fqu026">https://doi.org/10.1093/llc/fqu026</ref>.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Drucker, Johanna</author> (2021): “Sustainability and Complexity: Knowledge and Authority in the Digital Humanities”, in: 
                        <hi rend="italic">Digital Scholarship in the Humanities</hi> 36, Supplement_2: ii86–94 
                        <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1093/llc/fqab025">https://doi.org/10.1093/llc/fqab025</ref>.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Edmond, Jennifer</author> (2013): “CENDARI’s Grand Challenges: Building, Contextualising and Sustaining a New Knowledge Infrastructure”, in: 
                        <hi rend="italic">International Journal of Humanities &amp; Arts Computing: A Journal of Digital Humanities</hi> 7, 1/2: 58–69 
                        <ref target="https://doi.org/10.3366/ijhac.2013.0081">https://doi.org/10.3366/ijhac.2013.0081</ref>.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Edmond, Jennifer</author> / <author>Morselli, Francesca</author>  (2020): “Sustainability of Digital Humanities Projects as a Publication and Documentation Challenge”, in: 
                        <hi rend="italic">Journal of Documentation</hi> 76, 5: 1019-1031 
                        <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1108/JD-12-2019-0232">https://doi.org/10.1108/JD-12-2019-0232</ref>.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Fenlon, Katrina</author> / <author>Muñoz, Trevor</author>  (2020): “What If We Can’t Manage Our Way to Better Sustainability?”, in: Digital Humanities (DH2020), Ottawa, Canada: Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations 
                        <ref target="https://dh2020.adho.org/abstracts/">https://dh2020.adho.org/abstracts/</ref>.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Langmead, Alison</author> / <author>Quigley, Aisling</author> / <author>Gunn, Chelsea</author> / <author>Hakimi, Jedd</author> / <author>Decker, Lindsay</author>  (2018). 
                        <hi rend="italic">Sustaining MedArt: The Impact of Socio-Technical Factors on Digital Preservation Strategies</hi>: 
                        <ref target="https://sites.haa.pitt.edu/sustainabilityroadmap/wp-content/uploads/sites/10/2017/01/SustainingMedArt_FinalReport_Web.pdf">https://sites.haa.pitt.edu/sustainabilityroadmap/wp-content/uploads/sites/10/2017/01/SustainingMedArt_FinalReport_Web.pdf</ref>.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Mahony, Simon</author> (2017): “The Digital Classicist: Building a Digital Humanities Community”, in: 
                        <hi rend="italic">Digital Humanities Quarterly </hi>11, 3: <ref target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/11/3/000335/000335.html">http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/11/3/000335/000335.html</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Maron, Nancy L.</author> / <author>Pickle, Sarah</author>  (2014): 
                        <hi rend="italic">Sustaining the Digital Humanities: Host Institution Support Beyond the Start-up Phase</hi>: ITHAKA S+R 
                        <ref target="https://sr.ithaka.org/publications/sustaining-the-digital-humanities/">https://sr.ithaka.org/publications/sustaining-the-digital-humanities/</ref>. 
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Palmer, Carole L.</author> / <author>Teffeau, Lauren C.</author> / <author>Pirmann, C.M.</author>  (2009): 
                        <hi rend="italic">Scholarly Information Practices in the Online Environment: Themes from the Literature and Implications for Library Service Development</hi>: OCLC Research and Programs, Dublin, OH 
                        <ref target="http://www.oclc.org/content/dam/research/publications/library/2009/2009-02.pdf">http://www.oclc.org/content/dam/research/publications/library/2009/2009-02.pdf</ref>.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Poole, Alex H.</author> (2017): “‘A Greatly Unexplored Area’: Digital Curation and Innovation in Digital Humanities”, in: 
                        <hi rend="italic">Journal of the Association for Information Science and Technology</hi> 68, 7: 1772–81 
                        <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1002/asi.23743">https://doi.org/10.1002/asi.23743</ref>.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Risam, Roopika</author> (2018): “Diversity Work and Digital Carework in Higher Education”, in: 
                        <hi rend="italic">First Monday</hi> 23, 3-5 
                        <ref target="https://doi.org/10.5210/fm.v23i3.8241">https://doi.org/10.5210/fm.v23i3.8241</ref>.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Skinner, Katherine</author> (2018): 
                        <hi rend="italic">Community Cultivation – A Field Guide</hi>: Educopia Institute 
                        <ref target="https://educopia.org/cultivation/">https://educopia.org/cultivation/</ref>. 
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Smithies, James</author> / <author>Westling, Carina</author> / <author>Sichani, Anna-Maria</author> / <author>Mellen, Pam</author> / <author>Ciula, Arianna</author>  (2019): “Managing 100 Digital Humanities Projects: Digital Scholarship &amp; Archiving in King’s Digital Lab”, in: 
                        <hi rend="italic">Digital Humanities Quarterly</hi> 13,1 
                        <ref target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/13/1/000411/000411.html">http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/13/1/000411/000411.html</ref>.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Stevens, Mary</author> / <author>Flinn, Andrew</author> / <author>Shepherd, Elizabeth</author>  (2010): “New Frameworks for Community Engagement in the Archive Sector: From Handing over to Handing On”, in: 
                        <hi rend="italic">International Journal of Heritage Studies</hi> 16, 1–2: 59–76 
                        <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1080/13527250903441770">https://doi.org/10.1080/13527250903441770</ref>.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Warwick, Claire</author> / <author>Terras, Melissa</author> / <author>Huntington, Paul</author> / <author>Pappa, Nikoleta</author>  (2008): “If You Build It Will They Come? The LAIRAH Study: Quantifying the Use of Online Resources in the Arts and Humanities through Statistical Analysis of User Log Data”, in: 
                        <hi rend="italic">Literary and Linguistic Computing</hi> 23, 1: 85–102 
                        <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1093/llc/fqm045">https://doi.org/10.1093/llc/fqm045</ref>.
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text></TEI>