<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_allPlus.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_allPlus.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mapping Antiquity in Collaboration: The Digital Periegesis Project </title>
                <author n="FokaAnnaFOKA_Anna_Mapping_Antiquity_in_Collaboration__The_Digital_Pe.xml"><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-9949-616X" n="FokaAnna">
                        <surname>Foka</surname>
                        <forename>Anna</forename>
                    </persName><affiliation>Uppsala University, Sweden</affiliation><email>anna.foka@abm.uu.se</email></author><meeting><date from-iso="2023-07-10" to-iso="2023-07-14"/><title>Digital Humanities 2023. Collaboration as Opportunity</title><placeName>Graz</placeName></meeting>
                <author n="BarkerEltonFOKA_Anna_Mapping_Antiquity_in_Collaboration__The_Digital_Pe.xml"><persName n="BarkerElton">
                        <surname>Barker</surname>
                        <forename>Elton</forename>
                    </persName><affiliation>Open University, UK</affiliation><email>Elton.Barker@OPEN.AC.UK</email></author><meeting><date from-iso="2023-07-10" to-iso="2023-07-14"/><title>Digital Humanities 2023. Collaboration as Opportunity</title><placeName>Graz</placeName></meeting>
                <author n="KonstantinidouKyriakiFOKA_Anna_Mapping_Antiquity_in_Collaboration__The_Digital_Pe.xml"><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-2640-4519" n="KonstantinidouKyriaki">
                        <surname>Konstantinidou</surname>
                        <forename>Kyriaki</forename>
                    </persName><affiliation>Swedish Institute Athens</affiliation><email>kyriakikon@hotmail.com</email></author><meeting><date from-iso="2023-07-10" to-iso="2023-07-14"/><title>Digital Humanities 2023. Collaboration as Opportunity</title><placeName>Graz</placeName></meeting>
                <author n="KieslingBradyFOKA_Anna_Mapping_Antiquity_in_Collaboration__The_Digital_Pe.xml"><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-3281-5741" n="KieslingBrady">
                        <surname>Kiesling</surname>
                        <forename>Brady</forename>
                    </persName><affiliation>Swedish Institute Athens</affiliation><email>westtothesea@hotmail.com</email></author><meeting><date from-iso="2023-07-10" to-iso="2023-07-14"/><title>Digital Humanities 2023. Collaboration as Opportunity</title><placeName>Graz</placeName></meeting>
            </titleStmt>
            
            <publicationStmt><publisher><orgName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1137284463">Zentrum für Informationsmodellierung
                    - Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities, Karl-Franzens-Universität
                    Graz</orgName></publisher><date when="2023">2023</date><pubPlace>Graz</pubPlace><availability><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">Creative Commons BY
                    4.0</licence></availability></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title>Digital Humanities 2023: Book of Abstracts</title><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-9256-0958"><forename>Walter</forename><surname>Scholger</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>University of Graz</orgName><placeName>Graz, Austria</placeName></affiliation><email>walter.scholger@uni-graz.at</email></editor><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-1726-1712"><forename>Georg</forename><surname>Vogeler</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>University of Graz</orgName><placeName>Graz, Austria</placeName></affiliation><email>georg.vogeler@uni-graz.at</email></editor><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-3919-993X"><forename>Toma</forename><surname>Tasovac</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>Belgrade Center for Digital Humanities</orgName><placeName>Belgrade, Serbia</placeName></affiliation><email>ttasovac@humanistika.org</email></editor><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-4593-059X"><forename>Anne</forename><surname>Baillot</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>Le Mans Université</orgName><placeName>Le Mans, France</placeName></affiliation><email>anne.baillot@univ-lemans.fr</email></editor><respStmt><resp>Data Management</resp><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0009-0007-9019-8215"><forename>Elisabeth</forename><surname>Raunig</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Management</resp><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-1438-3236"><forename>Martina</forename><surname>Scholger</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Management</resp><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-9116-0402"><forename>Elisabeth</forename><surname>Steiner</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Curation</resp><persName><forename>Johanna</forename><surname>Ofenauer</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Curation</resp><persName><forename>Christina</forename><surname>Burgstaller</surname></persName></respStmt><idno type="DOI">10.5281/zenodo.7961822</idno></seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="DHCONVALIDATOR" version="1.22">
                    <label>DHConvalidator</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc><abstract><p>This long paper examines the affordances and challenges in interdisciplinary collaboration between researchers, projects and contemporary digital research infrastructures for the analysis of ancient narratives. Our case study is Pausanias’s Description of Greece a 10 volume 2nd century CE traveling guide to Greece.</p></abstract><langUsage><language ident="en">English</language></langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="category">
                    <term>Paper</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="subcategory">
                    <term>Long Presentation</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="keywords">
                    <term>Linked Open Data</term>
                    <term>Interoperability</term>
                    <term>Spatial Humanities</term>
                    <term>Classics</term>
                    <term>Archaeology</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="topics">
                    <term>linked (open) data</term>
                    <term>semantic analysis</term>
                    <term>spatial &amp; spatio-temporal analysis</term>
                    <term>modeling and visualization</term>
                    <term>text encoding and markup language creation</term>
                    <term>deployment</term>
                    <term>and analysis</term>
                    <term>Archaeology</term>
                    <term>Cultural studies</term>
                    <term>History</term>
                    <term>Philology</term>
                    
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <p>Spatial analytical methods predate the field of digital humanities, most notably
                through cartography, the practice of drawing and studying maps. More recently, the
                spatial analysis of texts via Geographic Information Systems (GIS) is trending as a
                research method. Mapping pre-modern space is rarely a matter of documenting toponyms
                or establishing precise coordinates. Rather, space becomes place through interaction
                with historical agents and the human footprint left on the ground in the form of
                monuments, religious sites and other infrastructures. While contemporary geographic
                information science and historical modes of describing space often appear to have
                disparate, even incompatible, viewpoints of the world, there is a growing ecosystem
                that seeks to remedy the complexity of ancient space. This ecosystem of tools,
                content and communities about ancient place and space illustrate how collaboration
                within the field of digital humanities can be an opportunity for scientific
                discovery. </p>
            <p>Against this backdrop, this paper examines the affordances and challenges in interdisciplinary collaboration between researchers, projects and contemporary digital research infrastructures for the analysis of ancient narratives. Our case study is a well-known ancient narrative of space: namely Pausanias’s <hi rend="italic">Periegesis Hellados</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Description of Greece</hi>), a ten-volume description of Greek towns, villages, monuments, works of art and their histories from Attica to Phocis, following a circuit around the Peloponnese. The Digital Periegesis project,
                    funded by the Marcus and Amalia Wallenberg Foundation (MAW 2017.0057; 2018–2021), and comprising an interdisciplinary team of scholars builds on existing digital spatial research infrastructures, using maps as visual portals into narratives, as a means to interrogate rather than merely illustrate spatial information. In the second phase of the project that is financed by the Swedish Research Council from 2022 to 2026 (Vetenskapsrådet 2021-02799) the Digital Periegesis project is set out to investigate descriptions of time and people and to incorporate this to the ongoing Digital Periegesis’s visualisation. </p>
            <p>This long research paper then discusses scientific collaboration between researchers
                and research infrastructures more generally, incorporating information about space,
                time and people into a reflexive process to illuminate change and development as a
                way of understanding place fully. From the outset, the Digital Periegesis’ project
                team utilize an existing eco-system of digital spatial research infrastructure and
                analysis but also additional and customized infrastructures that are used more
                widely, beyond Pausanias’s Description of Greece. The overarching argument presented
                here is that Digital Periegesis is not simply a collaboration of scholars from
                different backgrounds and with different skills, which is a standard
                interdisciplinary practice in Digital Humanities. Additionally, the Digital
                Periegesis project team is attempting to break new ground in applying linked data
                methods and tools and, as such, is establishing a new model of collaboration. </p>
            <p>At one level, this collaboration promotes a bottom up
                    approach: that is establishing workflows and pipelines, involving a broader
                    community of classicists, archaeologists and digital humanists. Collaboration is
                    thus manifested in reusing data— a TEI digital text, as well as reusing tools,
                    more specifically the semantic annotation tool Recogito, developed by the
                    Pelagios Network of Partners. At another level, the Digital Periegesis project
                    team hosts a private and customized instance of Recogito in order to make use of
                    actual archaeological databases, such as the German Archaeological Institute’s
                    DAI/ ARACHNE for semantically annotating the more granular aspects of
                    Pausanias's description (temples, statues, etc.). But collaboration, recycling
                    and reuse of data and resources does not end there for the Digital Periegesis
                    project team. Examples of such reuse and recycling include yet are not limited
                    to, drawing on other resources, namely Wikidata, to provide URIs; providing the
                    enriched, annotated Pausanias’s text back to the Perseus Digital Library; and
                    returning new place information to the Pleiades structured vocabulary of ancient
                    place data. Additionally, the Digital Periegesis research group is developing
                    open source tools in collaboration for enabling the visualization and search of
                    geospatial information specifically in the re-launch of Peripleo — which has
                    subsequently been taken up by other projects, notably the British Library.</p>
            <p>Our project is essentially theoretically and methodologically inspired by the field
                of spatial humanities (e.g. Bodenhamer–Corrigan–Harris 2010). As is well rehearsed,
                the value of ‘locating historical and cultural exegesis more explicitly in space and
                time’ (Bodenhamer 2010: 28) has greatly assisted historical inquiry into places
                (Gregory and Ell 2007; Gregory–Geddes 2014). Applications of Geographic Information
                Systems (GIS) hold the promise of facilitating the gathering, management and
                analysis of spatially based data systematically (Gregory–Healey 2007; Dunn 2019).
                Yet, the very systematic structure of a GIS is frequently ill-suited to capturing
                aspects of uncertainty and ambiguity that typically characterise, and explain
                interest in, Humanities data (Gregory–Healey 2007: 641; Harris–Bergeron–Rouse 2011:
                228; Dunn 2019). Specifically, our project derives directly from the Hestia
                project’s blended methodological approach to exploring literary geography, which had
                highlighted ways in which texts organise spatial knowledge, based on relations
                between places (Bouzarovski–Barker 2016; Barker–Pelling 2016). The semantic
                annotation tool Recogito has been attracting increasing adoption in both the
                research into, and teaching of, places in historical records (Palladino 2016, 2021;
                O'Doherty 2021; Dunn–Vitale 2021). The fact that our use of Recogito is the most
                extensive, dense and complex application of this platform also goes to underline the
                value of the experience that we can share with the rest of the DH community, as
                Recogito itself undergoes a major overhaul. </p>
            <p>To conclude, by finding ways to compartmentalize concepts of space, people and time in a centuries’ old narrative the Digital Periegesis research team had the opportunity to engage and consequentially to collaborate with relevant content, but also tools and communities. Ultimately and through this knowledge production process, the Digital Periegesis project team are moving beyond the
                    confines of a Digital Humanities research project and are contributing and
                    enriching the wider and global landscape of digital humanities socio-technical
                    research infrastructure.</p>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliogr">
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Barker, E., Foka, A., and Konstantinidou, K. </author>
                        (2020): ‘Coding for the Many, Transforming Knowledge for All: Annotating
                            Digital Documents’. In Booth, A. and Posner, (eds) M. 
                        <hi rend="italic">Varieties of Digital Humanities</hi>
                         (DH Methodologies), 
                        <hi rend="italic">PMLA</hi>
                         the Modern Language Association of America. Cambridge: Cambridge
                            University Press: 135:1: 195-202.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Barker, E. T. E and Pelling, C. B. R. P. </author>
                        (2016): ‘Space-Travelling in Herodotus 5.’ In E. T. E. Barker, S.
                            Bouzarovski, C. B. R. Pelling, and L. Isaksen (eds) (2016) New Worlds
                            Out of Old Texts: Revisiting Ancient Space and Place. Oxford: Oxford
                            University Press, pp. 225-52,
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Bodenhamer, D. </author>
                        (2015): ‘Narrating space and place.’ In D. Bodenhamer, J. Corrigan, and
                            T. Harris (eds) (2010) The Spatial Humanities: GIS and the Future of
                            Humanities Scholarship. Bloomington: Indiana University Press, pp.
                            7-27.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Bodenhamer, D. </author>
                        (2010): 'The potential of spatial humanities.' In D. Bodenhamer, J.
                            Corrigan, and T. Harris (eds) (2010) The Spatial Humanities: GIS and the
                            Future of Humanities Scholarship. Bloomington: Indiana University
                            Press,pp. 14-30.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Bodenhamer, D., Corrigan, J., and Harris, T. (eds) </author>
                        (2015): Deep Maps and Spatial Narratives. Bloomington: Indiana
                            University Press. 
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Bodenhamer, D., Corrigan, J. and Harris, T. (eds) </author>
                        (2010): The Spatial Humanities: GIS and the Future of Humanities
                            Scholarship. Bloomington: Indiana University Press.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Bouzarovski, S. and Barker, E. T. E. </author>
                        (2016): ‘Between east and west: movements and transformations in
                            Herodotean topology.’ In E. T. E. Barker, S. Bouzarovski, C. B. R.
                            Pelling, and L. Isaksen (eds) (2016) New Worlds Out of Old Texts:
                            Revisiting Ancient Space and Place. Oxford: Oxford University Press, pp.
                            155-79 
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Dunn, S. </author>
                        (2019): A History of Place in the Digital Age. London: Routledge. 
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Dunn, S. and Vitale, V. </author>
                        (2021): 'Linking text and maps: Annotation as a critical tool for
                            teaching in the Spatial Humanities.' Literary Geographies 7(2), pp.
                            292-310. 
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Foka, A., Demiroglu, C., Konstantinidou, K., Barker, E.,
                            Kiesling, B. Talatas L., Mostofian, N. </author>
                        (2022): ‘Visualising Pausanias’s Description of Greece with Contemporary
                            GIS’, 
                        <hi rend="italic">Digital Scholarship in the Humanities,</hi>
                         Oxford: Oxford University Press: 37: 3: 761-724.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Foka, A., Konstantinidou, K., Mostofian, N., Talatas, L.,
                            Kiesling, J. B. Barker, E., Demiroglu, O. C., Palm, K., McMeekin, D.,
                            A., and Vekselius , J. </author>
                        (2021): ‘Heritage metadata: A Digital Periegesis’ in Golub, K., and Liu
                            Y-H., 
                        <hi rend="italic">Information and Knowledge Organisation in Digital
                            Humanities: Global Perspectives, </hi>
                        London and New York, Routledge: 227-242. 
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Foka, A., Barker, E., Konstantinidou, K., Demiroglu, O. C.,
                            Mostofian, N., Talatas, L., Kiesling, B. </author>
                        (2021): ‘Mapping Ancient Heritage Narratives with Digital Tools’ in
                            Champion, E. (Ed). (2021). 
                        <hi rend="italic">Virtual Heritage: A Concise Guide</hi>
                        . Ubiquity Press: London: 55-66. 
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Gregory, I. N. and Geddes A. </author>
                        (2014): Towards Spatial Humanities: Historical GIS and Spatial History.
                            Indiana University Press: Bloomington. 
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Gregory, I. N. and Ell P.S. </author>
                        (2007): Historical GIS: Technologies, Methodologies and Scholarship.
                            Cambridge University Press: Cambridge. 
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Gregory, I. N. and Healey R.G. </author>
                        (2007) 'Historical GIS: structuring, mapping and analysing geographies
                            of the past.' Progress in Human Geography 31, pp. 638-53. 
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Garris, T.M., Bergeron, S. and Rouse, L.J., </author>
                        (2011): Humanities GIS: Place, spatial storytelling, and immersive
                            visualization in the humanities. In GeoHumanities. Routledge: pp.
                            244-258. 
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>O'Doherty, M. </author>
                        (2021): 'Medieval traditions, new technologies: Linked Open Geodata and
                            Burchard of Mount Sion's Descriptio terrae sanctae.' International
                            Journal of Humanities and Arts Computing 15 (1-2), pp. 60–84. 
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Palladino, C. </author>
                        (2021): 'Representing places in texts: a spatial investigation into
                            Agathemerus’ Sketch of Geography.' International Journal of Humanities
                            and Arts Computing 15(1-2), pp. 33-59. 
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Palladino, C. </author>
                        (2016): ‘New approaches to ancient spatial models: Digital Humanities
                            and classical geography.' Bulletin of the Institute of Classical Studies
                            59(2), pp. 56–70.  
                        <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1111/j.2041-5370.2016.12038.x">https://doi.org/10.1111/j.2041-5370.2016.12038.x</ref>
                        .
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Vitale, V. Simon, R., and Barker E. </author>
                        (2020): Recogito: A Beginner’s Guide.  
                        <ref target="https://github.com/pelagios/pelagios.github.io/wiki">https://github.com/pelagios/pelagios.github.io/wiki</ref>
                        .
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Vitale, V., de Soto, P., Simon, R., Barker, E. T. E.,
                            Isaksen, L., and Kahn, R. </author>
                        (2021): ‘Pelagios - Connecting histories of place. Part I: Methods and
                            Tools.’ International Journal of Humanities and Arts Computing 15(1-2),
                            pp. 5-32. 
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text></TEI>