<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_allPlus.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_allPlus.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Skin of Venice: Automatic Facade Extraction from Point Clouds.</title>
                <author n="GuhennecPaulGUHENNEC_Paul_The_Skin_of_Venice__Automatic_Facade_Extractio.xml"><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-5490-5249" n="GuhennecPaul">
                        <surname>Guhennec</surname>
                        <forename>Paul</forename>
                    </persName><affiliation>Digital Humanities Laboratory, EPFL, Switzerland</affiliation><email>paul.guhennec@epfl.ch</email></author><meeting><date from-iso="2023-07-10" to-iso="2023-07-14"/><title>Digital Humanities 2023. Collaboration as Opportunity</title><placeName>Graz</placeName></meeting>
                <author n="diLenardoIsabellaGUHENNEC_Paul_The_Skin_of_Venice__Automatic_Facade_Extractio.xml"><persName n="diLenardoIsabella">
                        <surname>di Lenardo</surname>
                        <forename>Isabella</forename>
                    </persName><affiliation>Institute for Area and Global Studies, EPFL,
                        Switzerland</affiliation><email>isabella.dilenardo@epfl.ch</email></author><meeting><date from-iso="2023-07-10" to-iso="2023-07-14"/><title>Digital Humanities 2023. Collaboration as Opportunity</title><placeName>Graz</placeName></meeting>
            </titleStmt>
            
            <publicationStmt><publisher><orgName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1137284463">Zentrum für Informationsmodellierung
                    - Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities, Karl-Franzens-Universität
                    Graz</orgName></publisher><date when="2023">2023</date><pubPlace>Graz</pubPlace><availability><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">Creative Commons BY
                    4.0</licence></availability></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title>Digital Humanities 2023: Book of Abstracts</title><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-9256-0958"><forename>Walter</forename><surname>Scholger</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>University of Graz</orgName><placeName>Graz, Austria</placeName></affiliation><email>walter.scholger@uni-graz.at</email></editor><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-1726-1712"><forename>Georg</forename><surname>Vogeler</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>University of Graz</orgName><placeName>Graz, Austria</placeName></affiliation><email>georg.vogeler@uni-graz.at</email></editor><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-3919-993X"><forename>Toma</forename><surname>Tasovac</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>Belgrade Center for Digital Humanities</orgName><placeName>Belgrade, Serbia</placeName></affiliation><email>ttasovac@humanistika.org</email></editor><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-4593-059X"><forename>Anne</forename><surname>Baillot</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>Le Mans Université</orgName><placeName>Le Mans, France</placeName></affiliation><email>anne.baillot@univ-lemans.fr</email></editor><respStmt><resp>Data Management</resp><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0009-0007-9019-8215"><forename>Elisabeth</forename><surname>Raunig</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Management</resp><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-1438-3236"><forename>Martina</forename><surname>Scholger</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Management</resp><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-9116-0402"><forename>Elisabeth</forename><surname>Steiner</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Curation</resp><persName><forename>Johanna</forename><surname>Ofenauer</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Curation</resp><persName><forename>Christina</forename><surname>Burgstaller</surname></persName></respStmt><idno type="DOI">10.5281/zenodo.7961822</idno></seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="DHCONVALIDATOR" version="1.22">
                    <label>DHConvalidator</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc><abstract><p>We propose a method to extract orthogonal views of facades from photogrammetric models of cities. This method was applied to extract all facades of the city of Venice. The result images open up new areas of research in architectural history.</p></abstract><langUsage><language ident="en">English</language></langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="category">
                    <term>Paper</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="subcategory">
                    <term>Long Presentation</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="keywords">
                    <term>architectural history</term>
                    <term>orthophotos</term>
                    <term>distant seeing</term>
                    <term>artistic propagation</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="topics">
                    <term>image processing and analysis</term>
                    <term>spatial &amp; spatio-temporal analysis</term>
                    <term>modeling and visualization</term>
                    <term>Archaeology</term>
                    <term>Art history</term>
                    <term>Geography and geo-humanities</term>
                    
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div type="div1">
                <head>Facades as objects of study</head>
                <p>While recent years have seen the flourishing of a digital art history (Bonfait et
                    al. 2021), the intersection between architectural history and ”distant viewing”
                    within Digital Humanities remains mostly an open ground. In particular, a
                    large-scale compositional study of buildings based on the analysis of the
                    distribution of elements on the fa ̧cade is still unexplored. </p>
                <p>Such comparative analysis of facades would, though, be particularly valuable, for
                    they are key descriptive elements to understand the evolutionary palimpsest of a
                    building, as if they were the historical ’skin’ of its construction (Savorra
                    2006, Radding and Clark 1992). Facades also act also, often, as an indicator of
                    the articulation of interior spaces (Trinanato 1948). Furthermore, the
                    grammatical analysis of the facade permits its constitutive elements to be
                    defined separately as key chronological and stylistic signs from which to infer
                    information on its location, temporality, construction method and, of course,
                    authorship (Zevi 1949, Zevi 1973).</p>
                <p>Considering the articulation of the facade elements as a ”discourse” – in which
                    what is relevant is not only the element in itself but its position and
                    relationship with the other elements – stems from a long tradition in
                    architectural theory (Guadet 1904). Whether at the micro-scale of elements of a
                    single facade, or with the larger-scale comparison of different neighbourhoods,
                    cities or landscapes, across time and space, the identification of constitutive
                    elements of facades and their “grammatical reading” would be particularly suited
                    to a computational approach (Mitchell 1994).</p>
            </div>
            <div type="div1">
                <head>An automated method for orthophoto generation</head>
                <p>These considerations call for a set of homogeneous representations of facades,
                    free from disparities in perspectives and points of view, from which visual
                    elements can be automatically extracted and onto which comparative analyses can
                    be conducted at scale. Orthogonal views of facades are one possible homogeneous
                    solution. The so-called orthophoto is a representation of the facade as if drawn
                    on a plane with all points equally distant to the virtual camera, and is as such
                    analogous to an orthographic drawn elevation. Producing orthophotos from
                    photogrammetric surveys is a time-consuming effort and can hardly be envisioned
                    for the city-scale analyses we suggest. Instead we propose an approach which
                    automatically generates orthophotos by combining an input pointcloud with
                    footprint geometries. </p>
                <p>The pointcloud we apply our method to covers the full city of Venice, and was
                    obtained through photogrammetry on airborne images (Fig. 1). The footprint
                    geometries are provided by the City of Venice open data portal, along with the
                    geometries of canals and of the street network. We determine for each line
                    segment in the footprints whether they spatially intersect with those canal and
                    street geometries; this permits us to identify which segments correspond
                    canal-side or street-side facades (Fig. 2). Each point in the point cloud is
                    then labelled with the facade it belongs to (if any). To account for the depth
                    of the facade (which is flattened in any orthophoto), we allow for a small
                    buffer around the facade segment. </p>
                <p>At the end of this process, a set of 3D coloured points is associated to each
                    facade segment. This set needs to be rotated around the <hi rend="italic">z</hi>-axis, so that the plotting plane of the photo is properly orthogonal to
                    the vision axis. Applying Principal Component Analysis to the set of points
                    permits us to identify the dominant axes, and as such to reduce points from
                    three dimensions ( <hi rend="italic">x, y, z</hi>) to two ( <hi rend="italic">x’, z</hi>). The orthophoto is finally obtained by scatter plotting the
                    points in these reprojected coordinates. </p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic n="1001" width="16.002cm" height="9.33273611111111cm" url="Pictures/1db72668c8ae0e78a790afd09e582588.png" rend="inline"/>
                    <head>Figure 1. Photogrammetric model of Venice obtained from airborne imagery</head>
                </figure>
                <figure>
                    <graphic n="1002" width="16.002cm" height="9.233958333333334cm" url="Pictures/83f17343e138127bbf3acef9d6819400.png" rend="inline"/>
                    <head>Figure 2. Distribution of canal-side (in blue) and street-side (in red) facades
                    on the main island of Venice.</head>
                </figure>
                <p>In this way, the facade orthophotos of more than 8,000 buildings were extracted,
                    forming the first complete set of the facades of the city. As an example, the
                    orthophotos of the 156 facades in direct contact with the Canal Grande are shown
                    in (Fig. 3), ordered by height. The applicability of our method to smaller-scale
                    pointclouds was also successfully tested on a denser photogrammetric model made
                    from street-level images (Fig. 4). This complementarity of scale and densities
                    is valuable, as photogrammetric campaigns can be more easily conducted on site
                    to overcome local occlusions or lower point density in the airborne model. </p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic n="1003" width="16.002cm" height="9.597319444444445cm" url="Pictures/8d53bd85872f8d441fec38fdaa25fbd6.png" rend="inline"/>
                    <head>Figure 3. Orthophotos of 156 facades on the Canal
                        Grande obtained following the automatic division of a city-scale
                        photogrammetric model.</head>
                </figure>
                <figure>
                    <graphic n="1004" width="16.002cm" height="12.975166666666667cm" url="Pictures/a85de9fc3b4e7f926f92c9efe4c4b652.png" rend="inline"/>
                    <head>Figure 4. Automatically produced orthophotos of four
                        buildings from a pointcloud obtained by street-level photogrammetry of the
                        Campo Santa Margherita</head>
                </figure>
            </div>
            <div type="div1">
                <head>Research perspectives: Venetian architectural history at the
                    large-scale</head>
                <p>This proposed pipeline makes possible, for the first time, the extraction of
                    orthophotos for all the facades of a city. Applied to Venice, the creation of
                    such very large homogeneous facade corpora opens up new avenues of research for
                    its architectural history. </p>
                <p>A first study could consist in the exhaustive analysis of dimensions across the
                    city, considering not only the landmarks of the city but also the larger mass of
                    buildings considered ‘minor’. Dimensional analysis makes it possible to
                    recognise any proportional specificities of the best-known buildings, but above
                    all to comparatively assess the dimensional structure (e.g. the number of
                    storeys and the ratio between the height and width of facades) of the entire
                    urban fabric in an attempt to understand its statistical dimensional
                    distribution and more broadly, some of the fundamental characteristics of the
                    Venetian urban space. </p>
                <p>The facade orthophotos can also be
                    input into a subsequent segmentation algorithm through which individual elements
                    are identified and extracted (Murtiyoso et al. 2021). From there, another
                    possible approach is the geometric-proportional analysis of the facade as a
                    complex syntax of these individual elements. This classic methodology of facade
                    analysis has also been attempted for the vernacular architecture of Venetian <hi rend="italic">palazzetti</hi> (Goy 1989). This type of analysis is
                    particularly interesting when attempting to reread the iconic architecture of
                    large buildings as a repertoire of prototypical forms that can be redistributed
                    to the architecture of the outlying lagoon landscape. The segmentation of the
                    facades elements of the 8,657 buildings in the city would allow a comprehensive
                    computational approach to assess the propagation of certain architectural
                    motifs, as well as the density and popularity of certain rules of geometric
                    proportionality among Venetian facades. </p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliogr">
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Bonfait, Olivier</author> / <author>Courtin, Antoine</author> / <author>Klammt, Anne</author> 
                        (2021): “Humanités Numériques : de nouveaux récits en histoire de l’art ?
                        Introduction”, in:
                        <hi rend="italic">Histoire de l’art, </hi>87: 5-16. </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Goy, Richard</author> (1989): <hi rend="italic">Venetian
                            Vernacular Architecture: Traditional Housing in the Venetian
                        Lagoon</hi>. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press. </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Guadet, Julien</author> (1904): <hi rend="italic">Éléments et
                            Théorie de l’Architecture. Cours Professé à l’École Nationale et
                            Spéciale des Beaux-Arts</hi>. Paris: Aulanier. </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Mitchell, William J.</author> (1994): <hi rend="italic">The
                            Logic of Architecture</hi>. Cambridge: MIT Press. </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Murtiyoso, Arnadi</author> / <author>Lhenry, C.</author> / <author>Landes, Tania</author> / <author>Grussenmeyer, Pierre</author> / <author>Alby, Emmanuel</author>  (2021): “Semantic
                        Segmentation for Building Facade 3D Point Cloud from 2D Orthophoto Images
                        using Transfer Learning”, in: <hi rend="italic">The International Archives
                            of the Photogrammetry, Remote Sensing and Spatial Information
                            Sciences</hi>, XLIII-B2-2021:201–206. </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Radding, Charles M.</author> / <author>Clark, William W.</author>  (1992): <hi rend="italic">Medieval Architecture, Medieval Learning: Builders and
                            Masters in the Age of Romanesque and Gothic</hi>. New Haven: Yale
                        University Press. </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Savorra, Massimiliano</author> (2006): <hi rend="italic">Storia
                            Visiva dell’Architettura Italiana, 1400-1700</hi>. Milano: Electa. </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Trincanato, Egle Renata</author> (1948): <hi rend="italic">Venezia Minore</hi>. Venezia: Fillipi editore. </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Zevi, Bruno</author> (1949): <hi rend="italic">Saper Vedere
                            l’Architettura: Saggio sull’Interpretazione Spaziale
                            dell’Architettura</hi>. Torino: Einaudi. </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Zevi, Bruno</author> (1973): <hi rend="italic">Il Linguaggio
                            Moderno dell’Architettura: Guida al Codice Anticlassico</hi>. Torino:
                        Einaudi. </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text></TEI>