<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_allPlus.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_allPlus.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Kaleidoscopic Patterns of Protest: Qualifying and Quantifying Visual and
                    Textual (Self-)Representations in Eastern European Protest Cultures</title>
                <author n="HowanitzGernotHOWANITZ_Gernot_Kaleidoscopic_Patterns_of_Protest__Qualifyin.xml"><persName n="HowanitzGernot">
                        <surname>Howanitz</surname>
                        <forename>Gernot</forename>
                    </persName><affiliation>U of Innsbruck, Austria</affiliation><email>gernot.howanitz@uibk.ac.at</email></author><meeting><date from-iso="2023-07-10" to-iso="2023-07-14"/><title>Digital Humanities 2023. Collaboration as Opportunity</title><placeName>Graz</placeName></meeting>
                <author n="KaltseisMagdalenaHOWANITZ_Gernot_Kaleidoscopic_Patterns_of_Protest__Qualifyin.xml"><persName n="KaltseisMagdalena">
                        <surname>Kaltseis</surname>
                        <forename>Magdalena</forename>
                    </persName><affiliation>U of Innsbruck, Austria</affiliation><email>magdalena.kaltseis@uibk.ac.at</email></author><meeting><date from-iso="2023-07-10" to-iso="2023-07-14"/><title>Digital Humanities 2023. Collaboration as Opportunity</title><placeName>Graz</placeName></meeting>
            </titleStmt>
            
            <publicationStmt><publisher><orgName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1137284463">Zentrum für Informationsmodellierung
                    - Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities, Karl-Franzens-Universität
                    Graz</orgName></publisher><date when="2023">2023</date><pubPlace>Graz</pubPlace><availability><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">Creative Commons BY
                    4.0</licence></availability></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title>Digital Humanities 2023: Book of Abstracts</title><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-9256-0958"><forename>Walter</forename><surname>Scholger</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>University of Graz</orgName><placeName>Graz, Austria</placeName></affiliation><email>walter.scholger@uni-graz.at</email></editor><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-1726-1712"><forename>Georg</forename><surname>Vogeler</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>University of Graz</orgName><placeName>Graz, Austria</placeName></affiliation><email>georg.vogeler@uni-graz.at</email></editor><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-3919-993X"><forename>Toma</forename><surname>Tasovac</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>Belgrade Center for Digital Humanities</orgName><placeName>Belgrade, Serbia</placeName></affiliation><email>ttasovac@humanistika.org</email></editor><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-4593-059X"><forename>Anne</forename><surname>Baillot</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>Le Mans Université</orgName><placeName>Le Mans, France</placeName></affiliation><email>anne.baillot@univ-lemans.fr</email></editor><respStmt><resp>Data Management</resp><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0009-0007-9019-8215"><forename>Elisabeth</forename><surname>Raunig</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Management</resp><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-1438-3236"><forename>Martina</forename><surname>Scholger</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Management</resp><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-9116-0402"><forename>Elisabeth</forename><surname>Steiner</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Curation</resp><persName><forename>Johanna</forename><surname>Ofenauer</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Curation</resp><persName><forename>Christina</forename><surname>Burgstaller</surname></persName></respStmt><idno type="DOI">10.5281/zenodo.7961822</idno></seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="DHCONVALIDATOR" version="1.22">
                    <label>DHConvalidator</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc><abstract><p>In the last ten years, massive protests against the government and/or unfair elections took place in all three Eastern Slavic countries—Russia (2011/12), Ukraine (2014), and Belarus (2020). In 2022, protesters demonstrated against Russia's invasion of Ukraine. All these protests were mainly organized via social networks, were disseminated in independent media and countered by the official state-owned media. Thus, visual (self-)representations of the protest cultures must be recognized as an integral part of the protests proper.
Our project unites close and distant viewing to assess how kaleidoscopic patterns of protest emerge from the constant recombination of specific visual symbols such as banners, flags, slogans, or people marching in the streets. Not only are we interested in a general description of visual and textual (self-)representations of protest in Eastern Europe but we also analyze the patterns of specific protest cultures to describe their symbolic repertoire. In order to achieve this, we build a corpus of visual and textual (self-)representations of protest. We then use deep learning to identify specific symbols in the corpus. These results are utilized to (1) visualize and analyze the differences between official and user-generated content, traditional and new media, and individual countries, and (2) to select specific images and video clips for a qualitative multimodal discourse analysis.</p></abstract><langUsage><language ident="en">English</language></langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="category">
                    <term>Paper</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="subcategory">
                    <term>Poster</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="keywords">
                    <term>Visual Media</term>
                    <term>Protest Cultures</term>
                    <term>Eastern Europe</term>
                    <term>Distant Viewing</term>
                    <term>Multimodal Discourse Analysis</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="topics">
                    <term>artificial intelligence and machine learning</term>
                    <term>mixed-media analysis</term>
                    <term>semantic analysis</term>
                    <term>social media analysis and methods</term>
                    <term>Cultural studies</term>
                    <term>Media studies</term>
                    <term>Central/Eastern European Studies</term>
                    
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader><text>
        <body>

            <div>
                <head>Motivation</head>
                <p><lb/>This poster presentation aims to introduce the project ‘Kaleidoscopic
                        Patterns of Protest’, which analyzes visual and textual
                        (self-)representations of Eastern European protest cultures both
                        qualitatively and quantitatively. This project is funded by the Austrian
                        Academy of Sciences and starts in January 2023. <lb/><lb/>In the last ten years, massive protests against the government and/or
                        unfair elections took place in all three Eastern Slavic countries—Russia
                        (2011/12), Ukraine (2014), and Belarus (2020). More recently, the Russian
                        invasion of Ukraine in February 2022 led to anti-war protests in Russia,
                        Ukraine and Belarus as well as many other countries around the world. All
                        these protests were mainly organized via social networks (cf. Smyth &amp;
                        Oates 2015; Onuch 2015), disseminated in independent media and countered by
                        the official state-owned media. Thus, visual (self-)representations of the
                        protest cultures must be recognized as an integral part of the protests
                        proper: Symbols and slogans are used to spread the ideas and claims of the
                        protesting people, which is why protests can be characterized as a
                        “communicative act” per se (Kuße 2021). In the Russian protests of 2011/12,
                        for example, white ribbons signified an anti-governmental stance, as opposed
                        to ‘official’ and pro-government black-orange Saint George’s ribbons. During
                        the Maidan protests in Ukraine, symbols of nationalist and right-wing
                        parties were present as was the flag of Europe. In Belarus, the
                        white-red-white flag served as the main symbol of anti-government protests
                        (cf. Gaufman 2021). This flag had been replaced by a flag similar to the old
                        Soviet one after a controversial referendum in 1995 and had since then
                        remained a symbol of the Belarusian opposition (cf. Bekus 2021). </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Methods</head>
                <p><lb/><lb/>In order to capture the Kaleidoscopic Patterns of Protest in Eastern
                        Slavic countries, we zoom in on three different types of media: (1) the
                        self-representation of different protest cultures as disseminated on blogs,
                        YouTube channels, and social networks, (2) the official representations of
                        the protest cultures, in state-run and independent news broadcasts, and (3)
                        the cinematic representation of the protest cultures in feature-length
                        documentaries. Because of these different perspectives we metaphorically
                        speak of ‘kaleidoscopic patterns of protest’ that our project aims to make
                        visible. In order to achieve that we combine automatic symbol recognition
                        using artificial neural networks (R-CNN) with multimodal discourse analysis
                        (MDA). With this approach we follow N. K. Hayles’ (2010) combination of
                        “close”, “machine” and “hyper reading”; applied to visual media, “machine
                        reading” becomes Arnold/Tilton’s (2019) “distant viewing”. <lb/><lb/>Relying on “distant viewing” is necessary because of the massive size
                        of the corpus. Since February 2022 we have collected roughly 120,000 YouTube
                        videos about Belarus, Russia and Ukraine including all available metadata—as
                        of now, the total run time of these videos amounts to roughly two years.
                        This video corpus is searched for nationalist symbols from Eastern Europe by
                        a self-trained neural network. Training the network ourselves is necessary
                        insofar as freely available pretrained networks do not bring the necessary
                        domain-specific knowledge. The example in Fig. 1 shows how the pretrained
                        network can describe the basic configuration of the video frame; however,
                        the flags that are our main concern are not recognized or are recognized
                        incorrectly. The context-specific information is thus provided by our own
                        network, whose beta version we have already published (Howanitz/Radisch
                        2022). <lb/></p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic n="1001" width="16.002cm" height="8.212547222222222cm" url="Pictures/1f0b91954d51fb7711ab2953c9d97111.png" rend="inline"/>
                    <head>Fig. 1: Sample frame from a YouTube video (left), annotations by a
                        pre-trained net for panoptic segmentation (center), annotations of our
                        self-trained net (right</head>
                </figure>
                <p>The results of symbol
                        recognition are first evaluated, visualized, and then processed for MDA in
                        MAXQDA. Finally, we use MDA to analyze selected videos to investigate the
                        context, the actors and their roles, and the interaction of verbal and
                        visual information. In doing so, we focus on the questions of which general
                        patterns of visual and textual (self-)representations of protest are
                        recognizable, which similarities and differences there are between the
                        individual countries as well as between different media, and on the question
                        of how protest symbols and slogans are (re-)contextualized in the respective
                        media.</p>
            </div>

            <div>
                <head>Goals</head>
                <p><lb/>The aim of our project is on the one hand to provide a best practice
                        example for the analysis of a large visual corpus. Furthermore, we explore
                        visual and textual (self-)representations of protest cultures in Eastern
                        Europe and investigate how images and texts are (re)used in different media
                        and contexts. Finally, our project also provides a snapshot of different
                        Eastern European protest cultures and answers the question of what remains
                        of the protests after a certain period of time has passed: Especially in
                        authoritarian states like Belarus and Russia, it cannot be assumed that
                        state media preserve the memory of anti-government protests. </p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliogr">
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Arnold, T.</author> / <author>Tilton, L.</author> 
                         (2019): “Distant Viewing: Analyzing Large Visual Corpora”. DSH, fqz013, <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1093/digitalsh/fqz013">https://doi.org/10.1093/digitalsh/fqz013</ref> [last access 4 November 2022].
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Gaufman, E.</author>
                         (2021): “The gendered iconography of Belarus protest”. New Perspectives, 29(1), 80–89.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Hayles, N. K.</author>
                         (2010): “How We Read: Close, Hyper, Machine”. ADE Bulletin, 150, 62–79.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Howanitz, G.</author> / <author>Radisch, E.</author> 
                         (2022): “Nationalist(ic) Symbols from Eastern Europe: Deep Watching Demo Scripts”. Github.com, 21.2.2022 (v1.0.0). Online: <ref target="https://github.com/ghowa/nationalistic-symbols">https://github.com/ghowa/nationalistic-symbols</ref> [last access 4 November 2022].
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Kuße, H.</author>
                         (2021) (Ed.): 
                        <hi rend="italic">Kommunikacija v ėpochu
                            protestov</hi>
                        . Berlin: Peter
                            Lang.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Onuch, O.</author>
                         (2015): 
                        <hi rend="italic">EuroMaidan protests in Ukraine:
                            social media versus social networks</hi>
                        . Problems of
                            Post-communism, 62(4), 217–235
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Smyth, R.</author> / <author>Oates, R.</author> 
                         (2015): 
                        <hi rend="italic">Mind the gaps: media use and mass action in Russia. </hi>
                        Europe-Asia Studies,
                            67(2), 285–305.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Szostek, J.</author>
                         (2018): The mass media and Russia’s “sphere of interests”: mechanisms of regional hegemony in Belarus and Ukraine. Geopolitics, 23(2), 307–329.
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text></TEI>