<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_allPlus.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_allPlus.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Creating digital collections of the ancient epigraphic heritage in Bulgaria
                    through collaboration </title>
                <author n="IlievDimitarILIEV_Dimitar_Creating_digital_collections_of_the_ancient_ep.xml"><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-5231-818X" n="IlievDimitar">
                        <surname>Iliev</surname>
                        <forename>Dimitar</forename>
                    </persName><affiliation>St. Kliment Ohridski University of Sofia, Bulgaria</affiliation><email>diiliev@uni-sofia.bg</email></author><meeting><date from-iso="2023-07-10" to-iso="2023-07-14"/><title>Digital Humanities 2023. Collaboration as Opportunity</title><placeName>Graz</placeName></meeting>
                <author n="SharankovNicolayILIEV_Dimitar_Creating_digital_collections_of_the_ancient_ep.xml"><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-3085-2813" n="SharankovNicolay">
                        <surname>Sharankov</surname>
                        <forename>Nicolay</forename>
                    </persName><affiliation>St. Kliment Ohridski University of Sofia, Bulgaria</affiliation><email>n.sharankov@uni-sofia.bg</email></author><meeting><date from-iso="2023-07-10" to-iso="2023-07-14"/><title>Digital Humanities 2023. Collaboration as Opportunity</title><placeName>Graz</placeName></meeting>
            </titleStmt>
            
            <publicationStmt><publisher><orgName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1137284463">Zentrum für Informationsmodellierung
                    - Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities, Karl-Franzens-Universität
                    Graz</orgName></publisher><date when="2023">2023</date><pubPlace>Graz</pubPlace><availability><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">Creative Commons BY
                    4.0</licence></availability></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title>Digital Humanities 2023: Book of Abstracts</title><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-9256-0958"><forename>Walter</forename><surname>Scholger</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>University of Graz</orgName><placeName>Graz, Austria</placeName></affiliation><email>walter.scholger@uni-graz.at</email></editor><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-1726-1712"><forename>Georg</forename><surname>Vogeler</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>University of Graz</orgName><placeName>Graz, Austria</placeName></affiliation><email>georg.vogeler@uni-graz.at</email></editor><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-3919-993X"><forename>Toma</forename><surname>Tasovac</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>Belgrade Center for Digital Humanities</orgName><placeName>Belgrade, Serbia</placeName></affiliation><email>ttasovac@humanistika.org</email></editor><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-4593-059X"><forename>Anne</forename><surname>Baillot</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>Le Mans Université</orgName><placeName>Le Mans, France</placeName></affiliation><email>anne.baillot@univ-lemans.fr</email></editor><respStmt><resp>Data Management</resp><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0009-0007-9019-8215"><forename>Elisabeth</forename><surname>Raunig</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Management</resp><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-1438-3236"><forename>Martina</forename><surname>Scholger</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Management</resp><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-9116-0402"><forename>Elisabeth</forename><surname>Steiner</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Curation</resp><persName><forename>Johanna</forename><surname>Ofenauer</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Curation</resp><persName><forename>Christina</forename><surname>Burgstaller</surname></persName></respStmt><idno type="DOI">10.5281/zenodo.7961822</idno></seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="DHCONVALIDATOR" version="1.22">
                    <label>DHConvalidator</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc><abstract><p>The paper presents the work on the Telamon and the Tituli projects which aim at creating online databases respectively of Greek and Latin epigraphic heritage from Bulgaria. The AIAX front-end service for the indexing and visualisation of EpiDoc XML files is described, as well as collaborations with different Bulgarian museums.</p></abstract><langUsage><language ident="en">English</language></langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="category">
                    <term>Paper</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="subcategory">
                    <term>Short Presentation</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="keywords">
                    <term>EpiDoc</term>
                    <term>Digital Epigraphy</term>
                    <term>Digital Classics</term>
                    <term>Museums</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="topics">
                    <term>data</term>
                    <term>object</term>
                    <term>and artefact preservation</term>
                    <term>database creation</term>
                    <term>management</term>
                    <term>and analysis</term>
                    <term>text encoding and markup language creation</term>
                    <term>deployment</term>
                    <term>and analysis</term>
                    <term>Archaeology</term>
                    <term>History</term>
                    <term>Humanities computing</term>
                    <term>Philology</term>
                    
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <p><lb/><hi rend="bold">Ancient epigraphic heritage and its corpora
                    in Bulgaria</hi></p>
            <p>The lands of today’s Bulgaria have a rich and diverse
                    epigraphic heritage from the period of Antiquity. The ancient Greek inscriptions
                    date from a time span of approximately 12 centuries, from 6<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> c. BCE to 6<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> c. CE. More than 5,000 in number, the largest part of them is published in two big corpora (Mihailov 1956-1995, Beševliev 1964). Many monuments, however, are either left outside the big collections, often scattered in inaccessible publications, or need serious revisions even when they are known and quoted. In the recent years, some publications appeared aiminf at correcting and updating some of Mihailov’s reading in <hi rend="italic">IGBulg</hi>, but they also need further expansion (Sharankov 2016).
                    The current state of the study of Latin inscriptions from Bulgaria is even more
                    complicated: there does not exist any comprehensive publication meeting modern
                    scholarly standards. The number of the Latin inscriptions is comparable to that
                    of the Greek inscriptions, although they belong to a much shorter period, from
                    the beginning of the 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> to the end of the 6<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> c. CE. Only a small fraction of them was published in what was intended as the first part of a large corpus which never materialized (Gerov 1989). Some inscriptions are included only in rather old editions with multiple errors and incomplete data, while many others still remain dispersed, obscure, or unknown to the scholarly public.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">The Telamon collection and the AIAX platform</hi></p>
            <p>Inspired by the achievements of the EpiDoc initiative and its guidelines for encoding ancient documents in TEI XNL which habe become the <hi rend="italic">de facto</hi> standard in the field (Tom Elliott / Bodard, Gabriel et al.: 2007-2022), a team of researchers at the Department of Classics to the University of Sofia, Bulgaria, initiated the creation of the <hi rend="italic">Telamon</hi> online collection of the Greek inscriptions from Bulgaria. In <hi rend="italic">Telamon</hi>, inscriptions from the large corpora and other
                    publications are gathered for the first time in one place, provided, also for
                    the first time, with metadata, translations, and commentaries in English and
                    Bulgarian, and also inspected by close personal observation (<hi rend="italic">ex autopsia</hi>) and re-interpreted in the light of new data, if needed.
                    For this purpose, the close collaboration in the team between an epigrapher, a
                    webmaster, assistants and coordinators, created a customized EpiDoc XML template
                    for the encoding of the inscriptions, as well as our own AIAX front-end platform
                    for the storage, indexing, visualization, and filtering of the collection of
                    .xml files. AIAX is partly based on the functionalities of the Epi-Doc front-end
                    service (<ref target="https://github.com/EpiDoc/EFES">https://github.com/EpiDoc/EFES</ref>), but the underlying architecture differs from it. The
                    XML code is stored in an SQL database and then processed with PHP, thus making
                    AIAX more manageable by a webmaster with the skills needed for the maintenance
                    of a generic website. The platform is light and flexible, allowing for embedded
                    maps of geo-referenced inscriptions and other improvements. It is open-source
                    and freely available for download on the project’s web page both as a server and
                    as a desktop application:<ref target="https://telamon.uni-sofia.bg/en/page/project"> </ref><ref target="https://telamon.uni-sofia.bg/en/page/project">https://telamon.uni-sofia.bg/en/page/project</ref> . Since the launch of the website, we have been actively seeking the support of various regional historical and archaeological museums to promote digital epigraphy among the museum specialists as well as to retrieve important new data for the inscriptions in our collection. So far, collaborations with several museums have been established, thus providing the wider scholarly audience using <hi rend="italic">Telamon</hi> with updated information for many inscriptions previously studied only through publications which sometimes appeared decades ago.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">The Tituli collection</hi></p>
            <p>The most fruitful among these collaborations is the one established with the National Archaeological Institute with Museum (NAIM) in Sofia which keeps the largest collection of ancient inscriptions from Bulgaria. A group of researchers at NAIM together with a part of the <hi rend="italic">Telamon</hi> team is currently working on customizations of the Telamon template and the AIAX platform and is preparing a pilot database of encoded Latin inscriptions. Building upon what is already achieved by <hi rend="italic">Telamon</hi>, the <hi rend="italic">Tituli</hi> project pays special attention to rarer types of monuments peculiar to Latin epigraphy, to the encoding and indexing for features of iconography and decoration that have generally been overlooked, as well as to developping accurate encoding and indexing of the complex titulatures of Roman emperors (a problem so far largely unsolved worldwide). For the initial part of the <hi rend="italic">Tituli</hi> project, the team has selected monuments which reflect the diversity of Latin inscriptions from Bulgaria. Preference is given to inscriptions from the huge collection of NAIM, as well as to monuments kept in several regional museums in Northern Bulgaria. Careful study and detailed documentation is made of all relevant inscriptions in order to clarify their data and authenticate or revise any existing readings in the publications.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Encoding, vocabularies, authorities</hi></p>
            <p>The template according to which the single inscriptions in both collections are encoded, then visualised, and indexed is Epi-Dox compativble and valid against the latest versions of the EpiDoc schema. However, it is customized according to the peculiarities of the local source material and the audiences targeted by both web sites. One of its prominent features is the doubling of all the elements in the metadata potentially containing text. This ensures the bilingual content of the output via the attribute <hi rend="italic">@xml:lang</hi>. The same reduplication of elements occurs within the
                    body of the text in the parts dedicated to translation and commentary. The
                    metadata concerning the material of the monument, the object types and the
                    document types are linked to authority lists containing different categories,
                    which, in turn, are adapted from the EAGLE Europeana vocabularies (<ref target="https://www.eagle-network.eu/resources/vocabularies/">https://www.eagle-network.eu/resources/vocabularies/</ref> ). The place name, ancient or modern, are as well linked to the respective gazetteers, Pleiades (<ref target="http://pleaides.stoa.org">http://pleaides.stoa.org</ref>) and Geonames (<ref target="https://www.geonames.org/">https://www.geonames.org/</ref> ). The exact locations of the monuments is displayed on maps embedded in the web sites.</p>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliogr">
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Sharankov, Nicolay</author> (2015
                            ): “
                            Notes on the Greek
                                Inscriptions from Bulgaria
                            ”, in: 
                            <hi rend="italic">Studia Classica
                                Serdicensia</hi>
                             V
                            : 
                            305-361
                            .
                        
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Mihailov, Georgi</author>
                         (1956-1995): 
                        <hi rend="italic">Inscriptiones Graecae in Bulgaria
                            repertae</hi>.
                         Sofia: BAS Publishers.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Beševliev, Veselin</author>
                         (1964): 
                        <hi rend="italic">Spätgriechische und spätlateinische
                            Inschriften aus Bulgarien</hi>.
                         Berlin: Akademie-Verlag.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Gerov, Boris</author>
                         (1989): 
                        <hi rend="italic">Inscriptiones Latinae in Bulgaria
                            repertae</hi>.
                         Sofia: University Press.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Tom Elliott</author> / <author>Bodard, Gabriel</author> / <author>Mylonas, Elli</author> / <author>Stoyanova, Simona</author> / <author>Tupman, Charlotte</author> / <author>Vanderbilt, Scott et al.</author>  (2007-2022
                            ): <hi rend="italic">EpiDoc Guidelines:
                                Ancient documents in TEI XML (Version 9)</hi>. 
                        <ref target="https://epidoc.stoa.org/gl/latest/">https://epidoc.stoa.org/gl/latest/</ref>
                        
                            [
                            04.05.2023
                            ]. 
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text></TEI>