<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_allPlus.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_allPlus.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>LEAF: Developing Streamlined Digital Scholarly Workflows with the Linked
                    Editing Academic Framework</title>
                <author n="JakackiDianeKatherineJAKACKI_Diane_Katherine_LEAF__Developing_Streamlined_Digital.xml"><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-7836-1223" n="JakackiDianeKatherine">
                        <surname>Jakacki</surname>
                        <forename>Diane Katherine</forename>
                    </persName><affiliation>Bucknell University, United States of America</affiliation><email>dkj004@bucknell.edu</email></author><meeting><date from-iso="2023-07-10" to-iso="2023-07-14"/><title>Digital Humanities 2023. Collaboration as Opportunity</title><placeName>Graz</placeName></meeting>
                <author n="BrownSusanJAKACKI_Diane_Katherine_LEAF__Developing_Streamlined_Digital.xml"><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-0267-7344" n="BrownSusan">
                        <surname>Brown</surname>
                        <forename>Susan</forename>
                    </persName><affiliation>University of Guelph, Canada</affiliation><email>sbrown@uoguelph.ca</email></author><meeting><date from-iso="2023-07-10" to-iso="2023-07-14"/><title>Digital Humanities 2023. Collaboration as Opportunity</title><placeName>Graz</placeName></meeting>
                <author n="CummingsJamesJAKACKI_Diane_Katherine_LEAF__Developing_Streamlined_Digital.xml"><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-6686-3728" n="CummingsJames">
                        <surname>Cummings</surname>
                        <forename>James</forename>
                    </persName><affiliation>Newcastle University, United Kingdom</affiliation><email>James.Cummings@newcastle.ac.uk</email></author><meeting><date from-iso="2023-07-10" to-iso="2023-07-14"/><title>Digital Humanities 2023. Collaboration as Opportunity</title><placeName>Graz</placeName></meeting>
                <author n="IlovanMihaelaJAKACKI_Diane_Katherine_LEAF__Developing_Streamlined_Digital.xml"><persName n="IlovanMihaela">
                        <surname>Ilovan</surname>
                        <forename>Mihaela</forename>
                    </persName><affiliation>University of Alberta, Canada</affiliation><email>ilovan@ualberta.ca</email></author><meeting><date from-iso="2023-07-10" to-iso="2023-07-14"/><title>Digital Humanities 2023. Collaboration as Opportunity</title><placeName>Graz</placeName></meeting>
                <author n="MilioRachelJAKACKI_Diane_Katherine_LEAF__Developing_Streamlined_Digital.xml"><persName n="MilioRachel">
                        <surname>Milio</surname>
                        <forename>Rachel</forename>
                    </persName><affiliation>Bucknell University, United States of America</affiliation><email>rtm012@bucknell.edu</email></author><meeting><date from-iso="2023-07-10" to-iso="2023-07-14"/><title>Digital Humanities 2023. Collaboration as Opportunity</title><placeName>Graz</placeName></meeting>
            </titleStmt>
            
            <publicationStmt><publisher><orgName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1137284463">Zentrum für Informationsmodellierung
                    - Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities, Karl-Franzens-Universität
                    Graz</orgName></publisher><date when="2023">2023</date><pubPlace>Graz</pubPlace><availability><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">Creative Commons BY
                    4.0</licence></availability></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title>Digital Humanities 2023: Book of Abstracts</title><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-9256-0958"><forename>Walter</forename><surname>Scholger</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>University of Graz</orgName><placeName>Graz, Austria</placeName></affiliation><email>walter.scholger@uni-graz.at</email></editor><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-1726-1712"><forename>Georg</forename><surname>Vogeler</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>University of Graz</orgName><placeName>Graz, Austria</placeName></affiliation><email>georg.vogeler@uni-graz.at</email></editor><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-3919-993X"><forename>Toma</forename><surname>Tasovac</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>Belgrade Center for Digital Humanities</orgName><placeName>Belgrade, Serbia</placeName></affiliation><email>ttasovac@humanistika.org</email></editor><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-4593-059X"><forename>Anne</forename><surname>Baillot</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>Le Mans Université</orgName><placeName>Le Mans, France</placeName></affiliation><email>anne.baillot@univ-lemans.fr</email></editor><respStmt><resp>Data Management</resp><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0009-0007-9019-8215"><forename>Elisabeth</forename><surname>Raunig</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Management</resp><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-1438-3236"><forename>Martina</forename><surname>Scholger</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Management</resp><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-9116-0402"><forename>Elisabeth</forename><surname>Steiner</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Curation</resp><persName><forename>Johanna</forename><surname>Ofenauer</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Curation</resp><persName><forename>Christina</forename><surname>Burgstaller</surname></persName></respStmt><idno type="DOI">10.5281/zenodo.7961822</idno></seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="DHCONVALIDATOR" version="1.22">
                    <label>DHConvalidator</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc><abstract><p>In this half-day workshop, participants will learn how to use different components of the Linked Editing Academic Framework (LEAF) digital scholarship production platform: encoding and annotating texts, entity tagging and reconciliation, coordinating different types of media files into compound objects and galleries, managing metadata and workflow tracking, and producing a simple collection of objects. Using sample text and image objects, with the possibility of experimenting with their own materials, participants will come away with an understanding of how LEAF supports collaborative digital scholarly production in an open-source, open-access web environment.</p></abstract><langUsage><language ident="en">English</language></langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="category">
                    <term>Paper</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="subcategory">
                    <term>Pre-Conference Workshop and Tutorial</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="keywords">
                    <term>TEI-XML</term>
                    <term>web-based editor</term>
                    <term>RDF</term>
                    <term>named entity recognition</term>
                    <term>linked open data</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="topics">
                    <term>digital publishing projects</term>
                    <term>systems</term>
                    <term>and methods</term>
                    <term>digital research infrastructures development and analysis</term>
                    <term>scholarly editing and editions development</term>
                    <term>analysis</term>
                    <term>and methods</term>
                    <term>Cultural studies</term>
                    <term>Humanities computing</term>
                    <term>Literary studies</term>
                    
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>In this half-day workshop, participants will learn how
                    to use different components of the Linked Editing Academic Framework (LEAF)
                    digital scholarship production platform: encoding and annotating texts, entity
                    tagging and reconciliation, coordinating different types of media files into
                    compound objects and galleries, managing metadata and workflow tracking, and
                    producing a simple collection of objects. Using sample text and image objects,
                    with the possibility of experimenting with their own materials, participants
                    will come away with an understanding of how LEAF supports collaborative digital
                    scholarly production in an open-source, open-access web environment, connected
                    to a linked data infrastructure</p>
            </div>
            <div type="div1">
                <head>Concept</head>
                <p>This workshop, which is aimed at both digital
                    humanities researchers and institutional library and information technology
                    administrators interested in instituting efficient scholarly production,
                    research data repository, and publication workflows, will offer participants the
                    chance to experiment with model research projects in LEAF. The workshop will
                    combine demonstration and hands-on activities to cover:</p>
                <list type="ordered">
                    <item>the basics: LEAF navigation, menus, user dashboards (hands-on);</item>
                    <item>metadata: overview of its importance, and how to create it
                        (hands-on); </item>
                    <item>scholarly curation: uploading an image and or text to being a thematic
                        collection; </item>
                    <item>born-digital scholarship: creating a document (hands-on);</item>
                    <item>semantic markup and linked data identifiers: editing, semi-automated
                        entity tagging and reconciliation (hands-on) using the LEAF-Writer TEI (XML)
                        and RDF editor (available embedded in LEAF or as a standalone
                        editor); </item>
                    <item>tracking work: adding a workflow stamp and communicating with
                        collaborators (hands-on);</item>
                    <item>project creation: creating a home page for a simple object-driven web
                        collection (hands-on);</item>
                    <item>linked data conversion: making data findable, accessible, interoperable
                        and reusable (FAIR) using the Linked Infrastructure for Networked Cultural
                        Scholarship (LINCS) (demo)</item>
                </list>
            </div>
            <div type="div1">
                <head>Background</head>
                <p>The Linked Editing Academic Framework virtual research
                    environment (LEAF) is a flexible collaborative platform that enables scholars to
                    create, publish, and preserve digital editions, born-digital scholarship,
                    digital collections, and virtual exhibits – of texts, images, audio files, and
                    videos. </p>
                <p>LEAF tackles the challenges faced by many in the DH
                    community who undertake and maintain complex research projects, whether as part
                    of a solo or small team edition or a large-scale multi-institutional collection:
                    the need to ensure that these projects remain operational and available to
                    editorial teams and audiences, at the same time encouraging new participants who
                    may or may not have digital experience to create new knowledge in dynamic and
                    iterative contexts.</p>
                <p>Adhering to the FAIR principles for enabling the reuse
                    of data (Findable, Accessible, Interoperable, and Reusable), LEAF uses
                    open-source software, open-access platforms, and open international standards
                    for best practices in text-encoding (TEI-XML) and web annotation (RDF), in a
                    Drupal 9 Islandora 2 content management and preservation system. Perhaps most
                    compelling for the ADHO community, LEAF is designed to promote sustainability by
                    aiming at a broad user base through bridging gaps between scholars who have
                    coding and encoding experience, and those who do not. LEAF gives broader
                    communities of researchers, teachers, and students the opportunity to take part
                    in digital knowledge production and open collaboration. The workshop will end
                    with an open discussion about pursuing such forms of open knowledge production
                    and collaboration. </p>
                <p>LEAF emerges from a collaboration to extend the
                    Canadian Writing Research Collaboratory (CWRC) virtual research environment that
                    has, since 2016, supported dozens of projects, including projects produced by
                    scholars and students new to digital scholarship.  It is being developed, with
                    Bucknell University and Newcastle University as founding partners, at the
                    Universities of Alberta and Guelph. LEAF will roll out its enhancement of CWRC’s
                    functionality through collaborative software development in 2023 through
                    multiple instances of the modular LEAF platform in Canada, the US, and UK.</p>
                <p>LEAF’s sister project, the Linked Infrastructure for
                    Networked Cultural Scholarship (LINCS), is dedicated to interlinking humanistic
                    research and cultural heritage data across the Semantic Web. LINCS supports the
                    development and mobilization of a suite of tools to create, search, and
                    visualize Linked Open Data (LOD). LEAF and LEAF-Writer create an accessible
                    on-ramp for LEAF users to be able to generate linked data from metadata, text,
                    and prosopographical information to contribute to the Semantic Web. Entity IDs
                    captured in LEAF-Writer can in turn create Web Annotations using RDF. LEAF users
                    will therefore be able to push to LINCS linked data based on their projects’
                    metadata, markup, and annotations.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="div1">
                <head>Features And Functions To Be Explored In Workshop</head>
                <p>Working on their own laptops (no software installation
                    is required), participants will experience various aspects of LEAF’s
                    functionality:</p>
                <list type="unordered">
                    <item>Simple Drupal collection development</item>
                    <item>Object locking/unlocking</item>
                    <item>Workflow tracking documentation</item>
                    <item>Rich text-encoding in the LEAF-Writer editor that creates both XML and/or
                        RDF</item>
                    <item>Entity tagging in NERVE, the Named Entity Recognition Vetting Environment
                        (NERVE is a named entity recognition tool developed by the Linked
                        Infrastructure for Networked Cultural Scholarship (LINCS) project);</item>
                </list>
            </div>
            <div type="div1">
                <head>Workshop Outline</head>
                <p>The workshop will be managed as follows (3 hours plus
                    breaks):</p>
                <div type="div2">
                    <head>Introductions of participants, concepts, and VRE (15 minutes)</head>
                </div>
                <div type="div2">
                    <head>Set up participants with individual LEAF project spaces (15
                        minutes)</head>
                    <div type="div3">
                        <head>Digital production phase, part 1 (90 minutes)</head>
                        <list type="unordered">
                            <item>Uploading a variety of project materials including text, image,
                                compound objects, citations, and associating metadata with
                                each</item>
                            <item>Encoding and annotating text objects using TEI and RDF
                                (LEAF-Writer)</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>BREAK (Time TBD) </p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="div3">
                        <head>Digital Production phase, part 2 (40 minutes)</head>
                        <list type="unordered">
                            <item>Using NERVE to recognize, process, and associate named entities
                                with external authorities <list type="unordered">
                                    <item>Creating a model project </item>
                                    <item>Producing published versions of those materials using
                                        Drupal blocks</item>
                                </list></item>
                            <item>LINCS demo, forthcoming LEAF development (e.g. Handwritten Text
                                Recognition), wrap-up (20 minutes)</item>
                        </list>
                    </div>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="div1">
                <head>Special Requirements</head>
                <p>Because LEAF is web-based and open-source no special
                    software or subscription is required. Participants will need a laptop and
                    wireless internet access. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="div1">
                <head>Statement Of Commitment To Diversity</head>
                <p>Workshop materials will be provided in multiple
                    languages, and attention to diversity will be given the the selection of sample
                    texts and images to ensure that a range of genders, races, and nationalities are
                    represented. Participants are also welcome to bring their own content. LEAF and
                    its tools are designed to meet accessibility standards as well as to make tools
                    more readily usable by a broader and more diverse user base than is typical in
                    the digital humanities.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="div1">
                <head>Workshop Leaders (Including Research Interests Pertaining to Workshop)</head>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Susan Brown</hi> (University of Guelph) Professor, Canada
                    Research Chair in Collaborative Digital Scholarship. Her work explores intersectional feminism, literary history, semantic
                        technologies, and online knowledge infrastructures. She directs the
                    Orlando Project, the Canadian Writing Research Collaboratory, and the Linked
                    Infrastructure for Networked Cultural Scholarship. </p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Diane Jakacki</hi> (Bucknell University) Digital Scholarship
                    Coordinator, associated faculty in Comparative &amp; Digital Humanities. At
                    Bucknell and through the Mellon Foundation-funded Liberal Arts Based Digital
                    (LAB) Editions Publishing Cooperative project, she works with faculty, students,
                    and their collaborators within and beyond Bucknell to develop and implement an
                    array of text-centric multicultural and multilingual research projects. She is
                    lead investigator of the LAB Cooperative, REED London, and currently serves as
                    the chair of the TEI’s Board of Directors. </p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">James Cummings</hi> (Newcastle University) Senior Lecturer in
                    Late Medieval Literature and Digital Humanities. His interests include the use
                    of digital technology for scholarly editing and also late-medieval performance.
                    He has a long history of involvement with the Consortium of the Text Encoding
                    Initiative and is currently an elected member to the TEI’s Board of Directors.
                    He is currently leading projects on both HTR to TEI workflows and digital
                    pedagogy, as well as a sub-project at Newcastle using LEAF.  <lb/><hi rend="bold">Mihaela Ilovan</hi> (Canadian Writing Research Collaboratory)
                    Assistant Director. A librarian and digital humanist by formation, she is the
                    technical project manager for the development of the LEAF Virtual Research
                    Environment and the coordinator for LEAF data ingestion and mapping. </p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliogr">
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Berners-Lee, Tim, et al</author> (2001): “The Semantic Web,” in
                        Scientific American, 284, 5: 28–37. </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Brown, Susan</author> (2014):  “Scaling Up Collaboration Online:
                        Towards a Collaboratory for Research on Canadian Writing,” in <hi rend="italic">International Journal of Canadian Studies</hi> 48: 233-51. </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Brown, Susan</author> / <author>Simpson, John</author>  (2015): “An Entity By Any
                        Other Name: Linked Open Data as a Basis for a Decentered, Dynamic Scholarly
                        Publishing Ecology | Scholarly and Research Communication. 6,2.
                        <ref target="https://src-online.ca/index.php/src/article/view/212">https://src-online.ca/index.php/src/article/view/212</ref>.  </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Brown, Susan</author> / <author>Simpson, John</author> / <author>the INKE Research Group</author> / <author>the CWRC project team</author>  (2015): “The Changing Culture of Humanities
                        Scholarship: Iteration, Recursion, and Versions in Scholarly Collaboration
                        Environments; Special Issue on "Building Partnerships to Transform Scholarly
                        Publishing," in
                        <hi rend="italic">Scholarly and Research Communication </hi>5.4.
                            <ref target="https://src-online.ca/index.php/src/article/view/191">https://src-online.ca/index.php/src/article/view/191</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Brown, Susan</author> / <author>Cummings, James</author> / <author>Frizzera, Luciano</author> / <author>Ilovan, Mihaela</author> / <author>Jakacki, Diane</author> / <author>Milio, Rachel</author> (2022):
                        “Engaging TEI Editors Through LEAF-Writer,” at the TEI 2022 Annual Meeting.  </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Canning, Erin</author> / <author>Brown, Susan</author> / <author>Roger, Sarah</author> / <author>Martin, Kim</author>  (2022): “The Power to Structure: Making Meaning from Metadata
                        through Ontologies,” in <hi rend="italic">Kula</hi> 6.3. </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Cope, Bill, et al.</author>, eds (2011): <hi rend="italic">Towards a Semantic Web: Connecting Knowledge in Academic Research</hi>.
                        Chandos Publishing. </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Cummings, James</author> (2019): “Opening the Book: Data Models
                        and Distractions in Digital Scholarly Editing.” <hi rend="italic">International Journal of Digital Humanities</hi>. 1, 179-193 (2019) </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Cummings, James</author> / <author>Flex, Valentina</author> / <author>Healey, Alexandra</author> / <author>Jakacki, Diane</author> / <author>Johnson, Ian</author> / <author>Pirmann,  Carrie</author>  (2022): “Evolving
                        Hands: HTR and TEI Workflows for cultural institutions,” at the TEI 2022
                        Annual Meeting. </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Eide, Øyvind</author> (2014): “Ontologies, Data Modeling, and
                        TEI.” <hi rend="italic">Journal of the Text Encoding Initiative</hi>, no.
                        Issue 8, Issue 8, Dec. 2014. <hi rend="italic">journals.openedition.org</hi>, <ref target="https://doi.org/10.4000/jtei.1191">https://doi.org/10.4000/jtei.1191</ref>. </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Jakacki, Diane</author> / <author>Brown, Susan</author> / <author>Cummings, James</author> / <author>Ilovan, Mihaela</author>  (2022): “The Linked Editing Academic Framework: Creating an
                        Editorial Environment for Collaborative Scholarship and Publication," at the
                        Digital Humanities 2022 Annual Meeting.
                        <ref target="https://youtu.be/jyCXRrfh5vk">https://youtu.be/jyCXRrfh5vk</ref>. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Islandora Digital Asset Management:
                        <ref target="https://ww.islandora.ca">https://ww.islandora.ca</ref>. </bibl>
                    <bibl>LEAF-Writer Commons:
                        <ref target="https://leaf-writer.leaf-vre.org/">https://leaf-writer.leaf-vre.org/</ref></bibl>
                    <bibl>LEAF-Writer Commons documentation:
                        <ref target="https://portal.lincsproject.ca/docs/tools/leaf-writer/leaf-writer-documentation">https://portal.lincsproject.ca/docs/tools/leaf-writer/leaf-writer-documentation</ref></bibl>
                    <bibl>Linked Infrastructure for Networked Cultural
                        Scholarship (LINCS) project. <ref target="https://lincsproject.ca">https://lincsproject.ca</ref>.</bibl>
                    <bibl>NERVE (Named Entity Recognition Vetting
                        Environment.
                        <ref target="https://portal.lincsproject.ca/docs/tools/nerve/">https://portal.lincsproject.ca/docs/tools/nerve/</ref>.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Text Encoding Initiative (TEI).
                        <ref target="https://tei-c.org/">https://tei-c.org/</ref></bibl>
                    <bibl>The Resource Description Framework (RDF).
                        <ref target="https://www.w3.org/RDF/">https://www.w3.org/RDF/</ref></bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text></TEI>