<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_allPlus.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_allPlus.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Toward establishing the standard digital public history framework:
                    information platform for Japanese historical materials</title>
                <author n="KamedaAkihiroKAMEDA_Akihiro_Toward_establishing_the_standard_digital_publ.xml"><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-5439-6456" n="KamedaAkihiro">
                        <surname>Kameda</surname>
                        <forename>Akihiro</forename>
                    </persName><affiliation>National Museum of Japanese History, Japan</affiliation><email>cm3ak@outlook.com</email></author><meeting><date from-iso="2023-07-10" to-iso="2023-07-14"/><title>Digital Humanities 2023. Collaboration as Opportunity</title><placeName>Graz</placeName></meeting>
                <author n="GotoMakotoKAMEDA_Akihiro_Toward_establishing_the_standard_digital_publ.xml"><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-9473-7673" n="GotoMakoto">
                        <surname>Goto</surname>
                        <forename>Makoto</forename>
                    </persName><affiliation>National Museum of Japanese History, Japan</affiliation><email>m-goto@rekihaku.ac.jp</email></author><meeting><date from-iso="2023-07-10" to-iso="2023-07-14"/><title>Digital Humanities 2023. Collaboration as Opportunity</title><placeName>Graz</placeName></meeting>
            </titleStmt>
            
            <publicationStmt><publisher><orgName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1137284463">Zentrum für Informationsmodellierung
                    - Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities, Karl-Franzens-Universität
                    Graz</orgName></publisher><date when="2023">2023</date><pubPlace>Graz</pubPlace><availability><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">Creative Commons BY
                    4.0</licence></availability></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title>Digital Humanities 2023: Book of Abstracts</title><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-9256-0958"><forename>Walter</forename><surname>Scholger</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>University of Graz</orgName><placeName>Graz, Austria</placeName></affiliation><email>walter.scholger@uni-graz.at</email></editor><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-1726-1712"><forename>Georg</forename><surname>Vogeler</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>University of Graz</orgName><placeName>Graz, Austria</placeName></affiliation><email>georg.vogeler@uni-graz.at</email></editor><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-3919-993X"><forename>Toma</forename><surname>Tasovac</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>Belgrade Center for Digital Humanities</orgName><placeName>Belgrade, Serbia</placeName></affiliation><email>ttasovac@humanistika.org</email></editor><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-4593-059X"><forename>Anne</forename><surname>Baillot</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>Le Mans Université</orgName><placeName>Le Mans, France</placeName></affiliation><email>anne.baillot@univ-lemans.fr</email></editor><respStmt><resp>Data Management</resp><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0009-0007-9019-8215"><forename>Elisabeth</forename><surname>Raunig</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Management</resp><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-1438-3236"><forename>Martina</forename><surname>Scholger</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Management</resp><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-9116-0402"><forename>Elisabeth</forename><surname>Steiner</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Curation</resp><persName><forename>Johanna</forename><surname>Ofenauer</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Curation</resp><persName><forename>Christina</forename><surname>Burgstaller</surname></persName></respStmt><idno type="DOI">10.5281/zenodo.7961822</idno></seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="DHCONVALIDATOR" version="1.22">
                    <label>DHConvalidator</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc><abstract><p>This report describes the methodology of public history practice based on a data infrastructure system for historical materials in Japan. We especially want to discuss activities of surveying, cataloging, and digitizing materials, and curation, classification, filtering, and publication of data, utilizing our data infrastructure.</p></abstract><langUsage><language ident="en">English</language></langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="category">
                    <term>Paper</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="subcategory">
                    <term>Poster</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="keywords">
                    <term>Public History</term>
                    <term>Design of Research Process</term>
                    <term>Data publication</term>
                    <term>Privacy and Personality Rights</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="topics">
                    <term>data publishing projects</term>
                    <term>systems</term>
                    <term>and methods</term>
                    <term>digital research infrastructures development and analysis</term>
                    <term>metadata standards</term>
                    <term>systems</term>
                    <term>and methods</term>
                    <term>public humanities collaborations and methods</term>
                    <term>History</term>
                    <term>Humanities computing</term>
                    
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <p>This report describes the methodology of public history
                practice based on a data infrastructure system for historical materials in Japan. In
                the 2020s, researchers, local governments, and industries started collaborating to
                conduct historical research, primarily through preserving and understanding local
                historical materials. Although the term “public history” has a multifaceted meaning
                worldwide, we define public history as an attempt to conduct research not only with
                professional historians but also with non-professional researchers and citizens.
                Some digital archives, such as Japan Disasters Digital Archive [Gerster et al.
                2022], have educational functions for citizens. Still, we want them to be not only
                recipients but also co-creators of historical knowledge. Specifically, we realize
                this with a data infrastructure system named “khirin,” which stores, connects, and
                publishes historical materials with various representations and formats like RDF,
                IIIF, and TEI.</p>
            <figure>
                <graphic n="1001" width="15.000111111111112cm" height="7.475361111111111cm" url="Pictures/c645f7bbc04c4aa3bb24337473ca15d8.png" rend="inline"/>
                <head>Fig. 1 Comprehensive research on data handling around the
                “khirin”</head>
            </figure>
            <p>Using khirin as a hub, we have been discussing and solving
                various problems related to historical collaborations (Fig. 1). In Japan, there are
                many historical materials in each local area, even in the houses or private storages
                of local citizens. The first process of our methodology is surveying and cataloging,
                in other words, registering historical materials stored in such places. We first go
                there, gather historical materials information, and catalog them. Building a network
                between local governments or universities is helpful in the activity, and we
                collaborate with Siryo-net(literally translated as Network for Historical Materials
                http://siryo-net.jp/). The second process is digitization and curation of them. This
                process can be subdivided into the types described in Fig. 2. The third process is
                data classification, filtering, and publication (Fig. 3). In this process, we must
                assess copyrights, and privacy and personality rights of materials. Then, as a
                fourth process, we finally research with that data. Historians tend to read the
                original material directly and, based on the contents, search related materials or
                research papers; Researchers in other domains, such as informatics, linguistics, or
                seismology, tend to extract information from contents or metadata in terms of their
                interest first; Citizens generally wants to grasp the whole image of the area,
                specific person, or cultural heritage, and translated or visual materials help their
                understandings. Therefore, we must prepare data for practical uses: 4.1 Data for
                historians, 4.2 Data for researchers other than historians, and 4.3 Data for
                citizens. Machine-readable data created in Step 2, adhering to international
                standards, enables flexible and swift data transformation, presentation, and
                curation for specific purposes. The fifth step is making the research results
                reusable by archiving result materials in khirin. We suppose three types of results:
                5.1 Outputs, 5.2 Outcomes, and 5.3 Impacts; these terms are used in the context of
                research impact assessment [Hinrichs-Krapels et al. 2016]. Each type of result has a
                corresponding style of representation: paper publication, exhibition, and news
                articles, respectively. All the processes and khirin as facilitation platforms for
                these processes will be examined in historical research practices regarding
                integrity in historical studies and the inclusion of researchers in other domains
                and citizens.</p>
            <figure>
                <graphic n="1002" width="15.000111111111112cm" height="7.8105cm" url="Pictures/cc4f981383666a0337516af9ab6d2413.png" rend="inline"/>
                <head>Fig. 2 Digitization and Curation</head>
            </figure>
            <figure>
                <graphic n="1003" width="15.000111111111112cm" height="6.536972222222222cm" url="Pictures/8282887ed8185da4c30a193793ac7427.png" rend="inline"/>
                <head>Fig. 3 Data Classification, Filtering, and Publication</head>
            </figure>
            <p>Khirin inputs, outputs, and represents information for
                each process. To practice public history, we must prepare sufficient open data
                available for citizens to conduct research. Going further back the processes, not
                only directly human-readable data but also machine-readable data compiled and
                visualized from the perspective of meaning and statistics will play an essential
                role in helping citizens understand historical materials. While working on
                collaborative projects between academia, local government, and industry, we still
                implement public history using khirin. Therefore, to create a collaborative approach
                with the public and to make the process of opening up the data to the public more
                efficient, we would like to discuss the possibilities based on each piece of data.
                From Data Management Plan (DMP) templates to FAIR Implementation Profiles checklists
                [Schultes et al. 2020], we plan to adopt a documentation-based assessment of whether
                the system and data can support research activities.</p>
            <p>Khirin was not merely created as a database system but as
                an information hub for comprehensive historical research. While we have completed
                the implementation of the system, the process of data input, utilization, and
                evaluation is still in its early stages and will be addressed moving forward. The
                methodology proposed above will also update the way of thinking and analyzing in the
                historical research process and establish the standard digital public history
                framework.</p>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliogr">
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Gerster, J., Boret S. P., Morimoto, R., Gordon, A., Shibayama, A. </author>(2022):
                        The potential of disaster digital archives in disaster education: The case
                        of the Japan disasters digital archive (JDA) and its geo-location function,
                        International Journal of Disaster Risk Reduction, Volume 77, DOI:
                        10.1016/j.ijdrr.2022.103085 </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Hinrichs-Krapels, S., Grant, J.</author> (2016): “Exploring the
                        effectiveness, efficiency and equity (3e’s) of research and research impact
                        assessment”. <hi rend="italic">Palgrave Communications</hi> 2, 16090. DOI:
                        10.1057/palcomms.2016.90 </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Schultes, E., Magagna, B., Hettne, K.M., Pergl, R.,
                            Suchánek, M., Kuhn, T.</author> (2020): “Reusable FAIR Implementation
                        Profiles as Accelerators of FAIR Convergence”. In: Grossmann, G., Ram, S.
                        (eds) <hi rend="italic">Advances in Conceptual Modeling</hi>. ER 2020.
                        Lecture Notes in Computer Science, vol 12584. Springer, Cham. DOI:
                        10.1007/978-3-030-65847-2_13 </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text></TEI>