<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_allPlus.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_allPlus.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Connecting Art and Science for Humanities Research: Mapping Color in
                    History</title>
                <author n="KimJinahKIM_Jinah_Connecting_Art_and_Science_for_Humanities_Research.xml"><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-0367-6447" n="KimJinah">
                        <surname>Kim</surname>
                        <forename>Jinah</forename>
                    </persName><affiliation>Harvard University, United States of America</affiliation><email>jinahkim@fas.harvard.edu</email></author><meeting><date from-iso="2023-07-10" to-iso="2023-07-14"/><title>Digital Humanities 2023. Collaboration as Opportunity</title><placeName>Graz</placeName></meeting>
                <author n="CrawfordColeKIM_Jinah_Connecting_Art_and_Science_for_Humanities_Research.xml"><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-8347-0096" n="CrawfordCole">
                        <surname>Crawford</surname>
                        <forename>Cole</forename>
                    </persName><affiliation>Harvard University, United States of America</affiliation><email>cole_crawford@fas.harvard.edu</email></author><meeting><date from-iso="2023-07-10" to-iso="2023-07-14"/><title>Digital Humanities 2023. Collaboration as Opportunity</title><placeName>Graz</placeName></meeting>
                <author n="SinghalRashmiKIM_Jinah_Connecting_Art_and_Science_for_Humanities_Research.xml"><persName n="SinghalRashmi">
                        <surname>Singhal</surname>
                        <forename>Rashmi</forename>
                    </persName><affiliation>Harvard University, United States of America</affiliation><email>rsinghal@fas.harvard.edu</email></author><meeting><date from-iso="2023-07-10" to-iso="2023-07-14"/><title>Digital Humanities 2023. Collaboration as Opportunity</title><placeName>Graz</placeName></meeting>
                <author n="StewardJeffKIM_Jinah_Connecting_Art_and_Science_for_Humanities_Research.xml"><persName n="StewardJeff">
                        <surname>Steward</surname>
                        <forename>Jeff</forename>
                    </persName><affiliation>Harvard University, United States of America</affiliation><email>jeff_steward@harvard.edu</email></author><meeting><date from-iso="2023-07-10" to-iso="2023-07-14"/><title>Digital Humanities 2023. Collaboration as Opportunity</title><placeName>Graz</placeName></meeting>
            </titleStmt>
            
            <publicationStmt><publisher><orgName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1137284463">Zentrum für Informationsmodellierung
                    - Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities, Karl-Franzens-Universität
                    Graz</orgName></publisher><date when="2023">2023</date><pubPlace>Graz</pubPlace><availability><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">Creative Commons BY
                    4.0</licence></availability></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title>Digital Humanities 2023: Book of Abstracts</title><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-9256-0958"><forename>Walter</forename><surname>Scholger</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>University of Graz</orgName><placeName>Graz, Austria</placeName></affiliation><email>walter.scholger@uni-graz.at</email></editor><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-1726-1712"><forename>Georg</forename><surname>Vogeler</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>University of Graz</orgName><placeName>Graz, Austria</placeName></affiliation><email>georg.vogeler@uni-graz.at</email></editor><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-3919-993X"><forename>Toma</forename><surname>Tasovac</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>Belgrade Center for Digital Humanities</orgName><placeName>Belgrade, Serbia</placeName></affiliation><email>ttasovac@humanistika.org</email></editor><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-4593-059X"><forename>Anne</forename><surname>Baillot</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>Le Mans Université</orgName><placeName>Le Mans, France</placeName></affiliation><email>anne.baillot@univ-lemans.fr</email></editor><respStmt><resp>Data Management</resp><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0009-0007-9019-8215"><forename>Elisabeth</forename><surname>Raunig</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Management</resp><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-1438-3236"><forename>Martina</forename><surname>Scholger</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Management</resp><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-9116-0402"><forename>Elisabeth</forename><surname>Steiner</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Curation</resp><persName><forename>Johanna</forename><surname>Ofenauer</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Curation</resp><persName><forename>Christina</forename><surname>Burgstaller</surname></persName></respStmt><idno type="DOI">10.5281/zenodo.7961822</idno></seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="DHCONVALIDATOR" version="1.22">
                    <label>DHConvalidator</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc><abstract><p>Mapping Color in HIstory compiles pigment analysis data from existing and on-going research on scientific analysis of pigments for historical research. As a digital humanities project at the intersection of art and science, multidisciplinary collaboration is at its heart. The paper will introduce the project and discuss methods and contributions.</p></abstract><langUsage><language ident="en">English</language></langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="category">
                    <term>Paper</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="subcategory">
                    <term>Long Presentation</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="keywords">
                    <term>mapping pigment</term>
                    <term>digital art history</term>
                    <term>south asian painting</term>
                    <term>IIIF</term>
                    <term>conservation science</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="topics">
                    <term>annotation structures</term>
                    <term>systems</term>
                    <term>and methods</term>
                    <term>database creation</term>
                    <term>management</term>
                    <term>and analysis</term>
                    <term>linked (open) data</term>
                    <term>metadata standards</term>
                    <term>systems</term>
                    <term>and methods</term>
                    <term>Art history</term>
                    <term>Book and print history</term>
                    <term>History of science</term>
                    <term>South Asian studies</term>
                    
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <head>Preamble</head>
                <p>
                    What color is the Hindu God Krishna? “Blue” would be an answer from anyone
                    familiar with the iconography today, but which blue? How Krishna was
                    pictorialized in color differed greatly across time and space. Our color
                    perception is not only subjective but also period and culture- specific. The
                    latter specificity has much to do with artisanal practices in making and using
                    colorants in the art of painting. In searching for answers to the questions
                    about historical usage of colorants (pigments and organic dyestuffs) in the
                    painting traditions of South Asia, we face two immediate challenges: first,
                    little is known about the history of pigments in Asia as the existing pigment
                    studies and databases rely heavily on the data drawn from Western Art (see the
                    discussion in Kim 2021; Krekel et al. 2006; Feller 1986) second, many museums
                    with conservation labs have been conducting their analytical studies on pigments
                    but the data is rarely shared beyond the immediate circles or shared in the
                    manner that students of humanities and general public cannot access easily (e.g.
                    Ravindran et al. 2011; Faria et al. 2017; Eremin et al. 2008). Thus, translating
                    the scientific analytical data and contextualizing the pigment analysis
                    information is the first order of business for further historical research. This
                    is what the Mapping Color in History [henceforth MCH,
                    https://mappingcolor.fas.harvard.edu] as a multidisciplinary digital humanities
                    project does. At the intersection of art and science brought together through a
                    digital humanities project, collaboration is at the heart of the MCH project.
                    This is what we would like to share in DH 2023. </p>
                
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>A three-legged stool</head>
                <p>
                    Mapping Color in HIstory is a digital platform that compiles pigment
                    analysis data from existing and on-going research on scientific analysis of
                    pigments with a capacity to add new data through collaboration with research
                    centers that are engaged in pigments analysis in Asian painting and put them in
                    a historical perspective. The MCH project builds on existing databases like the
                    Forbes pigment database and other digital humanities initiatives like the
                    Getty’s Thesaurus of Geographic Names (TGN) and Art and Architecture Thesaurus
                    (AAT) and GeoNames, and makes it possible to see pigment analysis data in the
                    geographic and historical context. <lb/>MCH takes an object-based entry method
                    for data collection instead of a pigment-based organization scheme taken in
                    existing pigment databases and publications. A database ontology developed for
                    the MCH captures the complex and multi-layered hierarchic relationship between
                    different data points, which in turn allows mapping each pigment’s appearance
                    geographically. This can help understand previously under-recognized
                    trans-regional connections not only in terms of trade (such as trade of
                    colorants and other raw materials, and even pigment recipes) but also in terms
                    of travels of religious, philosophical, and cultural ideas. MCH can help answer
                    when and where certain pigments started appearing and became popular and how it
                    relates to certain pictorial, cultural, religious, and economic practices. It
                    will also generate further research questions about local and global trade
                    connections, color symbolism, and artisanal knowledge transfer. MCH also records
                    the historical and technical information on the analysis, providing valuable
                    data on the history of analytical methods. <lb/>MCH is inherently
                    multidisciplinary as it aims to bring together scientific analysis and
                    humanistic research with computational methods and digital tools. The project
                    can be best described as a three-legged stool: its three legs are 1) digital
                    asset and software development, 2) conservation science research (core data),
                    and 3) art historical research (core data). All three legs need to be equally
                    balanced and refined to make the MCH project to function as an open research
                    platform. We are collaborating with six museums and libraries in the US and two
                    in India for generating and collecting analytical and art historical data. </p>
                
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Connecting Visual and Scientific Data with IIIF and Web Annotations</head>
                <p>
                    The visual display of information is central to Mapping Color in History.
                    The International Image Interoperability Framework (IIIF) defines a set of open
                    API standards for describing and delivering high-resolution, attributed digital
                    objects - a natural fit for a project which relies on visual works from
                    disparate museum and library digital collections (Appleby et al. 2022). Some
                    partner institutions already provide IIIF-compliant resources which are easily
                    integrated into MCH. To serve assets from institutions which do not yet provide
                    IIIF resources, MCH utilizes a IIIF pipeline developed by the Harvard Library
                    Technical Services team (LTS) and provided as infrastructure as a service for
                    multiple university clients. The asset ingest and delivery pipeline was created
                    in collaboration with partners such as MCH, HarvardX, and the Academic
                    Technology Group. The MCH team collaborated with ATG to create a reusable Python
                    library (Crawford et al. 2022) to generate IIIF manifests and interact with the
                    IIIF pipeline APIs. </p>
                <p><lb/>MCH also connects pigment analysis data to art object digital
                    representations through IIIF-compatible Web Annotations (Sanderson et al. 2017).
                    Connecting scientific data to digital cultural objects is difficult but
                    necessary for researchers interested in making the shift from visual and
                    historical analysis to material investigation and scientific data analysis
                    (France and Toth 2011). Using a CatchPy annotation server developed at HarvardX
                    (Maekawa), MCH researchers annotate analyses as layers on canvases representing
                    the works. We extended the Mirador 3 mirador-annotations plugin (Reed 2020) to
                    include an adapter for CatchPy and to allow researchers to capture the visible
                    color and analysis methodology (XRF, Raman, etc) associated with each annotation
                    point. This links the annotations to our application data, so users can click on
                    annotations within the Mirador IIIF viewer and see the associated pigments. Much
                    like the Library of Congress’ Scriptospatial Visualization Initiative, the MCH
                    viewer layers scientific pigment analyses on top of the digital object,
                    surfacing data that may otherwise remain locked in a pigment database (France
                    2017). This interface is more accessible than typical pigment databases, as
                    researchers can see exactly where pigments appear on the work and compare
                    analyses of different objects. These annotations will eventually allow
                    researchers to visualize the interconnections between pigment analyses and art
                    historical data in historically and geographically meaningful ways. </p>
            </div>

        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliogr">
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Appleby, Michael, Tom Crane, Robert
                            Sanderson, Jon Stroop, and Simeon Warner.</author>
                         “IIIF Presentation API 3.0.” <ref target="https://iiif.io/api/presentation/3.0/">https://iiif.io/api/presentation/3.0/</ref>
                         [04.11.2022]</bibl>
                    <bibl><lb/><hi rend="bold">Crawford, Cole / Arthur Barett / Jeremy Guillette /
                                Vesna Tan</hi> (2022): IIIF LTS Library. 
                        <ref target="https://github.com/Harvard-ATG/lts-iiif-ingest-service">https://github.com/Harvard-ATG/lts-iiif-ingest-service</ref>
                     
                         [04.11.2022]</bibl>
                    <bibl><author>De Faria</author> / <author>Dalva L., et al.</author> 
                         (2016): “A Definitive Analytical Spectroscopic Study of Indian Yellow, an Ancient Pigment Used for Dating Purposes,” in: Forensic Science International, 271: 1–7, 
                        
                        <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.forsciint.2016.11.037">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.forsciint.2016.11.037</ref>
                        </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Eremin, Katherine, et al.</author>
                         (2008): “Examination of Pigments on Thai Manuscripts: The First Identification of Copper Citrate,” in: Journal of Raman Spectroscopy  39, 8: 1057-65. 
                        <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1002/jrs.1985">https://doi.org/10.1002/jrs.1985</ref>
                       </bibl>
                    <bibl><author>Feller, Robert L., et al.</author>
                         (1986): Artists' Pigments : a Handbook of Their History and Characteristics. National Gallery of Art.</bibl>
                    <bibl><author>France, Fenella</author> / <author>Campagnolo, Alberto</author> 
                         (2017): “Integrating Humanities and Science: The Scriptospatial Visualization Interface.“ Montreal, Canada.</bibl>
                    <bibl><author>France, Fenella</author> / <author>Toth, Michael</author> 
                         (2011): “Knowledge and Reasoning: Connecting Scientific Data and Cultural Heritage” (Stanford, CA, 2011).</bibl>
                    <bibl><author>Kim, Jinah</author>
                         (2021): Garland of Visions : Color, Tantra, and a Material History of Indian Painting. University of California Press.</bibl>
                    <bibl><author>Krekel, Christoph, et al.</author>
                         (2006): “ARTISTS' PIGMENTS RECONSIDERED: DOES MODERN SCIENCE MATCH THE HISTORICAL CONTEXT?” Studies in Conservation 51, 2: 244-48. 
                        <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1179/sic.2006.51.Supplement-2.244">https://doi.org/10.1179/sic.2006.51.Supplement-2.244</ref>
                       </bibl>
                    <bibl><author>Maekawa, Naomi.</author>
                        <hi rend="italic">CatchPy:
                            Annotation Storage Backend</hi>
                         (version 2.5.2).  
                        <ref target="https://github.com/nmaekawa/catchpy">https://github.com/nmaekawa/catchpy</ref>
                       
                         [04.11.2022]</bibl>
                    <bibl><author>Ravindran, T. R., et al.</author>
                        (2011): “Raman Spectroscopic Study of Medieval Indian Art of 17th Century,” in Journal of Raman Spectroscopy, 42, 4: 803–07. 
                        <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1002/jrs.2776">https://doi.org/10.1002/jrs.2776</ref>
                   </bibl>
                    <bibl><author>Reed, Jack</author>
                         (2020): 
                        <hi rend="italic">mirador-annotations</hi>
                         (version 0.5.0) 
                        <ref target="https://github.com/ProjectMirador/mirador-annotations">https://github.com/ProjectMirador/mirador-annotations</ref></bibl>
                    <bibl><author>Sanderson, Robert</author> / <author>Paolo Ciccarese</author> / <author>Benjamin Young</author> 
                         (2017): 
                        <hi rend="italic">Web Annotation
                            Data Model.</hi>
                        <ref target="https://www.w3.org/TR/annotation-model">https://www.w3.org/TR/annotation-model</ref>
                        </bibl>
                    <lb/>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text></TEI>