<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_allPlus.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_allPlus.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>From Atoms to Eternity: Visualizing Space and Scale in Emily
                    Dickinson</title>
                <author n="LangAnoukLANG_Anouk_From_Atoms_to_Eternity__Visualizing_Space_and_Sca.xml"><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-9597-1026" n="LangAnouk">
                        <surname>Lang</surname>
                        <forename>Anouk</forename>
                    </persName><affiliation>University of Edinburgh, United Kingdom</affiliation><email>anouk.lang@ed.ac.uk</email></author><meeting><date from-iso="2023-07-10" to-iso="2023-07-14"/><title>Digital Humanities 2023. Collaboration as Opportunity</title><placeName>Graz</placeName></meeting>
            </titleStmt>
            
            <publicationStmt><publisher><orgName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1137284463">Zentrum für Informationsmodellierung
                    - Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities, Karl-Franzens-Universität
                    Graz</orgName></publisher><date when="2023">2023</date><pubPlace>Graz</pubPlace><availability><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">Creative Commons BY
                    4.0</licence></availability></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title>Digital Humanities 2023: Book of Abstracts</title><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-9256-0958"><forename>Walter</forename><surname>Scholger</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>University of Graz</orgName><placeName>Graz, Austria</placeName></affiliation><email>walter.scholger@uni-graz.at</email></editor><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-1726-1712"><forename>Georg</forename><surname>Vogeler</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>University of Graz</orgName><placeName>Graz, Austria</placeName></affiliation><email>georg.vogeler@uni-graz.at</email></editor><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-3919-993X"><forename>Toma</forename><surname>Tasovac</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>Belgrade Center for Digital Humanities</orgName><placeName>Belgrade, Serbia</placeName></affiliation><email>ttasovac@humanistika.org</email></editor><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-4593-059X"><forename>Anne</forename><surname>Baillot</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>Le Mans Université</orgName><placeName>Le Mans, France</placeName></affiliation><email>anne.baillot@univ-lemans.fr</email></editor><respStmt><resp>Data Management</resp><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0009-0007-9019-8215"><forename>Elisabeth</forename><surname>Raunig</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Management</resp><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-1438-3236"><forename>Martina</forename><surname>Scholger</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Management</resp><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-9116-0402"><forename>Elisabeth</forename><surname>Steiner</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Curation</resp><persName><forename>Johanna</forename><surname>Ofenauer</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Curation</resp><persName><forename>Christina</forename><surname>Burgstaller</surname></persName></respStmt><idno type="DOI">10.5281/zenodo.7961822</idno></seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="DHCONVALIDATOR" version="1.22">
                    <label>DHConvalidator</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc><abstract><p>This paper proposes a visualisation method for understanding how computational approaches can be used to both understand and defamiliarize the workings of space and scale in a corpus of poetry by Emily Dickinson. The ramifications for the compuational study of poetry more generally are also considered.</p></abstract><langUsage><language ident="en">English</language></langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="category">
                    <term>Paper</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="subcategory">
                    <term>Long Presentation</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="keywords">
                    <term>spatial humanities</term>
                    <term>digital mapping</term>
                    <term>Emily Dickinson</term>
                    <term>text analysis</term>
                    <term>poetry</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="topics">
                    <term>spatial &amp; spatio-temporal analysis</term>
                    <term>modeling and visualization</term>
                    <term>text mining and analysis</term>
                    <term>Geography and geo-humanities</term>
                    <term>Literary studies</term>
                    
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <p>Digital humanists who use spatial technologies have found
                common ground with scholars in geography who have, for some decades, been engaged in
                problematizing the positivistic assumptions such tools rest on, and conceiving
                alternative practices for using these technologies as a means of “understanding
                people’s lived experiences in an interpretive manner rather than for conducting
                spatial analysis that relies largely on quantitative geographical information” (Kwan
                and Knigge 1999). Cross-disciplinary collaboration in the spatial humanities thus
                offers the opportunity to repurpose digital mapping applications for humanistic ends
                and interrogate the assumptions underlying these tools. </p>
            <p>This paper takes up this challenge by considering how
                digital tools for identifying and visualizing place, size and scale might be used to
                simultaneously understand and defamiliarize the workings of spatiality in the poems
                of Emily Dickinson. Dickinson is an apt writer with which to conduct such a study,
                as her poems are almost completely unmappable in conventional cartographic ways:
                they are almost entirely devoid of specific geographical references, but many are
                preoccupied with literal and metaphorical space and her work is suffused with a
                vocabulary of scales, sizes and spatial contrasts. As Helen Vendler observes, there
                is “an almost illimitable set of templates” on which Dickinson maps her poems,
                including “a circular geometry of center, circumference, and the ‘spokes’ connecting
                them”, “a vertical scale extending from ‘under the beetle’s cellar’ to the stars”
                and “a horizontal scale extending from the East of dawn to the West of sunset”, with
                Dickinson disorienting the reader by mapping these templates over the top of each
                other, and “leap[ing] from plane to plane” (10). These leaps and shifts between
                different scales are a key part of the poems’ metaphorical resources as they explore
                abstract themes such as existentialism, human attempts to access the numinous, and
                the relationship between the human and animal worlds.</p>
            <p>To visualize space and scale in Dickinson’s work, I began
                with a collection of poems in which scale and space were thematically prominent, and
                in which there was a move from one scale to another. Using a log scale from 10 pm
                through to 10 <hi rend="superscript">15</hi> m, I distributed the various entities
                mentioned in the poems across it, designating for example 10 pm as roughly
                equivalent to “an Atom” (-11 on the axis), 100km as “the sea” or “the skies” (as
                seen from the ground; 12 on the axis), and 10 <hi rend="superscript">8</hi> m as
                “the firmament” (8 on the axis). I then plotted each poem according to where each
                line or half line fell on the scale, producing visualisations such as figure 1
                below. Creating these plots is, obviously, a highly interpretative process, and
                would vary from one reader to the next, but the role of the poetic interpreter in
                computational poetic analysis is part of what this project seeks to explore. </p>
            <figure>
                <graphic n="1001" width="16.002cm" height="8.3185cm" url="Pictures/43fb5aa850276ec3c8a77a027f6ab0b8.png" rend="inline"/>
                <head>Figure 1: Four of Emily Dickinson’s poems plotted according to shifts in scale</head>
            </figure>
            <p>There are three key challenges here for the spatial
                humanist. The first is finding visualisation methods that can encompass the dramatic
                differences in scale from “the Atom” to “the Universe” that can be contained in a
                single short poem. The second is finding a visualisation method capable of
                registering and visualising the often vertiginous <hi rend="italic">shifts</hi> in a
                poem between these scales dynamically, ie. to give a sense not just of scale but of
                the movement between them that occurs in a poem. The third challenge is to ascertain
                the analytical utility in visualising these poetic shifts. What are the
                opportunities offered by collaborative efforts to engage spatial technologies to
                better understand Dickinson’s poems, given that they so obviously resist being tied
                down to quantitative scales? In presenting visualisations such as these, which give
                no meaningful quantitative information but instead allow an instant grasp of the
                shape of Dickinson’s swoops and plunges between scales, I seek to make an argument
                both about the way such shifts provide Dickinson with the metaphorical resources to
                represent and interrogate of existential themes, and also to addess the wider
                question of how computational approaches might be used in the study of poetry, and
                whether the costs that such collaborative efforts involve—labor, environmental, and
                more—are worth the opportunities they present to scholars of poetry. One possible
                answer to the question of analytical utility is that approaches like these might be
                able to function as a Turing test of sorts for text generated by machine learning
                methods, ie. to see whether a model trained on Dickinson’s corpus might be able to
                replicate this kind of “spatial extravagance”, given that she expresses it using
                words such as “eternity” and “dip” that do not necessarily connote space or
                distance. The initial “training set”—gathered through domain expertise of poetry
                more generally rather than a close knowledge of all of Dickinson’s extensive
                oeuvre—allowed me to gather a vocabulary of words with which to search the entire
                corpus of Dickinson’s poems for other examples, so there is also the potential for
                such approaches to be used for discoverability. </p>
            <p>Finally, I used this list of terms in conjunction with the
                Women Writers Vector Toolkit ( <ref target="https://wwp.northeastern.edu/lab/wwvt/">https://wwp.northeastern.edu/lab/wwvt/</ref>), an offshoot of the Women Writers
                Project (WWP), to explore whether a word embeddings model could find terms that, to
                a nineteenth-century audience, might have connoted space, scale and shifts between
                them, and thus obtain further words with which to query the Dickinson corpus. This
                represented the opportunity to collaborate, so to speak, with the experts and
                scholars who built the WWP word embeddings model. The WWP corpus is, of course,
                built from fiction texts rather than poetry: any equivalent poetry corpus would not
                be sufficiently large for machine learning analysis. This part of the project was
                useful in suggesting how portable the lexical patterning around space and scale in
                one genre (longform literary fiction published mostly in Britain) was when applied
                to another genre (poetry written in the United States): while there are clear
                generic differences between these two genres, a model trained on pre-twentieth
                century literary fiction would seem to be a better match than a one trained on vast
                databanks of text harvested from the twenty-first century internet. </p>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliogr">
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Kwan, Mei-Po</author> / <author>Knigge, LaDona</author>
                        (2006): “Doing qualitative research using GIS: An oxymoronic endeavor?”, in:
                            <hi rend="italic">Environment and Planning A</hi> 38, 11: 1999-2002. </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Vendler, Helen</author> (2010): <hi rend="italic">Dickinson:
                            Selected Poems and Commentaries</hi>. Cambridge, MA: The Belknap Press
                        of Harvard University Press. DOI: 10.1068/a38462. </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Women Writers Project</author>. Women Writers Project,
                        Northeastern University, 1999–2022  <ref target="https://www.wwp.northeastern.edu">https://www.wwp.northeastern.edu</ref> [2.11.2022]. </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text></TEI>