<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_allPlus.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_allPlus.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Towards a datafication of Antwerp street life? Co-creating a dataset of
                    100.000+ pages of handwritten police reports (1876-1945)</title>
                <author n="LefrancLithLEFRANC_Lith_Towards_a_datafication_of_Antwerp_street_life__.xml"><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-6860-552X" n="LefrancLith">
                        <surname>Lefranc</surname>
                        <forename>Lith</forename>
                    </persName><affiliation>University of Antwerp, Belgium</affiliation><email>lith.lefranc@uantwerpen.be</email></author><meeting><date from-iso="2023-07-10" to-iso="2023-07-14"/><title>Digital Humanities 2023. Collaboration as Opportunity</title><placeName>Graz</placeName></meeting>
            </titleStmt>
            
            <publicationStmt><publisher><orgName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1137284463">Zentrum für Informationsmodellierung
                    - Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities, Karl-Franzens-Universität
                    Graz</orgName></publisher><date when="2023">2023</date><pubPlace>Graz</pubPlace><availability><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">Creative Commons BY
                    4.0</licence></availability></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title>Digital Humanities 2023: Book of Abstracts</title><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-9256-0958"><forename>Walter</forename><surname>Scholger</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>University of Graz</orgName><placeName>Graz, Austria</placeName></affiliation><email>walter.scholger@uni-graz.at</email></editor><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-1726-1712"><forename>Georg</forename><surname>Vogeler</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>University of Graz</orgName><placeName>Graz, Austria</placeName></affiliation><email>georg.vogeler@uni-graz.at</email></editor><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-3919-993X"><forename>Toma</forename><surname>Tasovac</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>Belgrade Center for Digital Humanities</orgName><placeName>Belgrade, Serbia</placeName></affiliation><email>ttasovac@humanistika.org</email></editor><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-4593-059X"><forename>Anne</forename><surname>Baillot</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>Le Mans Université</orgName><placeName>Le Mans, France</placeName></affiliation><email>anne.baillot@univ-lemans.fr</email></editor><respStmt><resp>Data Management</resp><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0009-0007-9019-8215"><forename>Elisabeth</forename><surname>Raunig</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Management</resp><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-1438-3236"><forename>Martina</forename><surname>Scholger</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Management</resp><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-9116-0402"><forename>Elisabeth</forename><surname>Steiner</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Curation</resp><persName><forename>Johanna</forename><surname>Ofenauer</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Curation</resp><persName><forename>Christina</forename><surname>Burgstaller</surname></persName></respStmt><idno type="DOI">10.5281/zenodo.7961822</idno></seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="DHCONVALIDATOR" version="1.22">
                    <label>DHConvalidator</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc><abstract><p>This poster presents the collaborative creation of a dataset of 100.000+ pages of handwritten police reports as a successful example of large-scale digitisation initiatives by small-scale research projects. It shows efficient solutions for applying Handwritten Text Recognition techniques on challenging historical documents and for bypassing noisy training material.</p></abstract><langUsage><language ident="en">English</language></langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="category">
                    <term>Paper</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="subcategory">
                    <term>Poster</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="keywords">
                    <term>handwritten text recognition</term>
                    <term>social history</term>
                    <term>collaboration</term>
                    <term>dataset</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="topics">
                    <term>artificial intelligence and machine learning</term>
                    <term>crowdsourcing</term>
                    <term>data publishing projects</term>
                    <term>systems</term>
                    <term>and methods</term>
                    <term>optical character recognition and handwriting recognition</term>
                    <term>History</term>
                    
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <p>Since the 1960s, when the so-called ‘new social
                historians’ started questioning mainstream historical narratives and experiences,
                new historical sources such as police and judicial sources came under scrutiny,
                putting the spotlight on social groups and ‘people without history’ who have left
                almost no paper trail of their own (Thompson 1963; Wolf 1982). These historical
                documents have been valuable for a myriad of approaches which are not necessarily
                crime-related: working-class history, the history of mentalities, gender and
                sexuality history, youth and family history, <hi rend="italic">Alltagsgeschichte</hi>, and so on. Up until today, qualitative methodological
                approaches have dominated this research area, emphasising thick description and
                case-based research. Only recently, social historians have been discovering the
                potential of data-driven approaches towards criminal records (e.g. Van den Heuvel
                2020; Saygi / Yasunaga 2021). One of the most straightforward explanations for this
                lag is the lack of machine-readable data. Nineteenth-century bureaucratisation
                processes have left historians of the modern period with an abundance of archival
                material, but only the tip of the iceberg is digitally available, let alone
                searchable. Grand digitisation initiatives such as Old Bailey Online remain scarce
                because they require a lot of time, money, and labour (Hitchcock et al. 2012). In
                response, crowdsourcing platforms have been popping up like mushrooms, but these are
                often ill-suited for researchers with limited means such as PhDs.  </p>
            <p>Over the past few years, the technique of Handwritten Text
                Recognition (HTR) – made accessible through e.g. Transkribus and eScriptorium –
                improved greatly, which broke new ground for small-scale research projects
                (Muehlberger et al. 2019; Kiessling et al. 2019). In this poster, I will present a
                dataset of approximately 100.000 HTRed pages of local police reports from the city
                of Antwerp (1876-1945). Apart from the dataset specifics, I will show the challenges
                for HTR-training, which relied on both gold standard expert transcriptions, and
                semi-gold standard material provided by undergraduate students. Both collections
                will be scrutinised, and solutions will be examined for bypassing noisy training
                data. I hope that this presentation not only encourages qualitative social
                historians to test their hypotheses on ‘big data’, but also inspires them to step by
                step unlock more underexplored paper archives for data-driven research.  </p>
            <div type="div1">
                <head>Dataset specifics</head>
                <div type="div2">
                    <head>Incident books</head>
                    <p>From the 1860s onwards Antwerp police officers
                        were obliged to write a daily report after patrolling their respective
                        neighbourhoods in the so-called ‘incident books’. One of the major
                        historiographical benefits is the fact that these reports not only document
                        prosecuted crimes, but non-prosecuted misdemeanours and other irregularities
                        as well. Therefore, they give a very extensive account of all sorts of
                        happenings on the Antwerp streets, such as neighbourhood quarrels, monkey
                        tricks, lost children… The serial character of the incident books ensures a
                        consistent registration of who (gender, profession, age, place of residence
                        and birth) was when (date and time of day) and where (address) doing what
                        (detailed description of incident) (see image below). </p>
                    <figure>
                        <graphic n="1001" width="16.002cm" height="8.198555555555556cm" url="Pictures/487bab31453d2993389b0d2e36d2d0be.png" rend="inline"/>
                        
                    </figure>
                </div>
                <div type="div2">
                    <head>Space and time</head>
                    <p>The dataset consists of 326 books which date from
                        1876 to 1945 and are located within 11 different police districts. The data
                        is not spread evenly throughout space and time. Most pages contain police
                        reports dedicated to the third and the sixth district (predominantly
                        bourgeois districts), and the page number increases during the 1930s and the
                        Second World War (a period of increasing police surveillance). </p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="div1">
                <head>HTR-training results</head>
                <p>The incident books were very challenging for
                    HTR-training because they contain numerous different handwritings and are
                    written in French as well as Dutch. Furthermore, the difficult and irregular
                    layout of the reports made segmentation very time-consuming. I have worked with
                    two different training sets: gold standard expert transcriptions, and semi-gold
                    standard material provided by undergraduates. The former consists of 326 pages
                    selected randomly from each incident book and the latter contains several
                    samples (in total 3000 pages).   </p>
                <p>Despite the imperfect undergraduate work, the models
                    trained on all the material performed best, but unfortunately only led up to a
                    (still unsatisfactory) character error rate (CER) of 9.3%. After systematically
                    analysing the word and character errors of this model, I managed to improve the
                    CER up to 6.3% by eliminating skewed text and signature marks. Finally, I
                    switched to a more relaxed evaluation of the model by lowercasing all text and
                    excluding interpunction and redundant spacing characters.</p>
                <p>The fully HTRed dataset consists of about 30,5 million
                    words and will soon be published in open-access format.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliogr">
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Kiessling, Benjamin</author> et al. (2019): “eScriptorium: An
                        Open Source Platform for Historical Document Analysis”, in: International
                        Conference on Document Analysis and Recognition Workshops (ICDARW), 2:
                        19–24. </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Hitchcock, Tim</author> et al. (2012): The Old Bailey
                        Proceedings Online, 1674-1913, <ref target="https://www.oldbaileyonline.org">https://www.oldbaileyonline.org</ref> [4.11.2022]; </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Muehlberger, Guenter</author> et al. (2019): “Transforming
                        scholarship in the archives through handwritten text recognition:
                        Transkribus as a case study”, I,: Journal of Documentation 75, 5: 954–976. </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Saygi, Gamze</author> / <author>Yasunaga, Marie</author>  (2021): “The digital
                        urban experience of a lost city using mixed methods to depict the historical
                        street life of Edo/Tokyo”, in: Magazén 2, 2: 193-224. </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Thompson, Edward Palmer</author> (1963): The Making of the
                        English Working Class. London: Victor Gollancz Ltd. </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>van den Heuvel, D.</author> et al. (2020): “Capturing gendered
                        mobility and street use in the historical city: a new methodological
                        approach”, in: Cultural and Social History 17, 4: 515–536. </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Wolf, Eric</author> (1982): Europe and the People without
                        History. Berkeley: University of California Press. </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text></TEI>