<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_allPlus.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_allPlus.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Revisiting connotations of digital humanists: Exploration based on
                    semi-structured interviews and survey</title>
                <author n="MaRongqianMA_Rongqian_Revisiting_connotations_of_digital_humanists__Ex.xml"><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-7141-1056" n="MaRongqian">
                        <surname>Ma</surname>
                        <forename>Rongqian</forename>
                    </persName><affiliation>Indiana University Bloomington, United States of
                        America</affiliation><email>rm56@iu.edu</email></author><meeting><date from-iso="2023-07-10" to-iso="2023-07-14"/><title>Digital Humanities 2023. Collaboration as Opportunity</title><placeName>Graz</placeName></meeting>
            </titleStmt>
            
            <publicationStmt><publisher><orgName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1137284463">Zentrum für Informationsmodellierung
                    - Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities, Karl-Franzens-Universität
                    Graz</orgName></publisher><date when="2023">2023</date><pubPlace>Graz</pubPlace><availability><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">Creative Commons BY
                    4.0</licence></availability></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title>Digital Humanities 2023: Book of Abstracts</title><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-9256-0958"><forename>Walter</forename><surname>Scholger</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>University of Graz</orgName><placeName>Graz, Austria</placeName></affiliation><email>walter.scholger@uni-graz.at</email></editor><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-1726-1712"><forename>Georg</forename><surname>Vogeler</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>University of Graz</orgName><placeName>Graz, Austria</placeName></affiliation><email>georg.vogeler@uni-graz.at</email></editor><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-3919-993X"><forename>Toma</forename><surname>Tasovac</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>Belgrade Center for Digital Humanities</orgName><placeName>Belgrade, Serbia</placeName></affiliation><email>ttasovac@humanistika.org</email></editor><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-4593-059X"><forename>Anne</forename><surname>Baillot</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>Le Mans Université</orgName><placeName>Le Mans, France</placeName></affiliation><email>anne.baillot@univ-lemans.fr</email></editor><respStmt><resp>Data Management</resp><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0009-0007-9019-8215"><forename>Elisabeth</forename><surname>Raunig</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Management</resp><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-1438-3236"><forename>Martina</forename><surname>Scholger</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Management</resp><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-9116-0402"><forename>Elisabeth</forename><surname>Steiner</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Curation</resp><persName><forename>Johanna</forename><surname>Ofenauer</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Curation</resp><persName><forename>Christina</forename><surname>Burgstaller</surname></persName></respStmt><idno type="DOI">10.5281/zenodo.7961822</idno></seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="DHCONVALIDATOR" version="1.22">
                    <label>DHConvalidator</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc><abstract><p>This poster revisits the connotations of the umbrella term “digital humanists” by positioning it in the rapidly developing field of digital humanities (DH). The wide participation in DH from scholars, researchers, and practitioners coming from various knowledge domains and fields provides a good opportunity to rethink if advances in digital technologies and cross-field collaboration practices have impacted research communities’ collective understandings of “digital humanists,” including what the term refers to and how the term shapes the dynamics of the DH field. Particularly, in this poster, I explore the reasons why and why not a researcher would self-identify as a digital humanist.</p></abstract><langUsage><language ident="en">English</language></langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="category">
                    <term>Paper</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="subcategory">
                    <term>Poster</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="keywords">
                    <term>Digital humanist</term>
                    <term>collective identity</term>
                    <term>semi-structured interview</term>
                    <term>survey</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="topics">
                    <term>mixed-media analysis</term>
                    <term>rhetorical analysis</term>
                    <term>Library &amp; information science</term>
                    
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div type="div1">
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <p>This poster revisits the connotations of the umbrella
                    term “digital humanists” by positioning it in the rapidly developing field of
                    digital humanities (DH). The wide participation in DH from scholars,
                    researchers, and practitioners coming from various knowledge domains and fields
                    (Ma &amp; Li, 2021; Jänicke, 2016) provides a good opportunity to rethink if
                    advances in digital technologies and cross-field collaboration practices have
                    impacted research communities’ collective understandings of “digital humanists,”
                    including what the term refers to and how the term shapes the dynamics of the DH
                    field. Particularly, in this poster, I explore the reasons why and why not a
                    researcher would self-identify as a digital humanist. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="div1">
                <head>Related Work</head>
                <p>Who is and who is not a digital humanist is a classic
                    question in DH research literature? Early deliberations of “digital humanists”
                    have emphasized the humanist orientation for the term. Alvarado (2012) discussed
                    that a “digital humanist” should be someone who (1) aims to develop the deep
                    domain knowledge of the traditional humanist, (2) learns a wide variety of
                    technologies and programming languages, and (3) critically situates the
                    technologies as cultural artifacts participating in the production of social and
                    cognitive structures. This demonstrates that a “digital humanist,” to Alvarado’s
                    imagination, should be a versatile researcher who both has deep knowledge of
                    humanities research and a great mastery of digital technologies and programming.
                    Ramsay (2011) at the same time situates “digital humanists” as humanities
                    scholars who “can build something with digital methods.” This understanding has
                    a broader stance on what is included in “digital methods” and does not emphasize
                    digital humanists’ abilities to write codes or programs. Despite the different
                    ideas about digital humanists’ technological literacy and programming
                    proficiency, early understandings of the term suggest the main component of DH
                    workforce and labor landscape were humanities researchers. However, as
                    disciplinary boundaries blur and converge, interdisciplinary collaborations
                    deepen, and an increasing number of scholars from non-humanities fields enter
                    the DH landscape (Wang, 2018; Tang et al., 2017), it becomes a meaningful moment
                    to revisit the collective perceptions of “digital humanists” in the current DH
                    landscape. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="div1">
                <head>Questions and Methods</head>
                <p>Situated in this background, I ask: Why or why not
                    does a researcher or practitioner self-identify as a digital humanist? By means
                    of answering this question, I discuss what the current perceptions of a “digital
                    humanist” among DH research communities are, whether they are different from
                    early connotations, and how they are potentially affected by the current work
                    practices and labor structure of DH. Methodologically, I use a combination of
                    qualitative semi-structured interviews and quantitative survey methods to
                    explore the research question. For the preliminary study, I recruited fourteen
                    participants who have been actively engaged in DH research projects for
                    30-minute semi-structured interviews. During the interviews, I collected
                    participants’ demographic information, particularly their fields of research,
                    academic positions, and the major research questions they explore in their work.
                    I also asked participants to indicate if they self-identify as digital
                    humanists, based on their respective understandings of the term, and explain
                    why. Preliminary results showed that researchers’ self-identification varies,
                    and such variance is impacted by the nature of research questions and
                    researchers’ self-evaluation of their digital literacy. In the following survey,
                    I will test the above observations with larger datasets. I explore which
                    components of digital literacy matter the most for researchers’
                    self-identification as digital humanists, which types of research questions
                    ground their decisions and their sense of belonging, and how they make sense of
                    the highly interdisciplinary field of practice and critically think of
                    themselves as (or not as) part of it. Findings of this study will help us better
                    understand the connotations of “digital humanists” as of today and the
                    construction of collective identities of DH researchers and practitioners.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliogr">
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <bibl>
                        <author> Alvarado , R</author> (2012): 
                        <hi rend="italic">The digital humanities situation</hi>
                        <hi rend="italic">. In Matthew K. Gold (ed.), </hi>
                        <hi rend="italic">Debates in the Digital
                            Humanities</hi>
                        . Minneapolis: University of Minnesota
                            Press.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Jänicke , S. </author>
                         (2016): Valuable research for visualization and digital humanities: A balancing act. 
                        <hi rend="italic">Workshop on Visualization for the
                            Digital Humanities, IEEE VIS 2016, Baltimore, MD.</hi>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Ma, R</author> / <author>Li, K.</author> 
                         (2021): Visuality in a cross-disciplinary
                            battleground: Analysis of inscriptions in digital humanities journal
                            publications
                        <hi rend="italic">. </hi>
                        <hi rend="italic">Journal of the Association for
                            Information Science and Technology</hi>
                        <hi rend="italic">73</hi> (2), 172-187. </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author> Ramsay , S </author>
                         (2011): Who’s in and who’s out.
                        <hi rend="italic">In </hi>
                        Melissa Terras, Julianne Nyhan, and Edward Vanhoutte (eds.), 
                        <hi rend="italic">Defining Digital Humanities: A
                            Reader</hi>
                        (pp. 239-241)
                        <hi rend="italic">.</hi>
                        Farnham, Surrey, England: Ashgate Publishing Limited. 
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author> Wang, Q</author> (2018): Distribution features and intellectual structures of digital
                            humanities: A bibliometric analysis.
                        <hi rend="italic">Journal of Documentation</hi>
                        <hi rend="italic">74</hi> (1),  223-246.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Tang , M</author> / <author>Cheng, Y.-J.</author> / <author>Chen, K. H.</author>  (2017):
                        Alongitudinalstudy of intellectual cohesion in digital humanities using
                        bibliometric analyses. <hi rend="italic">Scientometrics</hi>
                        <hi rend="italic">113</hi> (2), 985-1008.
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text></TEI>