<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_allPlus.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_allPlus.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Creating, storing, and sharing your own web archives with open source
                    Webrecorder tools</title>
                <author n="MullikenJasmineTiffanyMULLIKEN_Jasmine_Tiffany_Creating__storing__and_sharing_your.xml"><persName n="MullikenJasmineTiffany">
                        <surname>Mulliken</surname>
                        <forename>Jasmine Tiffany</forename>
                    </persName><affiliation>Stanford University, United States of America</affiliation><email>jasmine.mulliken@stanford.edu</email></author><meeting><date from-iso="2023-07-10" to-iso="2023-07-14"/><title>Digital Humanities 2023. Collaboration as Opportunity</title><placeName>Graz</placeName></meeting>
                <author n="KreymerIlyaMULLIKEN_Jasmine_Tiffany_Creating__storing__and_sharing_your.xml"><persName n="KreymerIlya">
                        <surname>Kreymer</surname>
                        <forename>Ilya</forename>
                    </persName><affiliation>Webrecorder</affiliation><email>ikreymer@gmail.com</email></author><meeting><date from-iso="2023-07-10" to-iso="2023-07-14"/><title>Digital Humanities 2023. Collaboration as Opportunity</title><placeName>Graz</placeName></meeting>
            </titleStmt>
            
            <publicationStmt><publisher><orgName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1137284463">Zentrum für Informationsmodellierung
                    - Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities, Karl-Franzens-Universität
                    Graz</orgName></publisher><date when="2023">2023</date><pubPlace>Graz</pubPlace><availability><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">Creative Commons BY
                    4.0</licence></availability></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title>Digital Humanities 2023: Book of Abstracts</title><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-9256-0958"><forename>Walter</forename><surname>Scholger</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>University of Graz</orgName><placeName>Graz, Austria</placeName></affiliation><email>walter.scholger@uni-graz.at</email></editor><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-1726-1712"><forename>Georg</forename><surname>Vogeler</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>University of Graz</orgName><placeName>Graz, Austria</placeName></affiliation><email>georg.vogeler@uni-graz.at</email></editor><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-3919-993X"><forename>Toma</forename><surname>Tasovac</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>Belgrade Center for Digital Humanities</orgName><placeName>Belgrade, Serbia</placeName></affiliation><email>ttasovac@humanistika.org</email></editor><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-4593-059X"><forename>Anne</forename><surname>Baillot</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>Le Mans Université</orgName><placeName>Le Mans, France</placeName></affiliation><email>anne.baillot@univ-lemans.fr</email></editor><respStmt><resp>Data Management</resp><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0009-0007-9019-8215"><forename>Elisabeth</forename><surname>Raunig</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Management</resp><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-1438-3236"><forename>Martina</forename><surname>Scholger</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Management</resp><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-9116-0402"><forename>Elisabeth</forename><surname>Steiner</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Curation</resp><persName><forename>Johanna</forename><surname>Ofenauer</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Curation</resp><persName><forename>Christina</forename><surname>Burgstaller</surname></persName></respStmt><idno type="DOI">10.5281/zenodo.7961822</idno></seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="DHCONVALIDATOR" version="1.22">
                    <label>DHConvalidator</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc><abstract><p>Engaging both creators of digital web-based content and researchers of content on the web, this tutorial introduces and demonstrates toolsets for crawling and sharing web archives. Unlike large-scale subscription services like ArchiveIt, these open-source tools allow individuals and small groups to archive websites and web-hosted data more granularly and deeply.</p></abstract><langUsage><language ident="en">English</language></langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="category">
                    <term>Paper</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="subcategory">
                    <term>Pre-Conference Workshop and Tutorial</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="keywords">
                    <term>web archiving</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="topics">
                    <term>data</term>
                    <term>object</term>
                    <term>and artefact preservation</term>
                    <term>digital archiving</term>
                    <term>digital publishing projects</term>
                    <term>systems</term>
                    <term>and methods</term>
                    <term>Communication studies</term>
                    <term>Computer science</term>
                    <term>Humanities computing</term>
                    <term>Library &amp; information science</term>
                    
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <p>This half-day tutorial will provide DH researchers with an
                introduction to web archiving tools, which they can use on their own or via a free
                and open-source toolset provided by Webrecorder.</p>
            <p>Web archiving has recently garnered mainstream attention
                for its indispensability in preserving online content in emergency situations, as
                with the Saving Ukranian Cultural Heritage Online (SUCHO) project. Launched in
                February 2022, two days after Russia’s invasion of Ukraine, SUCHO has worked to
                capture web-based Ukrainian artifacts, and Webrecorder tools have been an essential
                part of this workflow (see especially Verma 2022; Serrano 2022). But web archiving
                isn’t only for emergency situations. Key to the crowdsourcing success of efforts
                like SUCHO has been the user-friendly tools that amateur, as well as advanced,
                archivists can easily acclimate to. It’s this kind of accessibility that makes
                Webrecorder’s tools especially useful for digital humanists pursuing individual or
                small-group-led projects that require direct handling of web-based content and data.
                Whether it’s to archive your own website, web publication, or student web projects;
                to capture web archives of important and frequently updated web content from news
                sites or social media for research; or to curate archived content for others to
                engage with, this workshop will provide the foundation for getting started with
                hands-on (and automated!) web archiving.</p>
            <p>The tutorial will start with an introduction to
                “high-fidelity web archiving,” covering the basics of what is meant by these terms,
                and a demonstration of a specific use case and workflow for  archiving digital
                humanities and digital scholarly works published by Stanford University Press. As
                part of its Mellon-funded digital publishing initiative (Harvey 2019), SUP has
                partnered with Webrecorder to produce web archived versions of all eleven of its
                digital publications (Mulliken 2020). We will discuss the value of scholarly web
                archiving as an intervention to the perceivable ephemerality of digital scholarship
                and as a way to add value, via longevity, to non-traditional publication formats.
                Thus, this part of the tutorial will cover the rationale behind, ethical concerns
                of, and process of creating the web archives for complex digital publications using
                Webrecorder tools (Browsertrix Cloud, ArchiveWeb.page), storing them in an existing
                institutional repository, and making them available to the general public as a
                statically hosted site with minimal maintenance.</p>
            <p>In the next part of the tutorial, we will cover how users
                can create high-fidelity web archives of their own using the Browsertrix Cloud
                crawling system. Users will be presented with an interactive user interface to
                create crawls, allowing them to configure crawling options. We will describe the
                crawling configuration options and how these affect the result of the crawl. Users
                will have the opportunity to run a crawl of their own for at least 30 minutes and to
                see the results. We will then discuss and reflect on the results.</p>
            <p>In the following section, we will discuss how the web
                archives can be shared with others, using the ReplayWeb.page viewer. Participants
                will be able to download the contents of their crawls (as WACZ files) and load them
                on their own machines. We will also present options for sharing the outputs with
                others, by uploading to an easy-to-use hosting option such as Glitch or our custom
                WACZ Uploader. EIther method will produce a URL which participants can then share
                with others, in and outside the workshop, to show the results of their crawl. We
                will discuss how, once complete, the web crawl is no longer dependent on the crawler
                infrastructure, but can be treated like any other static file, and, as such, can be
                added to existing digital preservation repositories.</p>
            <p>In the final section, we will demonstrate how to augment
                the automated crawling with manual patching of the crawl using the ArchiveWeb.page
                extension. Participants will be able to use the extension to patch any content that
                was missed by the automated crawler, or to capture additional content that was not
                part of the original crawl. We will discuss how these tools can be used in
                combination to create both automated and manually-created web archives, and discuss
                the trade-offs between the two. Participants will then be able to upload their
                patched web archives and share with others, giving them another opportunity to
                practice a learned skill. In the end, we will discuss any issues encountered. We’ll
                also discuss current and on-going challenges of web archiving, including
                web-archiving ethics and what can be done to make these tools even easier, giving
                special attention to how we can make web archiving more accessible to digital
                humanities practitioners.</p>
            <p>The tutorial will cover: basic discussion of web archiving
                practices, introduction to web archiving terms, discussion of formats used,
                including WARC and WACZ, an overview of a specific use case at Stanford University
                Press, followed by hands-on web archiving experience (both automated and manual),
                sharing/publishing of web archives, and discussion of ethics, challenges, and things
                learned during the course of the session.</p>
            <p>Participants will leave the workshop with actual, web
                archive data which they can take with them and which they will have optionally
                published on the web for others to use. </p>
            <div>
                <head>Outline</head>
                <table xml:id="d214e195">
                    <row>
                        <cell>Introduction to web archiving</cell>
                        <cell>10 min</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Use Case: Web archiving workflow at Stanford
                            University Press; other useful scenarios, ethics</cell>
                        <cell>25 min</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Break</cell>
                        <cell>5 min</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Hands-On: Automated web archiving with
                            Browsertrix Cloud</cell>
                        <cell>35 min</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Break</cell>
                        <cell>5 min</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Hands-On: Viewing web archives and sharing
                            with others</cell>
                        <cell>20 min</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Discussion: Q&amp;A, issues so far</cell>
                        <cell>15 min</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Break</cell>
                        <cell>5 min</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Hands-on: Manual archiving with
                            ArchiveWeb.page extension</cell>
                        <cell>20 min</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Discussion: Automated vs manual, challenges
                            encountered</cell>
                        <cell>20 min</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Wrap-Up </cell>
                        <cell>10 min</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Workshop Leaders/Presenters</head>
                <p>Ilya Kreymer (ikreymer@gmail.com) is the founder and
                    lead developer of the Webrecorder project. Ilya has worked in the field of web
                    archiving for 11 years, and on the Webrecorder project since 2014. From
                    2011-2014, he worked at Internet Archive, where he contributed to their Wayback
                    Machine. From 2016-2019, he was working on Webrecorder at Rhizome.org, an arts
                    non-profit focused on preserving online digital culture. Since 2020, Webrecorder
                    project has been an independent entity focusing on expanding the open-source web
                    archiving ecosystem.</p>
                <p>Jasmine Mulliken (jasmine.mulliken@stanford.edu) is a
                    digital humanist working at the intersection of publishing, project development,
                    and digital archiving. Currently serving as Production and Preservation Manager,
                    Digital Projects at Stanford University Press, a role she’s been in since 2016,
                    her responsibilities include evaluating the technology powering the digital
                    projects SUP publishes to ascertain their sustainability and amenability to
                    current and developing web hosting, archiving, and preservation methods. She
                    works with Stanford University Libraries and external preservation initiatives
                    and agencies to identify, establish, and execute archiving solutions for the
                    unique needs and formats of digital publications. She has been using
                    Webrecorder’s tools for SUP’s digital projects since 2017 and has coordinated
                    SUP’s partnership with Webrecorder since 2019. She holds a Ph.D. (2011) in
                    English with an emphasis in Digital Literacies and Literatures from the
                    University of Texas at Austin.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>About Webrecorder</head>
                <p>Webrecorder project builds and maintains an ecosystem
                    of open source tools to support decentralized web archiving. From the beginning,
                    Webrecorder has focused on empowering others to make their own archives and
                    store them wherever is most convenient, from cloud services like AWS or Digital
                    Ocean to integrating with existing digital repository systems, like Archipelago.
                    Our motto is "web archiving for all" and we place emphasis on quality over
                    quantity, allowing users to create archives as accurately as possible.
                    Webrecorder is currently supported by a grant from the Filecoin Foundation and
                    has previously been funded by Mellon and various open source development and
                    support contracts.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Target audience</head>
                <list type="unordered">
                    <item>Librarians who collect, curate, or share web-based digital content</item>
                    <item>Researchers working with social media or frequently updated web-based news
                        sources</item>
                    <item>Creators of web-based content like digital projects, course websites,
                        web-based scholarship</item>
                    <item>Students and faculty with web-based digital portfolios</item>
                    <item>Historians of web content</item>
                </list>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Technical Requirements</head>
                <p>Presenters will need screen and projector and wifi
                    internet access for their laptops. Participants should bring their own laptops.
                    Charging outlets for participants would be useful, as would be tables to
                    accommodate everyone working on laptops.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Resources</head>
                <p>Participants will be provided with online and print
                    resources at the time of the workshop. Before the workshop, participants will be
                    asked to submit basic info to generate an account in the user interface to be
                    used in the workshop.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliogr">
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Harvey, Alan</author>
                         (2019): “The Stanford University Press digital publishing initiative receives $1.15 million to implement phase 2 of the program”, in: 
                        <hi rend="italic">supDigital Blog</hi>
                         <ref target="https://blog.supdigital.org/press-release/">https://blog.supdigital.org/press-release/</ref>.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Mulliken, Jasmine </author>
                        (2020): “Archival success!”, in: 
                        <hi rend="italic">supDigital Blog</hi>
                         <ref target="https://blog.supdigital.org/sup-webrecorder-partnership/">https://blog.supdigital.org/sup-webrecorder-partnership/</ref>.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Serrano, Jody</author>
                         (2022): “How to Stop Ukrainian Websites From Vanishing During War”, in: 
                        <hi rend="italic">Gizmodo</hi>
                        ,
                            <ref target="https://gizmodo.com/how-sucho-stops-ukrainian-websites-vanishing-in-russias-1848737441">https://gizmodo.com/how-sucho-stops-ukrainian-websites-vanishing-in-russias-1848737441</ref>.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Verma, Pranshu</author>
                         (2022): "Meet the 1,300 librarians racing to back up Ukraine’s digital archives", in: 
                        <hi rend="italic">Washington Post</hi>
                         <ref target="https://www.washingtonpost.com/technology/2022/04/08/ukraine-digital-history/">https://www.washingtonpost.com/technology/2022/04/08/ukraine-digital-history/</ref>.
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text></TEI>