<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_allPlus.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_allPlus.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Cultural Motifs on #bigdata - A Semi-Automated Topic Modeling from a
                    Socio-Cultural Constructionist Perspective</title>
                <author n="KnorrCharlotteNIEKLER_Andreas_Cultural_Motifs_on__bigdata___A_Semi_Automat.xml"><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-6591-3781" n="KnorrCharlotte">
                        <surname>Knorr</surname>
                        <forename>Charlotte</forename>
                    </persName><affiliation>Leipzig University, Germany</affiliation><email>charlotte.knorr@uni-leipzig.de</email></author><meeting><date from-iso="2023-07-10" to-iso="2023-07-14"/><title>Digital Humanities 2023. Collaboration as Opportunity</title><placeName>Graz</placeName></meeting>
                <author n="NieklerAndreasNIEKLER_Andreas_Cultural_Motifs_on__bigdata___A_Semi_Automat.xml"><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-3036-3318" n="NieklerAndreas">
                        <surname>Niekler</surname>
                        <forename>Andreas</forename>
                    </persName><affiliation>Leipzig University, Germany</affiliation><email>aniekler@informatik.uni-leipzig.de</email></author><meeting><date from-iso="2023-07-10" to-iso="2023-07-14"/><title>Digital Humanities 2023. Collaboration as Opportunity</title><placeName>Graz</placeName></meeting>
                <author n="BehretMariusNIEKLER_Andreas_Cultural_Motifs_on__bigdata___A_Semi_Automat.xml"><persName n="BehretMarius">
                        <surname>Behret</surname>
                        <forename>Marius</forename>
                    </persName><affiliation>Leipzig University, Germany</affiliation><email>m.behret@studserv.uni-leipzig.de</email></author><meeting><date from-iso="2023-07-10" to-iso="2023-07-14"/><title>Digital Humanities 2023. Collaboration as Opportunity</title><placeName>Graz</placeName></meeting>
                <author n="PentzoldChristianNIEKLER_Andreas_Cultural_Motifs_on__bigdata___A_Semi_Automat.xml"><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-6355-3150" n="PentzoldChristian">
                        <surname>Pentzold</surname>
                        <forename>Christian</forename>
                    </persName><affiliation>Leipzig University, Germany</affiliation><email>christian.pentzold@uni-leipzig.de</email></author><meeting><date from-iso="2023-07-10" to-iso="2023-07-14"/><title>Digital Humanities 2023. Collaboration as Opportunity</title><placeName>Graz</placeName></meeting>
            </titleStmt>
            
            <publicationStmt><publisher><orgName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1137284463">Zentrum für Informationsmodellierung
                    - Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities, Karl-Franzens-Universität
                    Graz</orgName></publisher><date when="2023">2023</date><pubPlace>Graz</pubPlace><availability><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">Creative Commons BY
                    4.0</licence></availability></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title>Digital Humanities 2023: Book of Abstracts</title><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-9256-0958"><forename>Walter</forename><surname>Scholger</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>University of Graz</orgName><placeName>Graz, Austria</placeName></affiliation><email>walter.scholger@uni-graz.at</email></editor><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-1726-1712"><forename>Georg</forename><surname>Vogeler</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>University of Graz</orgName><placeName>Graz, Austria</placeName></affiliation><email>georg.vogeler@uni-graz.at</email></editor><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-3919-993X"><forename>Toma</forename><surname>Tasovac</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>Belgrade Center for Digital Humanities</orgName><placeName>Belgrade, Serbia</placeName></affiliation><email>ttasovac@humanistika.org</email></editor><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-4593-059X"><forename>Anne</forename><surname>Baillot</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>Le Mans Université</orgName><placeName>Le Mans, France</placeName></affiliation><email>anne.baillot@univ-lemans.fr</email></editor><respStmt><resp>Data Management</resp><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0009-0007-9019-8215"><forename>Elisabeth</forename><surname>Raunig</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Management</resp><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-1438-3236"><forename>Martina</forename><surname>Scholger</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Management</resp><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-9116-0402"><forename>Elisabeth</forename><surname>Steiner</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Curation</resp><persName><forename>Johanna</forename><surname>Ofenauer</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Curation</resp><persName><forename>Christina</forename><surname>Burgstaller</surname></persName></respStmt><idno type="DOI">10.5281/zenodo.7961822</idno></seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="DHCONVALIDATOR" version="1.22">
                    <label>DHConvalidator</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc><abstract><p>In this study, we show a possible operationalization of the sociocultural framing concept by van Gorp (2010). Communication Research and Computational Humanities are exploring how the keyword #bigdata can be investigated via combined approaches of both framing analysis and topic modeling. A first study shows, how both methodological approaches complement each other profitably regarding the analysis of cultural motifs, which in turn allows to quantitatively capture such abstract and complex concepts in large data sets.</p></abstract><langUsage><language ident="en">English</language></langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="category">
                    <term>Paper</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="subcategory">
                    <term>Long Presentation</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="keywords">
                    <term>Framing Analysis</term>
                    <term>Framing Achors</term>
                    <term>Topic Modeling</term>
                    <term>Themes</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="topics">
                    <term>cultural analytics</term>
                    <term>mixed-media analysis</term>
                    <term>Communication studies</term>
                    
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div type="div1">
                <head>Abstract</head>
                <p><hi rend="italic">In this study, we show a possible
                        operationalization of the sociocultural framing concept by van Gorp (2010).
                        Communication Research and Computational Humanities are exploring how the
                        keyword #bigdata can be investigated via combined approaches of both framing
                        analysis and topic modeling. A first study shows, how both methodological
                        approaches complement each other profitably regarding the analysis of
                        cultural motifs, which in turn allows to quantitatively capture such
                        abstract and complex concepts in large data sets.</hi></p>
            </div>
            <div type="div1">
                <head>Aim</head>
                <p>Part of the history of science is its
                    self-constitution through discourse, also its conceptualization and
                    implementation of both theoretical and methodological approaches. Hereby,
                    scientific discourse can be facilitated by research collaborations in which
                    already proven theoretical approaches, and methodological procedures can be
                    tested collaboratively to adapt them, for example, to examine new media and data
                    environments. This work reports on such a collaboration.</p>
                <p>As part of the project Framing Big Data (Deutsche
                        Forschungsgemeinschaft (DFG) 447465824), which started in April 2021, the
                        departments Computational Humanities and Media and Communication Research
                        (both Leipzig University) are conducting a joint research program to
                        investigate how the media-communicative framing of Big Data can be
                        collected, analyzed, and evaluated both on a cross-national and on a
                        time-comparative basis. We examine the media-communicative framing of Big
                        Data and globally datafied processes in both press- and user-generated
                        aggregates (Facebook, Reddit, Twitter) over a period of the last 10 years
                        and in three countries (U.S., Germany, and South Africa) using both
                        frame-analytic and discursive approaches.</p>
                <p>In a way, we are researching large quantities of text data about Big Data. In our data, thousands of press releases and social media data from Facebook, Reddit and Twitter, extracted on the keywords #bigdata and “Big Data”, we recognize discursive references to public events such as political debates on regulation, election campaigns, data scandals, and economic innovations in the tech business. Following Gamson and Modigliani, a discourse can be understood as “a set of discourses that interact in complex ways” (Gamson, &amp; Modigliani, 1989, p. 2). However, the discourse on Big Data is apparently triggered by the keyword Big Data, which in turn is not associated with a single topic. Moreover, several themes at different times are merged, which – in addition – are hardly reflected by key events in our data. Furthermore, resonance effects between User Generated Content (UGC) and the press – as they are consensus in framing research (e.g., Benford, &amp; Snow, 2000) – seem to be mostly absent in the discourse on Big Data. </p>
                <p>This is where this report comes in: The Departments
                        Media and Communication Research and Computational Humanities at Leipzig
                        University are exploring how #bigdata can be investigated via combined
                        approaches of both framing analysis and topic modeling. We ask: How can
                        Topic Modeling be designed to reveal in Topics not only individual issues,
                        but also their implicit and frame-analytic references?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="div1">
                <head>Background</head>
                <p>Starting from a socio-cultural framing approach (Van
                        Gorp, 2010), we argument that each topic of #bigdata contains semantic
                        domain-typical patterns. These domain-typical patterns are subject to a
                        nature-given implicitness (Ryan, &amp; Gamson, 2006). Furthermore, these
                        patterns refer to the frames, which become visible over time in the
                        discourse on Big Data. Hereby, cultural motifs provide meaning to these
                        patterns. Following Van Gorp (2010), cultural motifs are “the implicit
                        cultural phenomenon” (p. 97) that can be extracted from a statement. In this
                        vein, cultural motifs become visible in annotating an event or an actor – be
                        it via hashtag, tweet, post, thread, subreddit or even just a hyperlink. We
                        argue, the cultural motifs serve as anchor for both framing analysis and
                        Topic Modeling. How Big Data is referred to over time, which frames are
                        initiated and addressed, is anchored in their topics with their specific
                        cultural motifs.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="div1">
                <head>Study</head>
                <p>During the manual coding process, we preliminary read
                        20 books that dealt with Big Data as socio-technological phenomenon (boyd
                        &amp; Crawford, 2012). Applying an inductive-deductive based framing
                        analysis (Van Gorp, 2010), we were able to identify eight cultural motifs
                        (Fig. 2). Afterwards, the paragraphs from the books, the manual analysis was
                        based on, were used as the basis for the Topic Model. We followed the
                        approach of Maier et. al. (2018) to implement a methodologically valid
                        processing chain for the modeling approach. Each paragraph represents a
                        document, and typical NLP-procedures and preprocessing-steps (Fig. 1) were
                        used to further process the textual data. We extracted significant
                        collocations but not all bigrams to represent important multiword tokens.
                        Then, we applied the implementation from the topicmodels package in R to the
                        data and the hyperparameters of the Topic Model were deter-mined by using
                        the Jensen-Shannon-Divergence from the ldatuning package. Afterwards, the
                        generated Topic Model was validated and finally evaluated by comparing the
                        manually coded cultural motives with the Top-20 terms from each topic from
                        the Topic Model, which showed that the results from the Topic Model are
                        similar to the results of the manual coding process.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic n="1001" width="16.002cm" height="3.903486111111111cm" url="Pictures/7aed1e2df68b98fe41a38a6aa0f9802f.png" rend="inline"/>

                    <head>Figure 1: Representation of the process chain (left to right) from manual
                        coding to the assignment of subjects to the manually determined motifs. For
                        the steps, the methodological implementation was essentially based on (Maier
                        et. al.).</head>
                </figure>
                <p>Interestingly, quite comprehensible cultural motifs
                        emerge such as data capitalism, Surveillance, crime prevention, increased
                        efficiency or social empowerment (Figure 2). Where, i.e. within which
                        digital spaces/platforms and with the help of which technical affordances
                        #bigdata is thematized and thereby framed in terms of media communication,
                        is not only a technical question, but also a socio-political one. A
                        different openness to technological innovations can be stated during the
                        last ten years. Also, the political governance for data protection and data
                        storage have become more critical. In this vein, the results gained are also
                        to be discussed collaboratively and against the background of the increasing
                        datafication of society and science.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic n="1002" width="15.998472222222222cm" height="13.423194444444444cm" url="Pictures/6b1657e14797f14a783c41ce5a931ebd.png" rend="inline"/>

                    <head>Figure 2: Illustration of the identified motives in the manually coded
                        data and the assignment process to the result of the Topic Model. The
                        assignment of specific colors was initially done by the researchers and the
                        transfer of colors was then supported with a text search. First, the
                        cultural themes were translated into English and then synonyms were
                        identified. The synonyms were searched for in the topics table and colored
                        when found. We added more words to the search based on our understanding of
                        their meanings and cultural motifs and colored them accordingly.</head>
                </figure>
            </div>
            <div type="div1">
                <head>Final Remarks</head>
                <p>The collaboration between Computational Humanities
                        and Media and Communication Research is fruitful for several reasons: First,
                        the tangible benefits of a frame-based topic modeling can be highlighted.
                        With the application of a topic model, it is possible to practically
                        replicate the manually detected cultural motifs based on pre-coded
                        paragraphs. Secondly, manual and automated approaches can be contrasted,
                        which means in that case, to improve the manual frame analysis from the
                        books with the help of automated procedures. Likewise, the results from the
                        semi-manual and semi-automated methods can be used as seeds in a
                        mixed-method scenario to analyze frames in large datasets. By creating a
                        Topic Model based on an inductive-deductive framework analysis, we can
                        search for cultural motifs in very large data sets and ultimately evaluate
                        them quantitatively. A modeling process guided in this way enables the valid
                        traceability of searched phenomena in very large data sources.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliogr">
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Benford, R. D., &amp; Snow, D. A.</author> (2000). <hi rend="italic">Framing </hi>
                        <hi rend="italic">Processes</hi>
                        <hi rend="italic"> and </hi>
                        <hi rend="italic">Social</hi>
                        <hi rend="italic">Movements</hi>
                        <hi rend="italic">: An Over-view and
                            Assessment</hi>
                        . Annual Review 
                        of
                        Sociology
                        , 26, 611–639.
                            http://www.jstor.org/stable/223459
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>boyd, d., &amp; Crawford, K.</author> (2012). <hi rend="italic">Critical Questions </hi>
                        <hi rend="italic">for</hi>
                        <hi rend="italic"> Big Data: </hi>
                        <hi rend="italic">Provocations</hi>
                        <hi rend="italic">for</hi>
                        <hi rend="italic"> a Cultural, Technological, and </hi>
                        <hi rend="italic">Scholarly</hi>
                        <hi rend="italic">Phenomenon</hi>
                        <hi rend="italic">. Information</hi>
                        , Communication &amp; Society, 15(5), 662–679. https://doi.org/10.1080/1369118X.2012.678878 
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Gamson, W. A., &amp; Modigliani, A.</author> (1989). <hi rend="italic">Media </hi>
                        <hi rend="italic">Discourse</hi>
                        <hi rend="italic"> and Public Opinion on </hi>
                        <hi rend="italic">Nuclear</hi>
                        <hi rend="italic"> Pow-er: A </hi>
                        <hi rend="italic">Constructionist</hi>
                        <hi rend="italic"> Approach</hi>
                        . American Journal 
                        of
                        Sociology
                        , 95(1), 1–37.
                            https://www.jstor.org/stable/2780405
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Ryan, C., &amp; Gamson, W. A.</author> (2006). <hi rend="italic">The Art </hi>
                        <hi rend="italic">of</hi>
                        <hi rend="italic"> Reframing Political </hi>
                        <hi rend="italic">Debates</hi>
                        . 
                        Contexts
                        , 5(1), 13–18.
                            https://doi.org/10.1525/ctx.2006.5.1.13
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Maier, D., Waldherr, A., Miltner, P., Wiedemann, G.,
                            Niekler, A., Keinert, A., Pfetsch, B., Heyer, G., Reber, U., Häussler,
                            T., Schmid-Petri, H., &amp; Adam, S.</author> (2018). <hi rend="italic">Applying</hi>
                        <hi rend="italic"> LDA </hi>
                        <hi rend="italic">topic</hi>
                        <hi rend="italic">modeling</hi>
                        <hi rend="italic"> in </hi>
                        <hi rend="italic">communication</hi>
                        <hi rend="italic">research</hi>
                        <hi rend="italic">: </hi>
                        <hi rend="italic">Toward</hi>
                        <hi rend="italic"> a valid and reliable </hi>
                        <hi rend="italic">methodology</hi>
                        <hi rend="italic">. Communication Methods and </hi>
                        <hi rend="italic">Measures</hi>
                        , 1–26.
                            https://doi.org/10.1080/19312458.2018.1430754
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Van Gorp, B.</author> (2010). Strategies
                        to
                         Take 
                        Subjectivity
                         Out 
                        of
                         Framing Analysis. In P. D´Angelo &amp; J. A. Kuypers (Eds.), Communication Series. 
                        <hi rend="italic">Doing</hi>
                        <hi rend="italic"> News Framing Analysis: </hi>
                        <hi rend="italic">Empirical</hi>
                        <hi rend="italic"> and </hi>
                        <hi rend="italic">Theoretical</hi>
                        <hi rend="italic">Perspectives</hi>
                         (pp. 84–109). Routledge.
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text></TEI>