<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_allPlus.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_allPlus.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Systematic Gender Asymmetries in Aesthetic Judgments: An Observational Study
                    of Book Reviewer Preferences</title>
                <author n="LassenIdaMarieSNIELBO_Kristoffer_Systematic_Gender_Asymmetries_in_Aesthetic.xml"><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-6905-5665" n="LassenIdaMarieS">
                        <surname>Lassen</surname>
                        <forename>Ida Marie S.</forename>
                    </persName><affiliation>Center for Humanities Computing, Aarhus University,
                        Denmark</affiliation><email>idamarie@cas.au.dk</email></author><meeting><date from-iso="2023-07-10" to-iso="2023-07-14"/><title>Digital Humanities 2023. Collaboration as Opportunity</title><placeName>Graz</placeName></meeting>
                <author n="BizzoniYuriNIELBO_Kristoffer_Systematic_Gender_Asymmetries_in_Aesthetic.xml"><persName n="BizzoniYuri">
                        <surname>Bizzoni</surname>
                        <forename>Yuri</forename>
                    </persName><affiliation>Center for Humanities Computing, Aarhus University, Denmark; School
                        of Communication and Culture - Comparative Literature, Aarhus University,
                        Denmark</affiliation><email>yuri.bizzoni@cc.au.dk</email></author><meeting><date from-iso="2023-07-10" to-iso="2023-07-14"/><title>Digital Humanities 2023. Collaboration as Opportunity</title><placeName>Graz</placeName></meeting>
                <author n="ThomsenMadsRNIELBO_Kristoffer_Systematic_Gender_Asymmetries_in_Aesthetic.xml"><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-4975-6752" n="ThomsenMadsR">
                        <surname>Thomsen</surname>
                        <forename>Mads R.</forename>
                    </persName><affiliation>School of Communication and Culture - Comparative Literature,
                        Aarhus University, Denmark</affiliation><email>madsrt@cc.au.dk</email></author><meeting><date from-iso="2023-07-10" to-iso="2023-07-14"/><title>Digital Humanities 2023. Collaboration as Opportunity</title><placeName>Graz</placeName></meeting>
                <author n="NielboKristofferNIELBO_Kristoffer_Systematic_Gender_Asymmetries_in_Aesthetic.xml"><persName n="NielboKristoffer">
                        <surname>Nielbo</surname>
                        <forename>Kristoffer</forename>
                    </persName><affiliation>Center for Humanities Computing, Aarhus University,
                        Denmark</affiliation><email>kln@cas.au.dk</email></author><meeting><date from-iso="2023-07-10" to-iso="2023-07-14"/><title>Digital Humanities 2023. Collaboration as Opportunity</title><placeName>Graz</placeName></meeting>
            </titleStmt>
            
            <publicationStmt><publisher><orgName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1137284463">Zentrum für Informationsmodellierung
                    - Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities, Karl-Franzens-Universität
                    Graz</orgName></publisher><date when="2023">2023</date><pubPlace>Graz</pubPlace><availability><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">Creative Commons BY
                    4.0</licence></availability></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title>Digital Humanities 2023: Book of Abstracts</title><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-9256-0958"><forename>Walter</forename><surname>Scholger</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>University of Graz</orgName><placeName>Graz, Austria</placeName></affiliation><email>walter.scholger@uni-graz.at</email></editor><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-1726-1712"><forename>Georg</forename><surname>Vogeler</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>University of Graz</orgName><placeName>Graz, Austria</placeName></affiliation><email>georg.vogeler@uni-graz.at</email></editor><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-3919-993X"><forename>Toma</forename><surname>Tasovac</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>Belgrade Center for Digital Humanities</orgName><placeName>Belgrade, Serbia</placeName></affiliation><email>ttasovac@humanistika.org</email></editor><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-4593-059X"><forename>Anne</forename><surname>Baillot</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>Le Mans Université</orgName><placeName>Le Mans, France</placeName></affiliation><email>anne.baillot@univ-lemans.fr</email></editor><respStmt><resp>Data Management</resp><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0009-0007-9019-8215"><forename>Elisabeth</forename><surname>Raunig</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Management</resp><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-1438-3236"><forename>Martina</forename><surname>Scholger</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Management</resp><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-9116-0402"><forename>Elisabeth</forename><surname>Steiner</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Curation</resp><persName><forename>Johanna</forename><surname>Ofenauer</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Curation</resp><persName><forename>Christina</forename><surname>Burgstaller</surname></persName></respStmt><idno type="DOI">10.5281/zenodo.7961822</idno></seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="DHCONVALIDATOR" version="1.22">
                    <label>DHConvalidator</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc><abstract><p>Aesthetic preferences are considered highly subjective resulting in inherently noisy judgments of aesthetic objects, yet certain aspects of aesthetic judgment display convergent trends over time. This paper presents a study that uses literary reviews as a proxy for aesthetic judgment in order to identify systematic components that can be attributed to bias. Specifically, we find that judgment of literary quality in newspapers displays a gender bias in preference of male writers. Male reviewers have a same gender preference while female reviewers show an opposite gender preference. While alternative accounts exist of this apparent gender disparity, we argue that it reflects a cultural gender antagonism.</p></abstract><langUsage><language ident="en">English</language></langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="category">
                    <term>Paper</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="subcategory">
                    <term>Long Presentation</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="keywords">
                    <term>Aesthetic Judgement</term>
                    <term>Gender</term>
                    <term>Bias Analysis</term>
                    <term>Literary Review</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="topics">
                    <term>artificial intelligence and machine learning</term>
                    <term>cultural analytics</term>
                    <term>Feminist studies</term>
                    <term>Humanities computing</term>
                    
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <p>Aesthetic judgments are notoriously complex and
                    subject to considerable variation because aesthetic objects are complex,
                    aesthetic preferences are subjective, and there is a general lack of shared
                    measurement. Literary quality, for instance, can be considered one of the most
                    subjective fields of evaluation, and variation is mostly attributable to noise
                    introduced by individual preferences. Yet the perception of literary quality
                    from many readers over time does show convergent trends: communities tend to
                    establish and update canons (Guillory 1993); specific texts and narratives
                    manage to remain popular (Stephens / McCallum 2013) despite the changing of
                    fashions and political phases, and certain author names become eponymous of
                    literary quality in different countries and throughout the social spectrum
                    (Bloom 2014). Some facets of literary quality can be explained in terms of the
                    literary content (e.g., predictability of content, coherence of the narrative),
                    while others depend on sociocultural priors that introduce systematic variation
                    in aesthetic judgments. It is the latter that are the object of this study,
                    specifically the possible effects of gender on the assessment of literary
                    quality as an example of how aesthetic judgments can be biased by contextual
                    factors.</p>
                <p>The problem of literary quality’s subjective status
                        becomes even more intriguing when we turn to the challenge of its
                        computational assessment. Most studies assume the possibility of a
                        one-dimensional ground truth by modelling literary quality as a single
                        rating or class associated with a text (Ferrer 2013; Wang et al. 2019; Walsh
                        / Antoniak, 2021). These ground truths are retrieved from various sources:
                        literary critics, book sale numbers, bestseller lists, or crowd-sourced
                        reader opinions. Such approaches have several limitations: Relying only on
                        experts’ judgment (e.g., awards, prestigious reviews) biases the model to
                        reflect their preferences, but striving for representativity by
                        crowd-sourcing opinions ends up ignoring important differences in the
                        readers’ population. To properly understand the value of these ground truths
                        and develop standardised measures of quality, it is necessary to model
                        possible sources of bias.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Methods</head>
                <div>
                    <head>Data</head>
                    <p>The data set covers book reviews published in
                            Danish media in the years 2010-2021. The data were retrieved from the
                            online platform<ref target="https://bog.nu/">bog.nu</ref>’s API which collects book reviews published in
                            Danish media. See table 1 for a brief overview of the data set.</p>
                    <figure>
                        <graphic n="1001" width="16.002cm" height="3.3566805555555557cm" url="Pictures/6f59fefda5464a3bc88cbd9880c987b0.png" rend="inline"/>
                    </figure>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Grade Transformation and Estimation</head>
                    <p>As different media use different grading scales,
                            the grades on bog.nu are transformed to a 100-point grading scale. This
                            approach, however, results in a sparse distribution of grades as the use
                            of the original grading scales maps onto different intervals on the
                            100-point scale. Instead of this naive approach, we have used the
                            original grade and applied a linear transformation to map all grades to
                            a shared 6-point scale<ref target="#NIELBO_Kristoffer_Systematic_Gender_Asymmetries_in_Aesthetic.xml_ftn1" n="1"/>. Mapping from an a-b–point scale to a 1-6–point
                            scale:</p>
                    <figure>
                        <graphic n="1002" width="16.002cm" height="1.1624027777777777cm" url="Pictures/4aa98cfe2e5fda0cb1ea2474f8ef86d6.png" rend="inline"/>
                    </figure>
                    <p>Figure 1 shows the distributions of grades in
                        Danish Newspapers transformed into a shared 6–point scale. See equation (1).
                        Some media do not provide a grade in a given review but only a qualitative
                        review. Bog.nu does, however, provide a quantification of the review, which
                        is estimated by an expert. For reviews written in Danish newspapers, this
                        estimation procedure is used in less than 25% of the cases.</p>
                    <figure>
                        <graphic n="1003" width="16.002cm" height="6.801555555555556cm" url="Pictures/8e7b4915d9a4c4eea70eff75482d63a0.png" rend="inline"/>
                    </figure>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Gender Retrieval</head>
                    <p>The original data set from bog.nu does not
                            contain gender for all authors and reviewers. We used an API<ref target="#NIELBO_Kristoffer_Systematic_Gender_Asymmetries_in_Aesthetic.xml_ftn2" n="2"/> built on binary gendered name lists to retrieve the missing gender variables. We are aware of the problems with this method and how it rules out other gender identities (Dev et al. 2021). However, a binary representation of gender is necessary for our analysis to understand the existing structures between men and women in contemporary society.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Model</head>
                    <p>In order to estimate the effect, the relative
                            effect of author and reviewer gender on the reviewer assigned grade
                            (six-point scale), we solve the following linear model with the null
                            model that<hi rend="italic">β</hi><hi rend="italic subscript">author</hi><hi rend="italic"> = β</hi><hi rend="italic subscript">reviewer </hi><hi rend="italic">= 0:</hi></p>
                    <figure>
                        <graphic n="1004" width="16.239344444444445cm" height="0.8270027777777778cm" url="Pictures/5d2517ad7d26119cf8f7eeca3647c5c0.png" rend="inline"/>
                    </figure>
                    <p>Where<hi rend="italic">y</hi><hi rend="italic subscript">i</hi>is the grade of review<hi rend="italic">i, x</hi><hi rend="italic subscript">i</hi> is the
                            predictor value (gender) of review<hi rend="italic">i, β</hi>represents unknown parameters, and <hi rend="italic">ε</hi>are the error terms.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Results</head>
                <p>Solving for<hi rend="italic">y</hi><hi rend="italic subscript">i</hi>in the model above with ordinary least square (OLS),
                        we get the following results, see Table 2. The model and all contrasts are
                        statistically significant (p &lt; .0001) Conceptually, same-gender (male *
                        male, female * female) reviews span the extreme values, while opposite
                        gender (female * male, male * female) reviews represent the middle of the
                        distribution, see Fig. 2. Female reviewers reviewing female authors account
                        for the, on average lowest grade. Male reviewers reviewing male authors
                        result in the highest grade, with a 0.2 average grade increase.
                        Opposite-gender reviews are statistically speaking, indistinguishable, but
                        they differ on average 0.1 grade point from same-gender scoring.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic n="1005" width="16.46836111111111cm" height="3.091447222222222cm" url="Pictures/faaddd0f9ee8a76e2784450e5e5c820a.png" rend="inline"/>
                </figure>
                <figure>
                    <graphic n="1006" width="16.002cm" height="7.101416666666666cm" url="Pictures/fe0cf3c313f68bc4c1f0a7769b104282.png" rend="inline"/>
                </figure>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Discussion</head>
                <p>In line with the results in Thelwall (2019) and Touileb et al. (2020), our results show that the gender of authors as well as of reviewers play a role in literary reviews written in Danish newspapers. In particular, the results above show that men review same-gender more positively than the opposite gender and that women show the reverse pattern, that is, same-gender is reviewed more negatively than the opposite gender. A partial explanation of the behaviour is that if males display a same-gender preference and male reviewers make up the majority of newspaper reviewers, then the gender minority adapt to this preference and develops a same-gender antagonism. At a more general level, the same gender preference of men in aesthetic judgment may reflect a cultural gender antagonism that follows a long historical trajectory. The female opposite gender preference is very likely to follow the same cultural gender antagonism. </p>
                <p>We are not arguing that newspapers follow an explicit
                        exclusionary strategy formulated by male reviewers and editors. Whenever we
                        make a judgment, there are essentially two sources of error, bias and noise.
                        While noise is randomly distributed and lacks a systematic explanatory
                        mechanism, biases are systematic and can be explained in terms of a
                        mechanism. Demographic biases often originate in a systemic oppression of
                        minority groups. For the specific review cases, the results are likely to
                        mirror existing oppressive structures in the society such as those found in
                        Dane (2020); MacNell et al. (2015); Johnson and Kirk (2020); Goldin and
                        Rouse (2000); Booth and Leigh (2010); Cole et al. (2004). We expect that
                        majority groups, in general, will define norms and values that result in
                        biased judgments irrespective of societal domain. Denmark is an excellent
                        example of how more or less explicit biases persist in the face of societal
                        countermeasures (ex. equal rights, parity policies) and in general high
                        gender equality.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="notes"><note n="1" xml:id="NIELBO_Kristoffer_Systematic_Gender_Asymmetries_in_Aesthetic.xml_ftn1">
                            It should be noted that most six-point
                                    scales have become the standard in many review outlets.
                        </note><note n="2" xml:id="NIELBO_Kristoffer_Systematic_Gender_Asymmetries_in_Aesthetic.xml_ftn2">
                            <ref target="https://genderize.io/">https://genderize.io/</ref>
                        </note></div><div type="bibliogr">
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Bloom, Harold</author>
                         (2014): 
                        <hi rend="italic">The western canon: The books and
                            school of the ages</hi>
                        . Houghton Mifflin Harcourt.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Booth, Alison</author> / <author>Leigh, Andrew</author> 
                         (2010): “Do employers discriminate by gender? A field experiment in female-dominated occupations”, in: 
                        <hi rend="italic">Economics Letters</hi>
                         107.2, pp. 236–238.
                        <ref target="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/abs/pii/S0165176510000352">https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/abs/pii/S0165176510000352</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Cole, Michael S.</author> / <author>Hubert, S. Feild</author> / <author>Giles, William F.</author> 
                        (2004): “Interaction of recruiter and applicant gender in resume evaluation: a field study”. In: 
                        <hi rend="italic">Sex Roles</hi>
                         51.9, pp. 597–608.
                        <ref target="https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s11199-004-5469-1">https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s11199-004-5469-1</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Dane, Alexandra</author> (2020):
                        <hi rend="italic">Gender and Prestige in
                            Literature</hi>.
                         Springer.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Dev, Sunipa</author> / <author>Monajatipoor, Masoud</author> / <author>Ovalle, Anaelia</author> / <author>Subramonian, Arjun</author> / <author>Phillips, Jeff M.</author> / <author>Chang, Kai-Wei</author> 
                        (2021): “Harms of Gender Exclusivity and Challenges in Non-Binary Representation in Language Technologies”, in: 
                        <hi rend="italic">Proceedings of the 2021 Conference on Empirical Methods in Natural Language Processing </hi>
                        <ref target="https://aclanthology.org/2021.emnlp-main.150/">https://aclanthology.org/2021.emnlp-main.150/</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Ferrer, Carolina </author>
                        (2013): “Canonical values vs. the Law of large numbers: The Canadian Literary Canon in the Age of Big Data”, in: 
                        <hi rend="italic">Rupkatha Journal on
                            Interdisciplinary Studies in Humanities,</hi>
                         5.3, pp. 81–90.
                        <ref target="https://www.semanticscholar.org/paper/Canonical-Values-vs.-the-Law-of-Large-Numbers%3A-The-Ferrer/844a4cfbea9fd16a8fbaeedcf3bb77f74d64425b">https://www.semanticscholar.org/paper/Canonical-Values-vs.-the-Law-of-Large-Numbers%3A-The-Ferrer/844a4cfbea9fd16a8fbaeedcf3bb77f74d64425b</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Goldin, Claudia</author> / <author>Rouse, Cecilia</author> 
                        (2000): “Orchestrating impartiality: The impact of" blind" auditions on female musicians”, in: 
                        <hi rend="italic">American economic review,</hi>
                         90.4, pp. 715–741.
                        <ref target="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/aer.90.4.715">https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/aer.90.4.715</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Guillory, John</author> (1993):
                        <hi rend="italic">Cultural capital: The problem of
                            literary canon formation</hi>
                        . University of Chicago Press.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Johnson, Stefanie K</author> / <author>Kirk, Jessica F.</author> 
                        (2020): “Dual-anonymization yields promising results for reducing gender bias: A naturalistic field experiment of applications for Hubble Space Telescope time”, in: 
                        <hi rend="italic">Publications of the Astronomical
                            Society of the Pacific,</hi>
                        132.1009, p. 034503.
                        <ref target="https://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.1088/1538-3873/ab6ce0">https://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.1088/1538-3873/ab6ce0</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>MacNell, Lillian</author> / <author>Adam Driscoll</author> / <author>Andrea N Hunt</author> 
                        (2015): “What’s in a name: Exposing gender bias in student ratings of teaching”, in: 
                        <hi rend="italic">Innovative Higher Education</hi>
                        , 40.4, pp. 291–303.
                        <ref target="https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s10755-014-9313-4">https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s10755-014-9313-4</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Stephens, John</author> / <author>Robyn McCallum</author> 
                        (2013):
                        <hi rend="italic">Retelling stories, framing culture:
                            traditional story and metanarratives in children’s literature.</hi>
                         Routledge.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Thelwall, Mike </author>
                        (2019): “Reader and author gender and genre in Goodreads”, in: 
                        <hi rend="italic">Journal of Librarianship and
                            Information Science</hi>
                         51.2, pp. 403–430. 
                        <ref target="https://journals.sagepub.com/doi/10.1177/0961000617709061">https://journals.sagepub.com/doi/10.1177/0961000617709061</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Touileb, Samia</author> / <author>Øvrelid, Lilja</author> / <author>Velldal, Erik</author> 
                        (2020): “Gender and sentiment, critics and authors: a dataset of Norwegian book reviews”, in: 
                        <hi rend="italic">Proceedings of the Second Workshop
                            on Gender Bias in Natural Language Processing</hi>
                        . Barcelona, Spain (Online): Association for Computational Linguistics, pp. 125–138. 
                        <ref target="https://aclanthology.org/2020.gebnlp-1.11/">https://aclanthology.org/2020.gebnlp-1.11/</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Walsh, Melanie</author> / <author>Antoniak, Maria</author> 
                        (2021): “The Goodreads ‘Classics’: A Computational Study of Readers, Amazon, and Crowdsourced Amateur Criticism”, in: 
                        <hi rend="italic">Journal of Cultural Analytics</hi>
                         4, pp. 243–287.
                        <ref target="https://culturalanalytics.org/article/22221-the-goodreads-classics-a-computational-study-of-readers-amazon-and-crowdsourced-amateur-criticism">https://culturalanalytics.org/article/22221-the-goodreads-classics-a-computational-study-of-readers-amazon-and-crowdsourced-amateur-criticism</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Wang, Xindi</author> / <author>Yucesoy, Burcu</author> / <author>Varol, Onur</author> / <author>Eliassi-Rad, Tina</author> / <author>Barabási, Albert-László</author> 
                        (2019): “Success in books: predicting book sales
                            before publication”, in:
                        <hi rend="italic">EPJ Data Science,</hi>
                         8.1,pp. 1–20. 
                        <ref target="https://epjdatascience.springeropen.com/articles/10.1140/epjds/s13688-019-0208-6">https://epjdatascience.springeropen.com/articles/10.1140/epjds/s13688-019-0208-6</ref>
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text></TEI>