<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_allPlus.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_allPlus.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title> Word Clouds with Spatial Stable Word Positions across
                        Multiple Text Witnesses </title>
                <author n="DhneJanisP_CKELMANN_Marcus__Word_Clouds_with_Spatial_Stable_Word_Posi.xml"><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-9009-4148" n="DhneJanis">
                        <surname>Dähne</surname>
                        <forename>Janis</forename>
                    </persName><affiliation>Martin Luther University Halle-Wittenberg, Germany</affiliation><email>janis.daehne@informatik.uni-halle.de</email></author><meeting><date from-iso="2023-07-10" to-iso="2023-07-14"/><title>Digital Humanities 2023. Collaboration as Opportunity</title><placeName>Graz</placeName></meeting>
                <author n="PckelmannMarcusP_CKELMANN_Marcus__Word_Clouds_with_Spatial_Stable_Word_Posi.xml"><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-8718-1198" n="PckelmannMarcus">
                        <surname>Pöckelmann</surname>
                        <forename>Marcus</forename>
                    </persName><affiliation>Martin Luther University Halle-Wittenberg, Germany</affiliation><email>marcus.poeckelmann@informatik.uni-halle.de</email></author><meeting><date from-iso="2023-07-10" to-iso="2023-07-14"/><title>Digital Humanities 2023. Collaboration as Opportunity</title><placeName>Graz</placeName></meeting>
                <author n="RitterJrgP_CKELMANN_Marcus__Word_Clouds_with_Spatial_Stable_Word_Posi.xml"><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-3080-7801" n="RitterJrg">
                        <surname>Ritter</surname>
                        <forename>Jörg</forename>
                    </persName><affiliation>Martin Luther University Halle-Wittenberg, Germany</affiliation><email>joerg.ritter@informatik.uni-halle.de</email></author><meeting><date from-iso="2023-07-10" to-iso="2023-07-14"/><title>Digital Humanities 2023. Collaboration as Opportunity</title><placeName>Graz</placeName></meeting>
            </titleStmt>
            
            <publicationStmt><publisher><orgName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1137284463">Zentrum für Informationsmodellierung
                    - Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities, Karl-Franzens-Universität
                    Graz</orgName></publisher><date when="2023">2023</date><pubPlace>Graz</pubPlace><availability><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">Creative Commons BY
                    4.0</licence></availability></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title>Digital Humanities 2023: Book of Abstracts</title><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-9256-0958"><forename>Walter</forename><surname>Scholger</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>University of Graz</orgName><placeName>Graz, Austria</placeName></affiliation><email>walter.scholger@uni-graz.at</email></editor><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-1726-1712"><forename>Georg</forename><surname>Vogeler</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>University of Graz</orgName><placeName>Graz, Austria</placeName></affiliation><email>georg.vogeler@uni-graz.at</email></editor><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-3919-993X"><forename>Toma</forename><surname>Tasovac</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>Belgrade Center for Digital Humanities</orgName><placeName>Belgrade, Serbia</placeName></affiliation><email>ttasovac@humanistika.org</email></editor><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-4593-059X"><forename>Anne</forename><surname>Baillot</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>Le Mans Université</orgName><placeName>Le Mans, France</placeName></affiliation><email>anne.baillot@univ-lemans.fr</email></editor><respStmt><resp>Data Management</resp><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0009-0007-9019-8215"><forename>Elisabeth</forename><surname>Raunig</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Management</resp><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-1438-3236"><forename>Martina</forename><surname>Scholger</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Management</resp><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-9116-0402"><forename>Elisabeth</forename><surname>Steiner</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Curation</resp><persName><forename>Johanna</forename><surname>Ofenauer</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Curation</resp><persName><forename>Christina</forename><surname>Burgstaller</surname></persName></respStmt><idno type="DOI">10.5281/zenodo.7961822</idno></seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from an OASIS Open Document</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="DHCONVALIDATOR" version="1.22">
                    <label>DHConvalidator</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc><abstract><p>In this paper we tackle the improvement of so called spatial stable word clouds. Specifically the improvements target the performance, layout and a generalization to synchronize clouds for multiple, collated text witnesses. This allows the spatial stable word clouds to be used in interactive applications and especially in tools for scholarly editions.</p></abstract><langUsage><language ident="en">English</language></langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="category">
                    <term>Paper</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="subcategory">
                    <term>Long Presentation</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="keywords">
                    <term>Word Cloud</term>
                    <term>Visualisation</term>
                    <term>Interactiv</term>
                    <term>Distant Reading</term>
                    <term>Scholarly Edition</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="topics">
                    <term>scholarly editing and editions development</term>
                    <term>analysis</term>
                    <term>and methods</term>
                    <term>spatial &amp; spatio-temporal analysis</term>
                    <term>modeling and visualization</term>
                    <term>user experience design and analysis</term>
                    <term>Computer science</term>
                    <term>Design studies</term>
                    <term>Humanities computing</term>
                    <term>Informatics</term>
                    
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div type="div1">
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <p>Word clouds are a common and widespread visualization technique [1][2], with
                    prominent layout algorithms like Wordle [3], and can be seen as a
                    distant-reading tool. Word clouds usually represent the supposedly most
                    meaningful words of a text, according to some criteria, e.g., word length,
                    part-of-speech tags, frequency (occurrences), etc. To be able to apply word
                    clouds to larger text witnesses, the word clouds must be restricted to the top X
                    words. Especially if the word clouds have to be dynamically regenerated when the
                    criteria change. The number X should be specified by the user as a
                    parameter.</p>
                <p>Another criterion, especially for interactive applications, is to define a
                    selection window of a desired length that restricts the words displayed to those
                    within the selection window. The window can be moved over the text to restrict
                    the scope of the word cloud to the desired segments. The word cloud changes when
                    the window is moved, as different words need to be displayed. This raises a
                    problem when the same words occur in successive word clouds. To track the
                    relevance of words throughout the text, each word should be in the same place in
                    all successive clouds while moving the window, i.e., the clouds should be
                    spatial stable. The few approaches [4][5][6] known in literature to generate
                    stable word clouds are discussed in full detail by Herold et at. [9], which also
                    introduces a first algorithm to keep word positions spatial stable in one
                    cloud.</p>
                <p>This paper describes how the approach in [9] can be generalized to multiple word
                    clouds, allowing it to be used for comparing multiple text witnesses in
                    scholarly editions. Our generalization ensures that the same word is always
                    placed at the same position across all clouds even if the selection window is
                    moved. We call this property synchronous. We also describe how to improve the
                    necessary calculations that allow us to use multiple clouds interactively.</p>
                <p>We have integrated our approach into LERA [7][8], a collation tool for scholarly
                    editions <ref target="#P_CKELMANN_Marcus__Word_Clouds_with_Spatial_Stable_Word_Posi.xml_ftn1" n="1"/>. LERA can be used to discover and inspect changes among text witnesses
                    and we think our stable word clouds can facilitate this process. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="div1">
                <head>Previous state</head>
                <p>A simple solution to guarantee spatial stable word positions would be to reserve
                    a separate position for each unique word. This is not practical as the available
                    drawing space is limited. However, it is possible to identify groups of words
                    that never occur together at the same time and thus can share the same
                    position.</p>
                <p>Identifying such groups is achieved in [9] by building a word-segment occurrence
                    matrix, merging consecutive segment vectors in order to represent the selection
                    window and finally identifying orthogonal word vectors that indicate that the
                    corresponding words never occur together within the selection window. This
                    former approach was originally integrated in LERA [9], see Fig. 1, but has some
                    issues. It does not take into account the actual word dimensions, thus cannot
                    guarantee an overlap-free layout. Another limitation is, that it can only handle
                    a single text witness. For multiple text witnesses the words might appear at a
                    different positions in each cloud, breaking spatial stability across the word
                    clouds. Finally, the runtimes are too slow for interactive applications,
                    especially for multiple text witnesses.</p>
                <p><figure>
                        <graphic url="Pictures/78e477acec2e115ee16f9208d619147a.png"/>
                        <head><hi rend="bold">Figure 1</hi>. Spatial stable word cloud for the
                            single text witness “Aus der Knabenzeit” by Karl Gutzkows (edition of
                            1852) for three different selection windows (beginning, middle and end
                            of the text). The words stay (e.g. <hi rend="italic">Knaben</hi>, <hi rend="italic">red</hi>) and reappear (e.g. <hi rend="italic">Pferd</hi>, <hi rend="italic">blue</hi>) at fixed positions.
                        </head>
                    </figure></p>
            </div>
            <div type="div1">
                <head>Improving the spatial stable clouds</head>
                <p>A major improvement in runtime was achieved by utilizing bitsets/bit-vectors for
                    the word vectors in the occurrence matrix. This is possible since only the
                    occurrence of a word in each segment has to be stored. The orthogonal check for
                    two bitset word vectors is very efficient as it uses bitwise operations and we
                    further optimized it, by returning a negative result as fast as we encounter two
                    non-orthogonal bytes. The groups can now be understood as the bitwise <hi rend="italic">OR</hi> of the vectors of all words within a group. </p>
                <p>We also improved the runtime of creating the groups described in [9] by removing
                    some checks and instead reordering the word vector positions in the occurrence
                    matrix. In our implementation, we used word frequencies as a criterion for word
                    relevance, as this is most useful for our applications and it allows for another
                    optimization. We precalculate a matrix whose columns represent the cumulative
                    frequencies of a word, so that we can calculate the frequency of a word for any
                    window size in one operation.</p>
                <p>The layout of the clouds is also improved by ensuring that no word overlaps can
                    occur, allowing for an even more compact layout. This is achieved by measuring
                    all words with their required font sizes beforehand in the browser. An accurate
                    bounding box for a group is than determined by the largest bounding box of its
                    members. To get an upper bound on the required space for the words we declared a
                    maximum font size for the words. This would change the semantics of the cloud,
                    as the font size correlates with the frequency (or some other measure). We
                    compensated for that by introducing a color scale that is used for frequencies
                    above some threshold. This is in contrast to other word clouds that normally
                    uses colors randomly to better distinct words but do not carry any additional
                    information.</p>
                <p>Finally, we generalized the spatial stable word clouds for multiple text
                    witnesses by making them synchronous., i.e., words occurring in more than one
                    text witness are always placed at the same position across all word clouds, even
                    if the selection window is moved, see Fig. 2. This makes it easier to visually
                    track a word across word clouds. We achieved this by taking all word vectors of
                    all texts into account during the process of creating groups. However, we still
                    need to process information for every text individually, e.g., top X words, in
                    order for every word cloud to be used on its own. All steps are optimized in a
                    way that all interactions with the clouds, like moving the selection window or
                    changing the size of the selection window can be done interactively.</p>
                <p><figure>
                        <graphic url="Pictures/4e89fafbae320e8047c94dfdc2fc9a7e.png"/>
                        <head><hi rend="bold">Figure 2</hi>. Spatial stable word clouds can now
                            share word positions across multiple text witnesses, in this case for
                            three editions of “Histoire des deux Indes”. The prominent words are
                            “les” and “des” (by frequency) for an interactively adjustable selection
                            window of 5 segments, starting at row seven in the text alignment, only
                            the top 30 words in this window by frequency are used. Note that all
                            words, that occur in multiple clouds, are at the same positions.</head>
                    </figure></p>
            </div>
            <div type="div1">
                <head>Conclusion</head>
                <p>The stable word clouds presented in this paper allow to effectively track changes
                    in the relevance of words throughout a text, even across multiple text
                    witnesses. In combination with a collation tool for providing the data basis and
                    a selection tool, the synchronous spatial stable clouds provide a novel
                    distant-reading approach to analyze and visualize text changes for scholarly
                    editions. The improvements presented here make the approach so efficient that it
                    can be used in interactive applications. An interactive demo version of the
                    entire system can be found at: <ref target="https://lera.uzi.uni-halle.de/">https://lera.uzi.uni-halle.de</ref>. </p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="notes"><note n="1" xml:id="P_CKELMANN_Marcus__Word_Clouds_with_Spatial_Stable_Word_Posi.xml_ftn1"> Homepage of LERA: <ref target="https://lera.uzi.uni-halle.de/">https://lera.uzi.uni-halle.de</ref>
                    </note></div><div type="bibliogr">
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Seifert, C., Kump, B., Kienreich, W., Granitzer, G.,
                            Granitzer, M.</author> (2008): <hi rend="italic">On the beauty and usability
                            of tag clouds</hi>. In: 2008 12th International Conference Information
                        Visualisation. pp. 17–25. IEEE. <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1109/IV.2008.89">https://doi.org/10.1109/IV.2008.89</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Lohmann, S., Ziegler, J., Tetzlaff, L.</author> (2009): <hi rend="italic">Comparison of tag cloud layouts: </hi>
                        <hi rend="italic">Task-related performance and visual </hi>
                        <hi rend="italic">performance and visual exploration</hi>. In: Gross, T.,
                        Gulliksen, J., Kotzé, P., Oestreicher, L., Palanque, P., Prates, R.O.,
                        Winckler, M. (eds.) INTERACT 2009. LNCS, vol. 5726, pp. 392–404. Springer,
                        Heidelberg. 
                        <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-642-03655-2_43">https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-642-03655-2_43</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Feinberg, J.</author> (2010): <hi rend="italic">Wordle</hi>. In:
                        Steele, J., Iliinsky, N. (eds.) Beautiful Visualization Looking at Data
                        Through the Eyes of Experts. O’Reilly Media, Newton </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Cui, W., Wu, Y., Liu, S., Wei, F., Zhou, M.X., Qu, H.</author>
                        (2010): <hi rend="italic">Context preserving dynamic word cloud
                            visualization</hi>. In: 2010 IEEE Pacific Visualization Symposium
                        (PacificVis), pp. 121–128. IEEE. <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1109/MCG.2010.102">https://doi.org/10.1109/MCG.2010.102</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Castella, Q., Sutton, C.</author> (2014): <hi rend="italic">Word
                            storms: multiples of word clouds for visual comparison of
                        documents</hi>. In: Proceedings of the 23rd International Conference on
                        World Wide Web, pp. 665–676. ACM. <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1145/2566486.2567977">https://doi.org/10.1145/2566486.2567977</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Silva e Silva, L.G., Assunção, R.M. </author>
                        (2018): 
                        <hi rend="bold">Cowords: a probabilistic model for multiple word
                            clouds</hi>. J. Appl. Stat. 45(15), 2697–2717. 
                        <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1080/02664763.2018.1435633">https://doi.org/10.1080/02664763.2018.1435633</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Bremer, T.,Molitor, P., Pöckelmann, M., Ritter, J., Schütz
                            S.</author> (2015): <hi rend="italic">Zum Einsatz digitaler Methoden bei der
                            Erstellung und Nutzung genetischer Editionen gedruckter Texte mit
                            verschiedenen Fassungen - Das Fallbeispiel der Histoire philosphique des
                            deux Indes von Guillaume Thomas Raynal</hi>. In: Editio, R. v.
                        Nutt-Kofoth, B. Plachta and W. Woesler (eds), Volume 29, Issue 1, pp. 29–51.
                            <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1515/editio-2015-004">https://doi.org/10.1515/editio-2015-004</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Pöckelmann, M., </author>
                        <author>Medek, A., Ritter, J., Molitor, P.</author> (2022): <hi rend="italic">LERA — an interactive platform for synoptical
                            representations of multiple text witnesses</hi>. In: Digital Scholarship
                        in the Humanities, Volume 38, Issue 1, pp. 330–346. <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1093/llc/fqac021">https://doi.org/10.1093/llc/fqac021</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Herold, E., Pöckelmann, M., Berg, C., Ritter, R., Hall,
                            M.M.</author> (2019): <hi rend="italic">Stable Word-Clouds for Visualising
                            Text-Changes Over Time</hi>. International Conference on Theory and
                        Practice of Digital Libraries, TPDL2019, Oslo. Springer, Cham. pp. 224-237.
                            
                        <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-030-30760-8_20">https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-030-30760-8_20</ref>
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text></TEI>