<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_allPlus.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_allPlus.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>It Takes a Village: Building an Infrastructure for 3D Scholarly
                    Editions</title>
                <author n="PapadopoulosCostasPAPADOPOULOS_Costas_It_Takes_a_Village__Building_an_Infrastr.xml"><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-1072-5198" n="PapadopoulosCostas">
                        <surname>Papadopoulos</surname>
                        <forename>Costas</forename>
                    </persName><affiliation>Maastricht University, Netherlands, The</affiliation><email>k.papadopoulos@maastrichtuniversity.nl</email></author><meeting><date from-iso="2023-07-10" to-iso="2023-07-14"/><title>Digital Humanities 2023. Collaboration as Opportunity</title><placeName>Graz</placeName></meeting>
                <author n="SchreibmanSusanPAPADOPOULOS_Costas_It_Takes_a_Village__Building_an_Infrastr.xml"><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-8782-0794" n="SchreibmanSusan">
                        <surname>Schreibman</surname>
                        <forename>Susan</forename>
                    </persName><affiliation>Maastricht University, Netherlands, The</affiliation><email>susan.schreibman@gmail.com</email></author><meeting><date from-iso="2023-07-10" to-iso="2023-07-14"/><title>Digital Humanities 2023. Collaboration as Opportunity</title><placeName>Graz</placeName></meeting>
                <author n="GillikinSchoueriKellyPAPADOPOULOS_Costas_It_Takes_a_Village__Building_an_Infrastr.xml"><persName n="GillikinSchoueriKelly">
                        <surname>Gillikin Schoueri</surname>
                        <forename>Kelly</forename>
                    </persName><affiliation>Maastricht University, Netherlands, The</affiliation><email>k.gillikinschoueri@maastrichtuniversity.nl</email></author><meeting><date from-iso="2023-07-10" to-iso="2023-07-14"/><title>Digital Humanities 2023. Collaboration as Opportunity</title><placeName>Graz</placeName></meeting>
                <author n="CopeJamiePAPADOPOULOS_Costas_It_Takes_a_Village__Building_an_Infrastr.xml"><persName n="CopeJamie">
                        <surname>Cope</surname>
                        <forename>Jamie</forename>
                    </persName><affiliation>Smithsonian Institution</affiliation><email>CopeG@si.edu</email></author><meeting><date from-iso="2023-07-10" to-iso="2023-07-14"/><title>Digital Humanities 2023. Collaboration as Opportunity</title><placeName>Graz</placeName></meeting>
                <author n="BlundellJonPAPADOPOULOS_Costas_It_Takes_a_Village__Building_an_Infrastr.xml"><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2493-9912" n="BlundellJon">
                        <surname>Blundell</surname>
                        <forename>Jon</forename>
                    </persName><affiliation>Smithsonian Institution</affiliation><email>BlundellJ@si.edu</email></author><meeting><date from-iso="2023-07-10" to-iso="2023-07-14"/><title>Digital Humanities 2023. Collaboration as Opportunity</title><placeName>Graz</placeName></meeting>
                <author n="OgawaJunPAPADOPOULOS_Costas_It_Takes_a_Village__Building_an_Infrastr.xml"><persName n="OgawaJun">
                        <surname>Ogawa</surname>
                        <forename>Jun</forename>
                    </persName><affiliation>Center for Open Data in the Humanities, University of
                        Tokyo</affiliation><email>htjk6513khbk@gmail.com</email></author><meeting><date from-iso="2023-07-10" to-iso="2023-07-14"/><title>Digital Humanities 2023. Collaboration as Opportunity</title><placeName>Graz</placeName></meeting>
                <author n="NagasakiKiyonoriPAPADOPOULOS_Costas_It_Takes_a_Village__Building_an_Infrastr.xml"><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-5485-0567" n="NagasakiKiyonori">
                        <surname>Nagasaki</surname>
                        <forename>Kiyonori</forename>
                    </persName><affiliation>International Institute for Digital Humanities, University of
                        Tokyo</affiliation><email>nagasaki@dhii.jp</email></author><meeting><date from-iso="2023-07-10" to-iso="2023-07-14"/><title>Digital Humanities 2023. Collaboration as Opportunity</title><placeName>Graz</placeName></meeting>
            </titleStmt>
            
            <publicationStmt><publisher><orgName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1137284463">Zentrum für Informationsmodellierung
                    - Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities, Karl-Franzens-Universität
                    Graz</orgName></publisher><date when="2023">2023</date><pubPlace>Graz</pubPlace><availability><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">Creative Commons BY
                    4.0</licence></availability></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title>Digital Humanities 2023: Book of Abstracts</title><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-9256-0958"><forename>Walter</forename><surname>Scholger</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>University of Graz</orgName><placeName>Graz, Austria</placeName></affiliation><email>walter.scholger@uni-graz.at</email></editor><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-1726-1712"><forename>Georg</forename><surname>Vogeler</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>University of Graz</orgName><placeName>Graz, Austria</placeName></affiliation><email>georg.vogeler@uni-graz.at</email></editor><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-3919-993X"><forename>Toma</forename><surname>Tasovac</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>Belgrade Center for Digital Humanities</orgName><placeName>Belgrade, Serbia</placeName></affiliation><email>ttasovac@humanistika.org</email></editor><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-4593-059X"><forename>Anne</forename><surname>Baillot</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>Le Mans Université</orgName><placeName>Le Mans, France</placeName></affiliation><email>anne.baillot@univ-lemans.fr</email></editor><respStmt><resp>Data Management</resp><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0009-0007-9019-8215"><forename>Elisabeth</forename><surname>Raunig</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Management</resp><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-1438-3236"><forename>Martina</forename><surname>Scholger</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Management</resp><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-9116-0402"><forename>Elisabeth</forename><surname>Steiner</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Curation</resp><persName><forename>Johanna</forename><surname>Ofenauer</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Curation</resp><persName><forename>Christina</forename><surname>Burgstaller</surname></persName></respStmt><idno type="DOI">10.5281/zenodo.7961822</idno></seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="DHCONVALIDATOR" version="1.22">
                    <label>DHConvalidator</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc><abstract><p>This panel will explore the various aspects of what is involved, not only in conceiving and building a 3D infrastructure, but in creating 3D Scholarly editions and developing the viewers that allow stories to be created around them. It will also explore issues around training the community of the infrastructure.</p></abstract><langUsage><language ident="en">English</language></langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="category">
                    <term>Paper</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="subcategory">
                    <term>Panel</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="keywords">
                    <term>3D scholarly editions</term>
                    <term>digital infrastructure</term>
                    <term>digital storytelling</term>
                    <term>training</term>
                    <term>collaboration</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="topics">
                    <term>digital research infrastructures development and analysis</term>
                    <term>digitization (2D &amp; 3D)</term>
                    <term>Interface design</term>
                    <term>development</term>
                    <term>and analysis</term>
                    <term>scholarly editing and editions development</term>
                    <term>analysis</term>
                    <term>and methods</term>
                    <term>Archaeology</term>
                    <term>Art history</term>
                    <term>Humanities computing</term>
                    <term>Media studies</term>
                    
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <p>The rationale for the creation and development of digital scholarly editions has
                    been to use available technologies to present, analyse, and augment the text; to
                    contextualise it, to illuminate it; at times to allow the public to collaborate
                    in its creation; to view the text in terms of patterns demonstrating connections
                    not easily visible to the human eye. In short, to create a knowledge site for
                    research and dissemination (Apollon et al. 2014; Sutherland 1997; Driscoll and
                    Pierazzo 2016; Pierazzo 2015). Typically, we think of the text at the centre of
                    these editions in semantic terms: a novel, a poem, a document. But what happens
                    when we think of the text as a 3D model: be it an individual object (e.g., a
                    sculpture or an artefact) or a complex scene (an archaeological site or a city).
                    Of course, we are not the first to describe texts this way. In 1999 DF McKenzie
                    described the panoply of objects that could be open to the kinds of intensive
                    bibliographical study (transmission, production, and reception) that textual
                    scholars have traditionally reserved for print and manuscript traditions, ‘as
                    verbal, visual, oral and numeric data’ (McKenzie 1999, 13).</p>
                <p>Thus, for the infrastructure under development by the PURE3D project, the 3D
                    model is the focal point for the editions being created: annotated and glossed
                    multimodally (text, images, video as well as other models) with the apparatus
                    displayed within the same information space as the model itself. Different 3D
                    viewers are utilised to serve different audiences: from more publicly focussed
                    narrative-based viewers (e.g., Smithsonian Voyager developed by the Smithsonian)
                    to more scholarly information-based viewers (developed by PURE3D). Viewers
                    reside within an infrastructure that also provides a preservation layer so that
                    all the assets of the edition (as well as preservation versions of the models)
                    can be securely stored for long term use and reuse.  </p>
                <p>In the title of this panel, we write that it takes a village to create the
                    infrastructure. The collaboration spans three continents, with the main project
                    team in The Netherlands, utilising a viewer developed by The Smithsonian
                    Institution (Washington DC), being informed by colleagues creating their own
                    editions in Japan, in addition to a range of heritage institutions creating
                    editions in The Netherlands. </p>
                <p>This panel will explore the various aspects of what is involved, not only in
                    conceiving and building the infrastructure, but in creating the 3D editions and
                    developing the viewers that allow stories to be created around them. It will
                    also explore issues of training, also a key to the development of the
                    infrastructure, as the requirements for creating 3D DSEs, conceptually,
                    methodologically, and technically, are quite different from what we have been
                    training for over the past 20+ years for more traditional text-based editions. </p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Paper 1: What is a 3D Digital Scholarly Edition?</hi><lb/></p>
                <p>Susan Schreibman, Maastricht University </p>
                <p>In 2016 Patrick Sahle advocated that Scholarly Digital Editions not be restricted
                    to literary texts but rather ‘cover all cultural artefacts from the past that
                    need critical examination in order to become useful sources for research in the
                    humanities’ (Sahle 2016, 22). </p>
                <p>Thus the goal of these editions is to move beyond how we typically interact with
                    3D models (for example on Sketchfab or via museum databases) as ‘twirly
                    objects’, albeit with metadata, to models that exist within a knowledge site,
                    e.g., a Digital Scholarly Edition; what Derrida (Derrida and Prenowitz 1995, 10)
                    and the earliest textual editors of web-based scholarship called the archive,
                    what Deleuze and Guattari (1987, 4) called an assemblage, in which the textual
                    and contextual are interwoven within the same viewing environment  (Gabler 2010,
                    46) thus providing an environment for the communication of 3D scholarship to
                    enjoy the same intellectual rigour as more traditional editions based on primary
                    text-sources. </p>
                <p>Several virtual world projects have followed the paradigm of what we call 3D
                    Scholarly Editions, providing contextual information, in the form of in-world
                    textual and multimedia annotations, including VSim (Snyder 2014, Sullivan and
                    Snyder 2017), the <ref target="http://idialab.org/virtual-middletown-living-museum-in-blue-mars/">Virtual Middletown Living Museum Project</ref> and <ref target="http://vcg.isti.cnr.it/cross/">The Visionary Cross Project</ref>.
                    This paper will explore issues surrounding the creation and the sustainability
                    of 3D scholarly editions, and hence the inspiration to create an infrastructure
                    to lessen the burden (economically and intellectually) for editors wishing to
                    create and sustain such scholarship.  </p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Paper 2: Building an Infrastructure for 3D Scholarship</hi><lb/></p>
                <p>Costas Papadopoulos, Maastricht University </p>
                <p>PURE3D, an infrastructure for the publication and preservation of 3D scholarship,
                    funded by Platform Digitale Infrastructuur - Social Sciences &amp; Humanities,
                    is establishing a framework in which 3D scholarship and heritage will be
                    published and preserved in the form of 3D Scholarly Editions (3DSEs) (Schreibman
                    and Papadopoulos, 2019; Papadopoulos and Schreibman, 2019). At the same time,
                    emphasis is placed on the preservation not only of the 3D models, but of all of
                    its associated information (e.g., annotations, apparatus etc.) following the
                    FAIR principles. PURE3D is also developing models for the evaluation of 3D
                    scholarship, aligning with the recent Declaration on Research Assessment (DORA)
                    and <ref target="https://coara.eu/app/uploads/2022/09/2022_07_19_rra_agreement_final.pdf">The EU Agreement on Reforming Research Assessment</ref>.  </p>
                <p>The development of the PURE3D infrastructure is informed by six pilot partners,
                    representing both academic researchers and heritage institutions, providing a
                    range of 3D models from a collection of individual objects to more complex
                    cityscapes. Following an iterative design thinking methodology, development is
                    informed by workshops, focus groups, and training, which in turn, informs the
                    conceptualisation and creation of 3D narratives. The goal of PURE3D is not to
                    reinvent the wheel, but draw from successful attempts in infrastructure
                    development, such as collaborating with The Smithsonian by implementing Voyager
                    Story and Voyager Explorer as one of the 3D editing and viewing environments.
                    This collaboration has also served to inform development of Voyager while
                    expanding its community of practice. This paper will reflect on the
                    collaborative process of development and will address opportunities and
                    challenges.   </p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Paper 3: At the Front End: The Smithsonian Voyager - Crafting
                        Engaging Digital Experiences</hi><lb/></p>
                <p>Jamie Cope, Smithsonian Institution</p>
                <p>Jon Blundell, Smithsonian Institution </p>
                <p>Cultural heritage objects are rarely presented in a vacuum. In a physical museum
                    great care is taken to display, provide context, and guide visitors through an
                    educational experience. Online 3D viewing experiences should not be different: 
                    to provide a meaningful and memorable virtual visit, construction of narratives
                    to provide users with multimodal contextualisation, interactivity, and affective
                    experiences is equally important. To this end, The Smithsonian developed the
                    Voyager suite of web components that provide authors and viewers of 3D
                    narratives with the functionalities to develop and consume such experiences.
                    Voyager is divided into two main components: Story, the content authoring
                    interface and Explorer, the user-facing interface, which can support augmented
                    reality viewing on compatible mobile devices. Voyager story enables users,
                    including curators and content experts, to author 3D narratives by means of: 1)
                    Annotation; 2) Articles; and, 3) Guided Tours.</p>
                <p>In developing PURE3D, Voyager is one of the authoring/viewing components for
                    developing 3D scholarly editions. Through this collaboration, Voyager had the
                    opportunity to reflect not only on storytelling features but also on the kinds
                    of audiences that could benefit from the platform as PURE3D works with a wide
                    variety of stakeholders, not only museum curators - which have been the primary
                    audience for Voyager Story, but also researchers, including architectural
                    historians, archaeologists, art historians, and 3D modellers. This paper will
                    present the narrative affordances of the Voyager suite and will reflect on the
                    lessons learnt from the collaboration with multiple and diverse stakeholders and
                    the PURE3D infrastructure.   </p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Paper 4: Training the Community: Theoretical &amp;
                        Methodological Considerations</hi><lb/></p>
                <p>Kelly Gillikin-Schoueri, Maastricht University <lb/></p>
                <p>Even if an environment is developed in which
                    researchers, curators, and archivists can create 3DSEs, the conceptual
                    underpinning of these editions is extremely different from other forms of
                    knowledge creation, including creating metadata for 3D models (eg as part of an
                    institutional database) to XML-based DSEs. Therefore, training is an integral
                    part of the 3D infrastructure so that editors can curate annotations and
                    apparatus in ways that directly interact with the 3D model. Thus, as part of the
                    PURE3D project activities, a series of iterative training modules for various
                    stakeholder groups (including bachelor’s students, public-sector heritage
                    professionals and academics) have been developed utilising Smithsonian’s Voyager
                    with a two-fold objective:</p>
                <p>1. To conceptualise 3D scholarly editions as a novel form of scholarly
                    communication;</p>
                <p>2. To teach competency in developing a 3D scholarly edition within Voyager
                    Story.</p>
                <p>The training materials have been developed through an interactive and
                    collaborative design cycle. Learning how to use the software has been relatively
                    easy to teach. But even for those who have a background in more traditional
                    text-based editing, what has proved challenging is a change in mindset as to how
                    to edit an edition in which the ‘textual’ centre is a 3D model which
                    necessitates an annotative focus on place-based location originating from the
                    physicality of the model. This paper will explore these challenges, as well as
                    the solutions now part of the suite of training materials used, as well as
                    future plans for making these materials publicly accessible. </p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Paper 5: The First Editions: Crafting Engaging Digital
                        Experiences </hi><lb/></p>
                <p> Jun Ogawa, University of Tokyo </p>
                <p>Kiyonori Nagasaki, University of Tokyo</p>
                <p>Susan Schreibman, Maastricht University </p>
                <p>This paper focuses on the intellectual, conceptual, and methodological decisions
                    to be considered in constructing a 3D DSE. At present, there are some 20
                    editions within the PURE3D infrastructure using models as different as Buddhist
                    statues, the Roman Imperial Fora, a battlefield in Dublin from the Easter 1916
                    Rising, a musical instrument called the Hurdy Gurdy, a Benin Bronze, a coal
                    mining lamp, and a modern statue, and buildings from 18th century Netherlands,
                    among others. </p>
                <p>Despite the fact that these objects are so different in the physical world,
                    within the context of the editing environment, in this case Smithsonian Voyager,
                    they share common issues in narrating and annotating to create scaffolding
                    around the 3D model appropriate to the audience the editor is targeting. As the
                    3D model maintains a central role in the edition, the narrative must begin and
                    end with the spatiality of the object being annotated. This means that all the
                    data included in the edition, even what we might consider background knowledge,
                    needs, somehow, to be connected to a specific location on the model, in addition
                    to issues present in more traditional editions, including what is selected for
                    annotation and how it is communicated. 　</p>
                <p>3D DSEs have the potential to open up spatial and temporal opportunities for new
                    forms of scholarly communication foregrounding the material and sensorial within
                    a 3D environment. These prototype editions have much to teach us about the
                    opportunities for this exciting new form of scholarship, geared to a wide
                    variety of audiences.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliogr">
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Apollon, D., Bélisle, C., &amp; Régnier, P.</author> (2014). 
                        <hi rend="italic">Digital critical edition</hi>
                        s. Urbana: University of Illinois Press.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Deleuze, G., &amp; Guattari, F.</author> (1987). 
                        <hi rend="italic">A thousand plateaus: Capitalism and
                            schizophrenia</hi>
                        . London: University of Minnesota Press.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Derrida, J. &amp; Prenowitz, E.</author> (1995). Archive fever: A Freudian impression. 
                        <hi rend="italic">Diacritics</hi>
                         25(2), 9–63. 
                        <ref target="http://www.jstor.org/stable/465144">http://www.jstor.org/stable/465144</ref>
                           
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Driscoll, M., &amp; Pierazzo, E.</author> (2016). 
                        <hi rend="italic">Digital scholarly editing: Theories
                            and practices</hi>
                        . Cambridge: Open Book Publishers.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Gabler, H.W.</author> (2010). Theorizing the digital scholarly edition. 
                        <hi rend="italic">Literature Compass</hi>
                        , 7, pp. 43–56. 
                        <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1741-4113.2009.00675.x">https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1741-4113.2009.00675.x</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>McKenzie, D. F.</author> (1999). 
                        <hi rend="italic">Bibliography and the sociology of
                            texts</hi>
                        . Cambridge: Cambridge University Press.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Papadopoulos, C. and Schreibman, S.</author> (2019). Towards 3D Scholarly Editions: The Battle of Mount Street Bridge. 
                        <hi rend="italic">Digital Humanities Quarterly</hi>
                        . 13(1). 
                        <ref target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/13/1/000415/000415.html">http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/13/1/000415/000415.html</ref>
                         
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Pierazzo, E.</author> (2015). 
                        <hi rend="italic">Digital scholarly editing:
                            Theories, models and methods</hi>
                        . New York: Ashgate.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Sahle, P.</author> (2016). What is a scholarly digital edition. In M. Driscoll &amp; E. Pierazzo (Eds), 
                        <hi rend="italic">Digital scholarly editing: Theories
                            and practices</hi>
                         (pp. 20–39). Cambridge: Open Book Publishers.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Schreibman, S., Papadopoulos, C.</author> (2019) Textuality in 3D: three-dimensional (re)constructions as digital scholarly editions. 
                        <hi rend="italic">International Journal of Digital
                            Humanities</hi>
                        , 1, 221–233. 
                        <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1007/s42803-019-00024-6">https://doi.org/10.1007/s42803-019-00024-6</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Snyder, L. M.</author> (2014). VSim: Scholarly Annotations in Real-Time 3D Environments. In P. Schmitz, L. Pearce, and Q. Dombrowski (Eds) 
                        <hi rend="italic">DH-CASE II: Collaborative
                            Annotations on Shared Environments: Metadata, Tools and Techniques in
                            the Digital Humanities (DH-CASE 2014)</hi>
                        , ACM, New York, NY, USA, Article 2, 8 pages. 
                        <ref target="http://dx.doi.org/10.1145/2657480.2657483">http://dx.doi.org/10.1145/2657480.2657483</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Sullivan, E. A., and Snyder, L.M.</author> (2017). Digital Karnak: An Experiment in Publication and Peer Review of Interactive, Three-Dimensional Content. 
                        <hi rend="italic">Journal of the Society of
                            Architectural Historians</hi>
                         76(4), 464-482.
                        <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1525/jsah.2017.76.4.464">https://doi.org/10.1525/jsah.2017.76.4.464</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Sutherland, K.</author> (1997). <hi rend="italic">Electronic text:
                            Investigations in method and theory</hi>. Oxford: Clarendon Press.
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text></TEI>