<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_allPlus.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_allPlus.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>DH4MA - (Digital Humanities for Marginal Areas). Tangible and
                        Intangible heritage digitalization to promote marginal areas and rural
                        development</title>
                <author n="PascucciAntonioPASCUCCI_Antonio_DH4MA____Digital_Humanities_for_Marginal_Ar.xml"><persName n="PascucciAntonio">
                        <surname>Pascucci</surname>
                        <forename>Antonio</forename>
                    </persName><affiliation>L'Orientale University of Naples, Italy</affiliation><email>antoniopascucci1990@gmail.com</email></author><meeting><date from-iso="2023-07-10" to-iso="2023-07-14"/><title>Digital Humanities 2023. Collaboration as Opportunity</title><placeName>Graz</placeName></meeting>
                <author n="CarlinoCarolaPASCUCCI_Antonio_DH4MA____Digital_Humanities_for_Marginal_Ar.xml"><persName n="CarlinoCarola">
                        <surname>Carlino</surname>
                        <forename>Carola</forename>
                    </persName><affiliation>L'Orientale University of Naples, Italy</affiliation><email>carlinocarola4@gmail.com</email></author><meeting><date from-iso="2023-07-10" to-iso="2023-07-14"/><title>Digital Humanities 2023. Collaboration as Opportunity</title><placeName>Graz</placeName></meeting>
                <author n="MontiJohannaPASCUCCI_Antonio_DH4MA____Digital_Humanities_for_Marginal_Ar.xml"><persName n="MontiJohanna">
                        <surname>Monti</surname>
                        <forename>Johanna</forename>
                    </persName><affiliation>L'Orientale University of Naples, Italy</affiliation><email>jmonti@unior.it</email></author><meeting><date from-iso="2023-07-10" to-iso="2023-07-14"/><title>Digital Humanities 2023. Collaboration as Opportunity</title><placeName>Graz</placeName></meeting>
                <author n="MannaRaffaelePASCUCCI_Antonio_DH4MA____Digital_Humanities_for_Marginal_Ar.xml"><persName n="MannaRaffaele">
                        <surname>Manna</surname>
                        <forename>Raffaele</forename>
                    </persName><affiliation>L'Orientale University of Naples, Italy</affiliation><email>raffaele.mann@gmail.com</email></author><meeting><date from-iso="2023-07-10" to-iso="2023-07-14"/><title>Digital Humanities 2023. Collaboration as Opportunity</title><placeName>Graz</placeName></meeting>
            </titleStmt>
            
            <publicationStmt><publisher><orgName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1137284463">Zentrum für Informationsmodellierung
                    - Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities, Karl-Franzens-Universität
                    Graz</orgName></publisher><date when="2023">2023</date><pubPlace>Graz</pubPlace><availability><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">Creative Commons BY
                    4.0</licence></availability></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title>Digital Humanities 2023: Book of Abstracts</title><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-9256-0958"><forename>Walter</forename><surname>Scholger</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>University of Graz</orgName><placeName>Graz, Austria</placeName></affiliation><email>walter.scholger@uni-graz.at</email></editor><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-1726-1712"><forename>Georg</forename><surname>Vogeler</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>University of Graz</orgName><placeName>Graz, Austria</placeName></affiliation><email>georg.vogeler@uni-graz.at</email></editor><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-3919-993X"><forename>Toma</forename><surname>Tasovac</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>Belgrade Center for Digital Humanities</orgName><placeName>Belgrade, Serbia</placeName></affiliation><email>ttasovac@humanistika.org</email></editor><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-4593-059X"><forename>Anne</forename><surname>Baillot</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>Le Mans Université</orgName><placeName>Le Mans, France</placeName></affiliation><email>anne.baillot@univ-lemans.fr</email></editor><respStmt><resp>Data Management</resp><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0009-0007-9019-8215"><forename>Elisabeth</forename><surname>Raunig</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Management</resp><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-1438-3236"><forename>Martina</forename><surname>Scholger</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Management</resp><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-9116-0402"><forename>Elisabeth</forename><surname>Steiner</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Curation</resp><persName><forename>Johanna</forename><surname>Ofenauer</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Curation</resp><persName><forename>Christina</forename><surname>Burgstaller</surname></persName></respStmt><idno type="DOI">10.5281/zenodo.7961822</idno></seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from an OASIS Open Document</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="DHCONVALIDATOR" version="1.22">
                    <label>DHConvalidator</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc><abstract><p>The Digital Humanities for Marginal Areas (DH4MA) workshop aims to investigate the state of the art of tangible and intangible heritage digitalization in marginal and rural areas and their accessibility.</p></abstract><langUsage><language ident="en">English</language></langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="category">
                    <term>Paper</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="subcategory">
                    <term>Pre-Conference Workshop and Tutorial</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="keywords">
                    <term>marginal areas</term>
                    <term>rural areas</term>
                    <term>digital humanities</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="topics">
                    <term>digital biography</term>
                    <term>personography</term>
                    <term>and prosopography</term>
                    <term>digitization (2D &amp; 3D)</term>
                    <term>media archaeology</term>
                    <term>virtual and augmented reality creation</term>
                    <term>systems</term>
                    <term>and analysis</term>
                    <term>Archaeology</term>
                    <term>Art history</term>
                    <term>Games studies</term>
                    <term>Humanities computing</term>
                    
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>The first edition of the Digital Humanities for Marginal Areas (DH4MA) workshop
                    aims to investigate the state of the art of tangible and intangible heritage
                    digitization in marginal and rural areas and their accessibility. DH4MA will be
                    held in conjunction with the DH2023 conference and is organized in the framework
                    of the KiNESIS Erasmus+ project. The KiNESIS (KNowledgE alliance for Social
                    Innovation in Shrinking villages) project is a three-year initiative (2021-2023,
                    extended to June 2024) co-funded by the European Union's Erasmus+ Programme. Its
                    primary objective is to establish a Knowledge Alliance among academia, NGOs,
                    communities, local authorities, and businesses to develop a program of
                    multidisciplinary activities in shrinking areas that promotes and fosters
                    entrepreneurship, projects, workforce, productivity, and attractiveness. The
                    KiNESIS project's aims are: revitalizing depopulated areas, creating local
                    living laboratories for exchanging knowledge and experiences, experimenting with
                    innovative approaches in teaching and learning, and facilitating the flow of
                    knowledge at local and global levels. One of the most important initiatives
                    promoted by the KiNESIS project was the Wiki Loves Monuments Terre dell’Ufita,
                    developed within the International photografic competition Wiki Loves Monuments1
                    (WLM). The aim of WLM is to highlight the heritage sites of the participating
                    countries to encourage people to capture pictures of these monuments, and to put
                    them under a free licence on Wikimedia Commons. The Ufita Valley edition made it
                    possible to collect 73 photos of monuments in the geographical area of interest,
                    thus fostering a spread of knowledge about them and a more shared use of digital
                    technologies, in an area where to be considered sensitive issues are both the
                    depopulation of rural areas, but also the difficulty caused by the digital
                    divide. Thanks to the cooperation between the KiNESIS project, Wikimedia Italia
                    and Terre dell’Ufita NGOs, local communities and students have acquired
                    knowledge in creating open contents online in order to disseminate local history
                    and cultural heritage2, trying to reduce the digital gap.</p>
                <p>The digital divide issue affects several areas all over the world, including
                    those that despite being part of the most developed countries, are behind the
                    times of the digital revolution. In light of the above, Digital Humanities (DH)
                    techniques represent an opportunity not to be missed to raise awareness about
                    cultural heritage and to overcome the digital divide.</p>
                <p>This topic was investigated through the various contributions that were received,
                    in the form of extended abstracts (500 words max.), from authors with different
                    research centres, scattered around the world.</p>
                <p>The field of digital history and heritage is rapidly evolving, paving the way for
                    new methods of preserving, documenting, and promoting cultural heritage.
                    Although there is a lack of research on using digital tools to preserve Cultural
                    Natural Heritage (CNH) in composite rural areas, as digital technologies
                    continue to advance, there is growing recognition of their potential to bridge
                    the divide and promote CNH-led strategies for remote and rural regions. The
                    study proposed by Farzaneh Aliakbari and Rosa Tamborrino from the
                    Interuniversity Department of Regional and Urban Studies and Planning of the
                    Politecnico di Torino (Italy), entitled Review mapping of digital tools and
                    applications in Cultural Natural heritage landscapes, aims to provide a
                    comprehensive overview of the digital tools and applications used in CNH sites,
                    as well as identifying existing digital gaps and potential future paths in
                    digitalization of CNH landscapes. The study will contribute to the promotion of
                    digital heritage-led strategies for rural and remote areas by providing insights
                    into preserving tangible and intangible heritage values.</p>
                <p>One of the key challenges in the digitization of cultural heritage is the lack of
                    research and resources available in certain regions. In order to fill this gap,
                    Serena Autiero, Frederik Elwert, Cristiano Moscatelli, Jessie Pons, from the
                    Center for Religious Studies, proposed the digitization of Buddhist heritage in
                    the Mountain Valleys of Khyber Pakhtunkhwa (Pakistan). As explained in their
                    proposal Digitization of Buddhist Heritage in the Mountain Valleys of Khyber
                    Pakhtunkhwa (Pakistan): results and perspectives, the BMBF-funded eHeritage
                    project (2021-2024) Digitization of Gandharan Artefacts (DiGA) is working to
                    digitise almost 2,000 Buddhist sculptures from the historical region of Gandhara
                    in Pakistan. By making these sculptures accessible, the project offers new
                    avenues for research on Gandharan styles, Buddhist iconographies, and the
                    interplay between literary and visual documents. Additionally, the project
                    creates bridges between traditional research and the Digital Humanities,
                    digitised collections and other projects, and European research landscape and
                    cultural heritage institutions in Khyber Pakhtunkhwa.</p>
                <p>About the Italian scenario, Vincenzo Colaprice from the University of Bari “Aldo
                    Moro”, proposes the creation of a digital atlas (A digital Atlas for Italian
                    “borghi”) to present the specificities of each territory through various
                    indicators. The author reflects on the fact that the Italian National Recovery
                    and Resilience Plan (PNRR) provides strategic interventions for villages (cfr.
                    ‘borghi’) in marginal areas, but not for many other smaller centres. The aim of
                    this innovative atlas is to offer useful data and information to multiple
                    communities of users and support public institutions in defining policies that
                    might activate the regeneration processes of villages in marginal areas. By
                    integrating qualitative and quantitative data, this atlas provides an organised
                    and easily usable ecosystem.</p>
                <p>The archaeological map of the upper Tammaro valley as a tool for governance and
                    planning of the cultural heritage of a marginalized rural area. (Benevento,
                    Campania region, Italy) is the title of a study focused on the rural landscape
                    of the upper valley of the Tammaro river in Campania, Italy, from the IV BC to
                    the VI AD century. The author, Oriana Cerbone, from the University of Salerno
                    (Italy), reflects on the importance of giving uniformity to the archaeological
                    data available while considering the environmental and human factors that
                    influenced the landscape's development. The methodology involves creating an
                    archaeological territorial information system and implementing it through
                    mapping tools. The results of this study can be used to protect cultural
                    heritage, support sustainable rural development, and encourage active
                    citizenship and local tourism.</p>
                <p>Another area where digital technologies are making an impact is in the study of
                    medieval Hebrew manuscripts, as demonstrated by Gila Prebor, from the Bar-Ilan
                    University (Israel). Using Machine Learning-Based Methods to Forecast the
                    Production-Date of Hebrew Medieval Manuscripts is the title of the proposal in
                    which the author describes the development of a reliable and efficient method
                    for dating ancient manuscripts. This development will enable a broader audience
                    of researchers to date manuscripts without the need for extensive codicological
                    knowledge, enriching the understanding of mediaeval Hebrew manuscripts and their
                    historical context. Furthermore, the understanding of the impact of different
                    data on the dating of manuscripts can aid in the identification of trends and
                    developments in the production of Hebrew manuscripts throughout the years. </p>
                <p>However, the use of digital tools and applications in preserving cultural
                    heritage is not without challenges. The paper The Rhetoric Gaze of Mehrangarh
                    Fort by Sayan Sanyal, from the IDRP, IIT Jodhpur (India), highlights the complex
                    relationship between art, architecture, and culture, and how they shape our
                    perceptions of the world. Using the Mehrangarh Fort as an example, the paper
                    explores how images and cultural heritage have been perceived and represented
                    over time. It emphasises the importance of adopting a critical and nuanced
                    perspective when analysing cultural heritage and using digital technologies to
                    study it. By doing so, we can gain a deeper understanding of the past, present,
                    and future of cultural heritage and promote its preservation for future
                    generations. </p>
                <p>According to Olga Terenstka (Europeana Foundation), the digitization of cultural
                    heritage offers new opportunities for a better understanding of the cultural
                    past, raises awareness about cultural heritage, and promotes its preservation
                    for future generations. The author, with the contribution entitled
                    Instrumentalization of culture in politics, fake cultural narratives, war
                    crimes, Ukraine, proposes to increase the voice of the digital cultural heritage
                    of Ukraine abroad and overcome the digital divide created by insufficient effort
                    aimed at educating EU people regarding Ukrainian cultural history topics in a
                    non-censored way. Through the collection of several projects focused on the
                    digitization of Ukrainian tangible and intangible heritage, the author offers an
                    elaboration of best practices of collaboration between people/teams with
                    different backgrounds across the EU.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>The DH4MA workshop was organized by</head>
                <p>- Johanna Monti, full Professor at the University of Naples "L'Orientale" (Italy)
                    (SSD L-LIN/02), where she is the head of the UNIOR NLP Research Group of the
                    Department of Literary, Linguistic and Comparative Studies, active in the field
                    of Computational Linguistics and Automatic Natural Language Processing (NLP) and
                    local node of the National Laboratory of Artificial Intelligence and Intelligent
                    Systems of CINI. She is also the Third Mission delegate at the same University
                    and is responsible for national and international research projects in the field
                    of NLP. </p>
                <p>- Antonio Pascucci, PhD in Literary, Linguistic and Comparative Studies at the
                    L'Orientale University of Naples with a thesis titled Does style characterize
                    haters? An investigation on an Italian hate speech corpus. His research
                    interests focus on Computational Stylometry and Forensic Linguistics. His other
                    interests include tourist promotion of internal areas and finding solutions to
                    develop rural areas. He is involved in the Erasmus+ KiNESIS project, which
                    focuses on creating connections among research institutes and businesses to
                    fight the phenomenon of depopulation;</p>
                <p>- Carola Carlino, PhD in Literary, Linguistic and Comparative Studies at the
                    L’Orientale University of Naples with a thesis titled Musei Liquidi. Digital
                    Storytelling, Social Media, Multilinguismo. Her research interests focus on
                    Cultural Heritage Digitization processes and Communicative strategies by
                    Cultural Institutions.</p>
                <p>- Raffaele Manna is a PhD candidate in Natural Language Processing at the UniOR
                    NLP Research Group. His research interests concern computational stylometry and
                    computational methods for emotion recognition from texts.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Program Committee</head>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Elisa Bonacini</hi>, University of Bari </p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Ruth Breeze</hi>, University of Navarra </p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Andrea D'Andrea</hi>, L'Orientale University of Naples </p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Stefania De Vincentis</hi>, University of Venice Ca' Foscari </p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Alba Irollo</hi>, Europeana </p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Marianna Marcucci</hi>, Invasioni digitali </p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Alfonso Santoriello</hi>, University of Salerno </p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Ludovico Solima</hi>, University of Campania Luigi Vanvitelli </p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Michele Domenico Todino</hi>, University of Salerno </p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Chiara Zuanni</hi>, University of Graz </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text></TEI>