<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_allPlus.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_allPlus.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title> Becoming the digital humanities as discourse(s) of subjectivation </title>
                <author n="PetzCindarellaPETZ_Cindarella__Becoming_the_digital_humanities_as_discours.xml"><persName n="PetzCindarella">
                        <surname>Petz</surname>
                        <forename>Cindarella</forename>
                    </persName><affiliation>Leibniz Institute of European History Mainz (IEG),
                        Germany</affiliation><email>petz@ieg-mainz.de</email></author><meeting><date from-iso="2023-07-10" to-iso="2023-07-14"/><title>Digital Humanities 2023. Collaboration as Opportunity</title><placeName>Graz</placeName></meeting>
            </titleStmt>
            
            <publicationStmt><publisher><orgName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1137284463">Zentrum für Informationsmodellierung
                    - Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities, Karl-Franzens-Universität
                    Graz</orgName></publisher><date when="2023">2023</date><pubPlace>Graz</pubPlace><availability><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">Creative Commons BY
                    4.0</licence></availability></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title>Digital Humanities 2023: Book of Abstracts</title><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-9256-0958"><forename>Walter</forename><surname>Scholger</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>University of Graz</orgName><placeName>Graz, Austria</placeName></affiliation><email>walter.scholger@uni-graz.at</email></editor><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-1726-1712"><forename>Georg</forename><surname>Vogeler</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>University of Graz</orgName><placeName>Graz, Austria</placeName></affiliation><email>georg.vogeler@uni-graz.at</email></editor><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-3919-993X"><forename>Toma</forename><surname>Tasovac</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>Belgrade Center for Digital Humanities</orgName><placeName>Belgrade, Serbia</placeName></affiliation><email>ttasovac@humanistika.org</email></editor><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-4593-059X"><forename>Anne</forename><surname>Baillot</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>Le Mans Université</orgName><placeName>Le Mans, France</placeName></affiliation><email>anne.baillot@univ-lemans.fr</email></editor><respStmt><resp>Data Management</resp><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0009-0007-9019-8215"><forename>Elisabeth</forename><surname>Raunig</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Management</resp><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-1438-3236"><forename>Martina</forename><surname>Scholger</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Management</resp><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-9116-0402"><forename>Elisabeth</forename><surname>Steiner</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Curation</resp><persName><forename>Johanna</forename><surname>Ofenauer</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Curation</resp><persName><forename>Christina</forename><surname>Burgstaller</surname></persName></respStmt><idno type="DOI">10.5281/zenodo.7961822</idno></seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="DHCONVALIDATOR" version="1.22">
                    <label>DHConvalidator</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc><abstract><p>This contribution argues to describe the discussions within the digital humanities (DH) discipline as a subjectivation discourse following the contention of Michel Foucault. This allows us to reframe the negotiation processes within the DH as a means to formally establish its disciplinary in/dependence, and as such provides and creates agency for the subjects of the discourse(s).</p></abstract><langUsage><language ident="en">English</language></langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="category">
                    <term>Paper</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="subcategory">
                    <term>Long Presentation</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="keywords">
                    <term>DH historiography</term>
                    <term>meta reflections</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="topics">
                    <term>meta-criticism (reflections on digital humanities and humanities
                        computing)</term>
                    <term>History</term>
                    <term>Humanities computing</term>
                    <term>Sociology</term>
                    
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <p>The digital humanities (DH) since their nominal conception in the early 2000s <ref target="#PETZ_Cindarella__Becoming_the_digital_humanities_as_discours.xml_ftn1" n="1"/> can be characterized by their near-constant discussion of what the DH are
                    <ref target="#PETZ_Cindarella__Becoming_the_digital_humanities_as_discours.xml_ftn2" n="2"/>, what they can be, and to which extent. <ref target="#PETZ_Cindarella__Becoming_the_digital_humanities_as_discours.xml_ftn3" n="3"/> This discussion revolves around the struggle to find a common definition and
                purpose of what has been described at the same time as a field encompassing
                heterogenous humanities’ fields (DH as an “umbrella term”, e.g., Terras 2011;
                Kirschenbaum 2012), a sub-discipline of their respective mother fields, a
                meta-discipline (e.g., König 2021), a toolbox of methodologies (e.g., Jannidis et
                al. 2017), or a workflow even (such as of a digitization process). <ref target="#PETZ_Cindarella__Becoming_the_digital_humanities_as_discours.xml_ftn4" n="4"/></p>
            <p>This contribution argues to reframe these negotiation processes of external and
                intra-community discussions of the DH – concerning what belongs (not) to the DH, the
                negotiation of their framework(s), modes of operation, and place within/outside the
                established disciplines (including the im/permanence of their institutions, be it
                physical centers or immaterial working groups) — as a subjectivation discourse
                following the conception of Michel Foucault. <ref target="#PETZ_Cindarella__Becoming_the_digital_humanities_as_discours.xml_ftn5" n="5"/></p>
            <div>
                <head>The Foucauldian subject </head>
                <p>Foucault’s concept of subjectivation describes the process of (re)forming an
                    individual to a subject: this subject is created by power relations, and in turn
                    is able to create its own power relations (compare to e.g., Foucault 1987;
                    Vogelmann 2017, p. 11). However, this doesn’t produce an “anthropological
                    constant” (Schrage 2008, p. 4125): the relational power dependencies of subjects
                    are influenced by their socio-historical context(s) as the “realm of
                    potentiality of its existence” (Campos 2015, p. 113). As such, the subject
                    itself is subjected to change within a discourse. </p>
                <p>Foucault ([1969] 1973) interpreted the participation in discourses and their
                    relational power dependencies as “practices of subjectivation” (“ <hi rend="italic">Praxis der Subjektivierung</hi>”). The participation of
                    individuals in discourses revolve around power (i.e., the individual shapes what
                    is acceptable content in negotiation processes in the discourse) and position
                    (i.e., the individual positions themselves into/against the group of dis-
                    course), which allows for a means of agency of the individual (compare, e.g., to
                    Wiede 2020). Foucault regarded the membership in these discourses as a form of
                    reduction of complexity: the participation practices are based on time-dependent
                    epistles (the so-called “truths,” which are subject to change over time), which
                    are part of the socio-historical context(s), and are structured by a distinct
                    set of rules (practices called “technologies of self”). These set the possible
                    range of behavior in the discourse, and thus provide finite limits to complex
                    interactions, thereby reducing complexity. <ref target="#PETZ_Cindarella__Becoming_the_digital_humanities_as_discours.xml_ftn6" n="6"/> These practices are subject to constant calibration in the discourse
                    community, and hence change. The discourse emerges out of the practices of
                    subjectivation of individuals, which at the same time are influenced by the
                    practices already existing within the discourse in an iterative, cyclical
                    process. In his later work, Foucault differentiated more between the possible
                    degrees of surrender of the subject to the discourse, taking into account more
                    variation of behavior. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Subjectivation discourse(s) of the DH </head>
                <p>This contribution argues that many discussions in the DH can be characterized as
                    such discourse(s) of subjectivation – based on a meta-study of the discussions
                    on their definition – in order to become a subject in the Foucauldian sense and
                    to establish a means of agency. This process thus enables the DH to become an
                    independent field, of which individuals position themselves to be a/part of.
                    These specific practices of subjectivation of individuals in this discourse
                    would then involve for example, publishing in specific DH journals,
                    participating in discussions about DH, or declaring to be a ‘digital humanist’
                    in the DH community, through which the individual researcher becomes part of the
                    DH discourse(s). They therefore subject themselves to a particular set of rules,
                    the “technologies of self”: practices that are considered to belong to the DH,
                    such as DH-specific requirements for good scientific practice (e.g., method
                    criticism, algorithmic criticism, FAIR data principles), or certain research
                    behaviors, such as collaborative work or experimentation as ‘ideal’ ways of
                    working. </p>
                <p>The socio-historical context(s) of the subjectivation discourses of the DH can be
                    seen as the ongoing digitalization of society and of the sciences, and the shift
                    in focus to their potential for research. It can be argued that the DH emerged
                    as an ‘update’ of what was previously known as ‘humanities computing,’ against a
                    backdrop of much easier access to technical infrastructure and resources, such
                    as the internet, and the spread of computers. The digitalization can be framed
                    as a regulative normalization through which entities are transformed into
                    subjects (compare to Foucault 1999; Schrage 2008, p. 4125). </p>
                <p>Foucault pointed to the changing epistles in the discourses, which are evident as
                    well in the discourses of DH. So far, no unified answer – or singular practice
                    in the Foucauldian sense – has been found in the last decades that would yet
                    remain uncontested, e.g., as to how the DH can be defined. Instead, they are
                    subjected to a high degree of change, following the Foucauldian idea of the
                    constant calibration of practices in negotiation processes within the
                    subjectivation discourses. These can be framed as permanent self-assurance and
                    self-actualization of the values, goals, and nature of the DH themselves, and as
                    form part of the subjectivation of the DH, and their members within. </p>
                <p>This contribution argues that discussions of the nature and place of the DH act
                    as a means of formally establishing the disciplinary in/dependence of the DH,
                    and as such provide and create agency for the subjects of the discourse(s). </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Outlook</head>
                <p>Also part of these discussions is the question on the future of the DH in the
                    face of the problems of the contemporary world hat have gained traction in
                    recent years: raising questions of inclusion (e.g., postcolonial DH and the
                    exclusion of the Global South in the digitalization efforts of the last decades
                    of the ‘Global North’), representation (e.g., LGBTQ+ perspectives of a queer DH,
                    or absences in archives, a question becoming more urgent in the phase of eased
                    access to digital &amp; retro-digitized resources), and quests resulting from
                    climate change (e.g., green DH, and questions of sustainability of the
                    digitalization of the humanities). Even the theme of this DH 2023 conference on
                    the revolutionariness of the DH fits well with this development on the
                    “presentism” of the DH, when asking about the potential of DH to contribute to
                    current political events (questioning responsibility and privilege) and to
                    building a new future. This up-to-dateness can be seen as part of the DH’s
                    self-perception as modern and future oriented – or in other words, digital – and
                    as part of a self-actualization of the subjectivation discourse(s) in the DH.
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="notes"><note n="1" xml:id="PETZ_Cindarella__Becoming_the_digital_humanities_as_discours.xml_ftn1">
                    The first note of the term ’digital humanities’
                            is usually credited to Blackwell’s “A Companion to digital humanities”
                            edited by Schreibman et al., but it has been stressed that a seminar at
                            the University of Virginia’s English Department by Johanna Drucker and
                            John Unsworth already bore that name in 2001 (Drucker and Unsworth 2002;
                            compare to Allington et al. 2016; Crymble 2021, p. 29). The introduction
                            of the term ‘DH’ effectively renamed what has been previously known as
                            ’humanities and computing’ or ’computing in the humanities’, shifting
                            focus to the possibilities resulting from access to personal computers
                            and the internet, and the mass digitization projects of the turn of the
                            millennia.
                </note><note n="2" xml:id="PETZ_Cindarella__Becoming_the_digital_humanities_as_discours.xml_ftn2">
                    As exemplified by the “Day of Digital Humanities” Conference sport coming up with a new definition collected among its participants, or as in the consequent influx of digital humanities readers and introductory works, exemplarily here Schreibman et al. (2004), Terras (2011) or Sahle (2015). 
                </note><note n="3" xml:id="PETZ_Cindarella__Becoming_the_digital_humanities_as_discours.xml_ftn3">
                    Consequently, the Call of the DH Graz 2023 also fits this discourse on the future extent of the DH concerning their revolutionary power(s). 
                </note><note n="4" xml:id="PETZ_Cindarella__Becoming_the_digital_humanities_as_discours.xml_ftn4">
                    This overview remains necessarily uncomplete. For a more extensive discussion compare also to chapter 2 and 6 on defining and becoming the DH of Petz (2022). 
                </note><note n="5" xml:id="PETZ_Cindarella__Becoming_the_digital_humanities_as_discours.xml_ftn5">
                    The following draws in large parts of the chapter 6, esp. 6.1 in Petz (2022, pp. 163–4). 
                </note><note n="6" xml:id="PETZ_Cindarella__Becoming_the_digital_humanities_as_discours.xml_ftn6">
                        An illustrative example for the “technologies of self” would be practices that produce or restrict femininity in sports (Thorpe 2008). 
                    </note></div><div type="bibliogr">
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <bibl><author>Allington, Daniel, Brouilette, Sarah, and Columbia, David</author>. 2016.
                        “Neoliberal Tools (and Archives): A Political History of Digital
                        Humanities.” Los Angeles Review of Books (website).
                        https://lareviewofbooks.org/article/neoliberal-
                        tools-archives-political-history-digital-humanities/. </bibl>
                    <bibl><author>Campos, Samuel</author>. 2015. “Subjekte der Praxis – Praxis der Subjekte.
                        Subjektivierung als Perspektive musikpädagogischer Unterrichtsforschung,”
                        edited by Anne Niessen and Jens Knigge, 111–123. Musikpädagogische Forschung
                        36. Münster; New York: Waxmann. doi:10.25656/01:12617. </bibl>
                    <bibl><author>Crymble, Adam</author>. 2021. Technology and the Historian. Transformation in the
                        Digital Age. Urbana, Chicago, Springfield: University of Illinois Press. </bibl>
                    <bibl><author>Drucker, Johanna and Unsworth, John</author>. 2002. “Final Report for Digital
                        Humanities Curriculum Seminar.” IATH. The Institute for Advanced Technology
                        in the Humanities (website). http://www.iath.virginia.edu/hcs/dhcs/toc.html. </bibl>
                    <bibl><author>Foucault, Michel</author>. (1969) 1973. Archäologie des Wissens. FRENCH: ”L’ARCHE
                        <hi rend="superscript"> ́</hi>OLOGIE
                        DU SAVOIR”, GALLIMARD, PARIS. Frankfurt a. Main: Suhrkamp. </bibl>
                    <bibl><author>Foucault, Michel</author>. 1987. “Das Subjekt und die Macht.” Widerspruch: Beiträge
                        zu sozialistischer Politik 7 (14): 5–7. doi:10.5169/seals-652072. </bibl>
                    <bibl><author>Foucault, Michel</author>. 1999. In Verteidigung der Gesellschaft. Vorlesungen am
                        Collège de France (1975–1976). Frankfurt a. Main: Suhrkamp. </bibl>
                    <bibl><author>Jannidis, Fotis, Kohle, Hubertus, and Rehbein, Malte</author>, eds. 2017. Digital
                        Humanities: Eine Einführung. Stuttgart: J. B. Metzler. </bibl>
                    <bibl><author>Kirschenbaum, Matthew</author>. 2012. “Digital Humanities As/Is a Tactical Term.”
                        In Debates in the Digital Humanities 2012, edited by Mathew K. Gold.
                        Minneapolis London: University of Minnesota Press.
                        https://dhdebates.gc.cuny. edu / read / untitled - 88c11800 - 9446 - 469b -
                        a3be - 3fdb36bfbd1e / section / c0b0a8ee-95f0-4a9c-9451-e8ad168e3db5. </bibl>
                    <bibl><author>König, Mareike</author>. 2021. “Die Digitale Transformation als reflexiver turn.
                        Einführende Literatur zur digital Geschichte im Überblick.” Neue Politische
                        Literatur 66:37– 60. doi:10.1007/s42520-020-00322-2. </bibl>
                    <bibl><author>Petz, Cindarella</author>. 2022. “On Combining Network Research and Computational
                        Methods on Historical Research Questions and its Implications for the
                        Digital Humanities.” Dissertation, Technical University of Munich.
                        http://mediatum. ub.tum.de/node?id=1624881. </bibl>
                    <bibl><author>Sahle, Patrick</author>. 2015. “Digital Humanities? Gibt’s doch gar nicht!” In
                        Grenzen und Möglichkeiten der Digital Humanities, edited by Constanze Baum
                        and Thomas Stäcker. (= Sonderband der Zeitschrift für digitale
                        Geisteswissenschaften) PDF Format ohne Paginierung. doi:10.17175/sb001_004. </bibl>
                    <bibl><author>Schrage, Dominik</author>. 2008. “Subjektivierung durch Normalisierung: zur
                        Aktualisierung eines poststrukturalistischen Konzepts,” edited by
                        Kai-Siegbert Rehberg, 4120– 4129. Teilbd. 1 u. 2. Frankfurt a. Main: Campus
                        Verlag. https://nbn-resolv ing.org/urn:nbn:de:0168-ssoar-155104. </bibl>
                    <bibl><author>Schreibman, Susan, Siemens, Ray, and Unsworth, John</author>, eds. 2004. A
                        Companion to Digital Humanities. Oxford: Blackwell.
                        http://www.digitalhumanities. org/companion/. </bibl>
                    <bibl><author>Terras, Melissa</author>. 2011. “Peering Inside the Big Tent: Digital Humanities
                        and the Crisis of Inclusion.” Melissa Terras (blog).
                        http://melissaterras.blogspot.
                        com/2011/07/peering-inside-big-tent-digital.html. </bibl>
                    <bibl><author>Thorpe, Holly</author>. 2008. “Foucault, Technologies of Self, and the Media:
                        Discourses of Femininity in Snowboarding Culture.” Journal of Sport and
                        Social Issues 32 (2): 199–229. doi:10.1177/0193723508315206. </bibl>
                    <bibl><author>Vogelmann, Frieder</author>. 2017. Foucault lesen. Springer Essentials.</bibl>
                    <bibl><author>Wiede, Wiebke</author>. 2020. “Subject und Subjektivierung.” Version 3.0,
                        Docupedia-Zeitgeschichte (website). doi:10.14765/zzf.dok-2075. </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text></TEI>