<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_allPlus.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_allPlus.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Making Hobbes’s Bible in the English Political Works Machine-Readable: A
                    TXM-Based Workflow</title>
                <author n="RebastiFrancescaREBASTI_Francesca_Making_Hobbes_s_Bible_in_the_English_Polit.xml"><persName n="RebastiFrancesca">
                        <surname>Rebasti</surname>
                        <forename>Francesca</forename>
                    </persName><affiliation>IHRIM (UMR 5317) - ENS de Lyon, France</affiliation><email>francesca.rebasti@gmail.com</email></author><meeting><date from-iso="2023-07-10" to-iso="2023-07-14"/><title>Digital Humanities 2023. Collaboration as Opportunity</title><placeName>Graz</placeName></meeting>
                <author n="HeidenSergeREBASTI_Francesca_Making_Hobbes_s_Bible_in_the_English_Polit.xml"><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-4682-7647" n="HeidenSerge">
                        <surname>Heiden</surname>
                        <forename>Serge</forename>
                    </persName><affiliation>IHRIM (UMR 5317) - ENS de Lyon, France</affiliation><email>slh@ens-lyon.fr</email></author><meeting><date from-iso="2023-07-10" to-iso="2023-07-14"/><title>Digital Humanities 2023. Collaboration as Opportunity</title><placeName>Graz</placeName></meeting>
            </titleStmt>
            
            <publicationStmt><publisher><orgName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1137284463">Zentrum für Informationsmodellierung
                    - Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities, Karl-Franzens-Universität
                    Graz</orgName></publisher><date when="2023">2023</date><pubPlace>Graz</pubPlace><availability><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">Creative Commons BY
                    4.0</licence></availability></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title>Digital Humanities 2023: Book of Abstracts</title><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-9256-0958"><forename>Walter</forename><surname>Scholger</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>University of Graz</orgName><placeName>Graz, Austria</placeName></affiliation><email>walter.scholger@uni-graz.at</email></editor><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-1726-1712"><forename>Georg</forename><surname>Vogeler</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>University of Graz</orgName><placeName>Graz, Austria</placeName></affiliation><email>georg.vogeler@uni-graz.at</email></editor><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-3919-993X"><forename>Toma</forename><surname>Tasovac</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>Belgrade Center for Digital Humanities</orgName><placeName>Belgrade, Serbia</placeName></affiliation><email>ttasovac@humanistika.org</email></editor><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-4593-059X"><forename>Anne</forename><surname>Baillot</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>Le Mans Université</orgName><placeName>Le Mans, France</placeName></affiliation><email>anne.baillot@univ-lemans.fr</email></editor><respStmt><resp>Data Management</resp><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0009-0007-9019-8215"><forename>Elisabeth</forename><surname>Raunig</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Management</resp><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-1438-3236"><forename>Martina</forename><surname>Scholger</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Management</resp><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-9116-0402"><forename>Elisabeth</forename><surname>Steiner</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Curation</resp><persName><forename>Johanna</forename><surname>Ofenauer</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Curation</resp><persName><forename>Christina</forename><surname>Burgstaller</surname></persName></respStmt><idno type="DOI">10.5281/zenodo.7961822</idno></seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="DHCONVALIDATOR" version="1.22">
                    <label>DHConvalidator</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc><abstract><p>Based on ongoing research in the collaborative Digital Theological Hobbes (DTH) project, this long presentation aims to showcase the benefits of a textometric approach to the elaboration and exploitation of a machine-readable model of Hobbes’s Bible in the English political works relying on the TXM software platform.</p></abstract><langUsage><language ident="en">English</language></langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="category">
                    <term>Paper</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="subcategory">
                    <term>Long Presentation</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="keywords">
                    <term>Bible</term>
                    <term>EEBO-TCP XML-TEI P5 diplomatic transcriptions</term>
                    <term>Hobbes</term>
                    <term>TXM</term>
                    <term>URS annotation TXM extension</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="topics">
                    <term>annotation structures</term>
                    <term>systems</term>
                    <term>and methods</term>
                    <term>data modeling</term>
                    <term>scholarly editing and editions development</term>
                    <term>analysis</term>
                    <term>and methods</term>
                    <term>text mining and analysis</term>
                    <term>History</term>
                    <term>Humanities computing</term>
                    <term>Philosophy</term>
                    <term>Theology and religious studies</term>
                    
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <p>During the elaboration of his political theory, the materialist philosopher Thomas
                Hobbes (1588-1679) developed an increasingly close relationship with the Bible.
                Although he credited himself with the scientific foundation of politics, Hobbes used
                more and more scriptural evidence in support of his arguments in <hi rend="italic">The Elements of Law</hi> (1640), <hi rend="italic">De Cive</hi> (1642, 1647),
                and the English and Latin
                <hi rend="italic">Leviathan </hi>(1651, 1668). Hobbes’s growing
                reliance on the sacred text thus raises the question of how his citational and
                exegetical practice developed between 1640 and 1668 and for what purposes. </p>
            <p>Yet, determining how the philosopher’s knowledge and use of the Scriptures evolved
                over time does not come without difficulty, to the extent that the affair has come
                to be known as “the problem of Hobbes and the Bible” (Jones 1984). As Harold
                Whitmore Jones pointed out as far back as 1984, the hundreds of biblical quotations
                sprinkled throughout the political works, Hobbes’s simultaneous use of multiple
                scriptural sources, and his inconsistent handling of the source texts make it
                arduous to manually account for the nature and evolution of the philosopher’s
                treatment of the Bible. That is why, despite the recent rise in interest in Hobbes’s
                religion, the philosopher’s knowledge and use of the Scriptures seems, as yet, never
                to have formed the object of a systematic inquiry. Even the most ground-breaking
                investigations (Jones 1984; Pacchi et al. 1988; Somos 2015; Davis 2018) have not
                ventured beyond specific case studies, sample surveys, general overviews, or
                methodological recommendations. </p>
            <p>However, if the scholarly community has made only limited progress towards “the
                problem of Hobbes and the Bible”, it is now generally agreed that its solution would
                foster a better understanding of the philosopher’s biblical exegesis but also of his
                works at large. Hence the interest in actualizing Jones’s pioneering undertaking, by
                exploring the opportunities made possible in the digital turn by a collaboration
                between computational linguistics and intellectual history. </p>
            <p>Based on ongoing research in the framework of the <hi rend="italic">Digital
                    Theological Hobbes</hi> (DTH) project, this long presentation aims to display
                the benefits of a textometric approach to the challenges that hindered the success
                of the enquiries conducted so far: a comprehensive inspection and analysis of
                heterogeneous scriptural data. Since it is not possible to ascertain how Hobbes’s
                knowledge and use of the Scriptures evolved without reconstituting the philosopher’s
                Bible from the numerous references and citations scattered in his works, this
                presentation illustrates the workflow developed to turn text (i.e., Hobbes’s
                explicit biblical references and quotations) into computable data. To do so, it
                presents a case study based on TXM, a Text Encoding Initiative (TEI) and Natural
                Language Processing (NLP) oriented, free and open-source software platform
                implementing textometry (Heiden 2010), and on EEBO-TCP XML-TEI P5 diplomatic
                transcriptions of Hobbes’s English political works (Kichuk 2007), automatically
                lemmatized by the MorphAdorner software (Burns 2013). </p>
            <p>After a brief introduction of the historical-philosophical problem that lies at the
                roots of the DTH project, the first part of the presentation focuses on the
                construction of the case study envisaged to elaborate a machine-readable model of
                Hobbes’s Bible in the English political works. Special attention is paid to the
                building of a TXM-based corpus of the EEBO-TCP XML-TEI P5 diplomatic transcriptions
                of such works: the published treaties composing the 1640 manuscript <hi rend="italic">The Elements of Law</hi> ( <hi rend="italic">Humane Nature</hi>
                and <hi rend="italic">De Corpore Politico</hi>), the English translation of <hi rend="italic">De Cive</hi> (P <hi rend="italic">hilosophicall Rudiments
                    concerning Government and Society</hi>), and the 1651 edition of <hi rend="italic">Leviathan</hi>. It is, indeed, the shared analogous philological
                and linguistic enrichments of these transcriptions that allow for a unified,
                systematic, and reproducible method for the processing of Hobbes’s explicit biblical
                references and quotations. </p>
            <p>The second part of the presentation introduces the workflow developed to model,
                retrieve, annotate, and operationalize Hobbes’s explicit biblical references and
                quotations as they appear in the EEBO-TCP XML-TEI P5 diplomatic transcriptions (see
                Figures 1-3).</p>
            <figure>
                <graphic url="Pictures/fig1.png"/>
                <head>Figure 1. Concordance of the 946 matches produced by the surface query for
                    Hobbes’s biblical references (corresponding to multiple book-chapter-verse and
                    verse patterns) in the corpus of the English political works. This screenshot
                    nicely illustrates the efficacy of the query, able to retrieve different formats
                    of isolated verses (like “ver. 8.”, “verse 10.”, “ver. 11, 12.”), isolated book
                    chapters (like “Mat. 10.”), standard references (like “Mat. 19. 28.”, “2 Cor. 1.
                    24.”), composite references (like “Mat. 18. 15, 16, 17” and “1 Cor. 5. 3, 4
                    &amp; 5”), but also references made up of several kinds of abbreviations (like
                    “1 Epist. chap. 2. ver. 13, 14, 15” or “1 Cor. 5. ver. 9, 10, &amp;c.”).
                    However, despite its overall efficacy, the query misses some references
                    (silence) and matches some false references (noise).</head>
            </figure>
            <figure>
                <graphic url="Pictures/fig2.png"/>
                <head>Figure 2. The screenshot illustrates the results of the
                    “Annotate-Hobbes-Biblical-References” script in the corpus of the English
                    political works. First of all, the script automatically creates as many URS
                    biblical reference units (here underlined in green) as are the verse or chapter
                    numbers found in the matches of the query for Hobbes’s biblical references.
                    Secondly, it performs an automatic annotation of these units by projecting the
                    constitutive elements of each biblical reference (the abbreviated book title and
                    eventual number as well as the chapter and verse numbers) into a set of
                    predetermined URS annotation fields as their properties. By applying a table of
                    correspondence between the biblical book abbreviations and their full titles and
                    the part of the Bible they belong to, the script further fills in annotation
                    fields that will be later used for the retrieval and analysis of the URS units.
                    Finally, every time it finds an isolated biblical verse, the script projects the
                    attributes of the “book”, “book Title”, “number” and “part” fields of the
                    preceding URS biblical reference unit into the URS unit corresponding to the
                    incomplete reference. Here “Vers. 2” (displayed in dark green) is automatically
                    annotated as the second verse of the fourth chapter of the first letter of
                    John.</head>
            </figure>
            <figure>
                <graphic url="Pictures/fig3.png"/>
                <head>Figure 3. This screenshot exemplifies the query result verification method. In
                    order to reduce the noise produced by the query for Hobbes’s biblical
                    references, the automatic annotation of the URS units is followed by their
                    manual correction. Here, the URS biblical reference unit “Act. 12” is manually
                    deleted once shown as false by its contextualisation through the synoptic
                    edition.</head>
            </figure>
           
            <p>To this end, it illustrates how TXM originally combines the potential of a systematic
                search of word sequence patterns formulated in the CQL query language of the CQP
                search engine with that of information annotation through the Unit-Relation-Schema
                (URS) annotation TXM extension (Heiden, 2018). It shows, as a result, how TXM
                ensures a full indexation of Hobbes’s diplomatic biblical references (see Figure 4),
                the complete extraction of the adjacent quotations and a textometric analysis of
                their lexicon.</p>
            <figure>
                <graphic url="Pictures/fig4.png"/>
                <head>Figure 4. The screenshot shows the dynamic index of the biblical reference
                    annotations occurring in the Humane Nature and De Corpore Politico sub-corpus.
                    Two sets of hyperlinks (displayed in blue in the middle of the figure) allow to
                    navigate to, respectively, the diplomatic and critical edition page of
                    occurrence of each index entry. By clicking on the [Psalms 15.1,] 2-DCP, 1.5.5,
                    p.41 hyperlink, the synoptic edition of Hobbes’s De Corpore Politico opens on
                    page 41, in correspondence of the reference to the first verse of the fifteenth
                    Psalm (on the left). By clicking on the [96] hyperlink, it is Tönnies’s critical
                    edition of The Elements of Law that opens in correspondence of the reference to
                    the same verse, on page 96, for comparison purposes (on the right).</head>
            </figure>
         
            <p>The third part of the presentation displays the workflow developed to model,
                annotate, and operationalize the micro-interpretations elaborated by the main modern
                critical editors of Hobbes’s English political works: Ferdinand Tönnies, Howard
                Warrender and Noel Malcolm. As Hobbes’s diplomatic biblical references are often
                incomplete, omitted, or erroneous, a new layer of complexity needs to be added for
                the machine-readable model of Hobbes’s Bible to be exhaustive and, therefore, useful
                for the advancement of scholarship. This part thus shows how TXM allows, via the URS
                TXM extension and its tools, not only for the thorough indexation and analysis of
                Hobbes’s critical biblical references but also for the calculation of the ‘editorial
                delta’, i.e., the variation between the diplomatic and critical information encoded
                in the texts (see Figure 5).</p>
            <figure>
                <graphic url="Pictures/fig5.png"/>
                <head>Figure 5. By comparing the indexes of biblical references of our two corpora,
                    the diplomatic edition of Humane Nature and De Corpore Politico and Tönnies’s
                    critical edition of The Elements of Law, some discordances appear. Sometimes,
                    they reveal the positive impact of editorial work: for instance, when Tönnies
                    amends the base text of Hobbes’s printed editions of Humane Nature and De
                    Corpore Politico on the basis of the Harley MS 4235 (MS A) witness. In other
                    cases, discordances may reveal residual typos or inaccuracies of the critical
                    edition itself. This screenshot provides an example of such discrepancies. The
                    reference to the Gospel of John has a different chapter number in De Corpore
                    Politico (upper section) and Tönnies’s edition (lower section): in De Corpore
                    Politico it is the eighteenth chapter that is referred to, while in The Elements
                    of Law the reference points to the twenty-eighth chapter.</head>
            </figure>
         
            <p>In conclusion, the presentation critically evaluates the results obtained and
                outlines further developments towards the textometric detection of Hobbes’s reuse of
                his most likely main biblical source, the King James Bible or Authorised Version
                (1611), in comparison with the principal competing Early Modern English translations
                available at the time: the Calvinist Geneva Bible of 1557-1560 and the Catholic
                Rheims-Douay Bible of 1582-1610.</p>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliogr">
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <bibl>Secondary literature:</bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Davis, P. B.</author> (2018): “Devil in the
                        Details. Hobbes’s Use and Abuse of Scripture”, in: van Apeldoorn, L. and
                        Douglass, R. (eds): <hi rend="italic">Hobbes on Politics and Religion</hi>.
                        Oxford: Oxford University Press, 135-49. </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Jones, H. W</author>. (1984): “Thomas
                        Hobbes and the Bible: A Preliminary Enquiry”, in: Société des amis du Centre
                        d'études supérieures de la Renaissance (ed): <hi rend="italic">Arts du
                            spectacle et histoire des idées : recueil offert en hommage à Jean
                            Jacquot</hi>. Tours: Centre d'études supérieures de la Renaissance,
                        271-85. </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Pacchi, A.</author> / <author>Invernizzi, G.</author> and <author>Lupoli, A.</author> (eds) (1988): <hi rend="italic">Scritti teologici</hi>. Franco Angeli, Milano. </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Somos, M.</author> (2015): “Bible
                        Interpretation and the Constitution of the Christian Commonwealth in
                        Hobbes’s <hi rend="italic">Leviathan</hi>”, Part III, <hi rend="italic">Storia del pensiero politico</hi>, 2: 175-201. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Corpora and tools:</bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Burns, R. R.</author>
                        (2013): <hi rend="italic">MorphAdorner v2: A Java Library for the
                            Morphological Adornment of English Language Texts</hi>. Northwestern
                        University, Evaston.
                        <ref target="http://morphadorner.northwestern.edu/morphadorner/download/morphadorner.pdf">http://morphadorner.northwestern.edu/morphadorner/download/morphadorner.pdf</ref>
                        [15.04.2019]. </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Heiden, S.</author> (2010): “The TXM
                        Platform: Building Open-Source Textual Analysis Software Compatible with the
                        TEI Encoding Scheme”, in: Otoguro, R., Ishikawa, K., Umemoto, H., Yoshimoto,
                        K. and Harada, Y. (eds): <hi rend="italic">24th Pacific Asia Conference on
                            Language, Information and Computation</hi> – <hi rend="italic">PACLIC24</hi>. Sendai: Institute for Digital Enhancement of Cognitive
                        Development, 389-98.
                        <ref target="https://halshs.archives-ouvertes.fr/halshs-00549764/en">https://halshs.archives-ouvertes.fr/halshs-00549764/en</ref> [15.04.2019]. </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Heiden, S.</author> (2018):
                        “Annotation-based Digital Text Corpora Analysis within the TXM Platform”,
                        in: Iezzi, D. F., Celardo, L. and Misuraca, M. (eds): <hi rend="italic">Proceedings of the 14th International Conference on the Statistical
                            Analysis of Textual Data (JADT 2018)</hi>. Rome: UniversItalia, 367-74.
                        <ref target="http://jadt2018.uniroma2.it">http://jadt2018.uniroma2.it</ref> [15.04.2019]. </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Kichuk, D.</author> (2007): Metamorphosis:
                        Remediation in Early English Books Online (EEBO), <hi rend="italic">Literary
                            and Linguistic Computing</hi>, 22(3): 291-303. </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>TEI Consortium</author> (eds) (2019): <hi rend="italic">TEI P5:
                            Guidelines for Electronic Text Encoding and Interchange. Version
                            3.5.0</hi>. Last updated on 29 January 2019.
                        <ref target="https://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/Guidelines.pdf">https://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/Guidelines.pdf</ref>
                        [15.04.2019]. </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text></TEI>