<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_allPlus.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_allPlus.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Innovators of the Past: Modelling Novelty and Resonance in
                        Dutch Historical Language Records</title>
                <author n="LasscheAlieROS_Ruben_Innovators_of_the_Past__Modelling_Novelty_and_Reso.xml"><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-7607-0174" n="LasscheAlie">
                        <surname>Lassche</surname>
                        <forename>Alie</forename>
                    </persName><affiliation>Leiden University, Netherlands, The</affiliation><email>a.w.lassche@hum.leidenuniv.nl</email></author><meeting><date from-iso="2023-07-10" to-iso="2023-07-14"/><title>Digital Humanities 2023. Collaboration as Opportunity</title><placeName>Graz</placeName></meeting>
                <author n="RosRubenROS_Ruben_Innovators_of_the_Past__Modelling_Novelty_and_Reso.xml"><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-5303-2861" n="RosRuben">
                        <surname>Ros</surname>
                        <forename>Ruben</forename>
                    </persName><affiliation>Leiden University, Netherlands, The</affiliation><email>r.s.ros@hum.leidenuniv.nl</email></author><meeting><date from-iso="2023-07-10" to-iso="2023-07-14"/><title>Digital Humanities 2023. Collaboration as Opportunity</title><placeName>Graz</placeName></meeting>
            </titleStmt>
            
            <publicationStmt><publisher><orgName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1137284463">Zentrum für Informationsmodellierung
                    - Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities, Karl-Franzens-Universität
                    Graz</orgName></publisher><date when="2023">2023</date><pubPlace>Graz</pubPlace><availability><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">Creative Commons BY
                    4.0</licence></availability></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title>Digital Humanities 2023: Book of Abstracts</title><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-9256-0958"><forename>Walter</forename><surname>Scholger</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>University of Graz</orgName><placeName>Graz, Austria</placeName></affiliation><email>walter.scholger@uni-graz.at</email></editor><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-1726-1712"><forename>Georg</forename><surname>Vogeler</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>University of Graz</orgName><placeName>Graz, Austria</placeName></affiliation><email>georg.vogeler@uni-graz.at</email></editor><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-3919-993X"><forename>Toma</forename><surname>Tasovac</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>Belgrade Center for Digital Humanities</orgName><placeName>Belgrade, Serbia</placeName></affiliation><email>ttasovac@humanistika.org</email></editor><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-4593-059X"><forename>Anne</forename><surname>Baillot</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>Le Mans Université</orgName><placeName>Le Mans, France</placeName></affiliation><email>anne.baillot@univ-lemans.fr</email></editor><respStmt><resp>Data Management</resp><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0009-0007-9019-8215"><forename>Elisabeth</forename><surname>Raunig</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Management</resp><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-1438-3236"><forename>Martina</forename><surname>Scholger</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Management</resp><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-9116-0402"><forename>Elisabeth</forename><surname>Steiner</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Curation</resp><persName><forename>Johanna</forename><surname>Ofenauer</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Curation</resp><persName><forename>Christina</forename><surname>Burgstaller</surname></persName></respStmt><idno type="DOI">10.5281/zenodo.7961822</idno></seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from an OASIS Open Document</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="DHCONVALIDATOR" version="1.22">
                    <label>DHConvalidator</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc><abstract><p>Studies in the humanities are increasingly incorporating methods from information theory, which are based on dynamics in word usage and measures of relative entropy. This paper uses windowed relative entropy to thematic text representations to generate signals that capture information novelty and resonance and, aggregated on the actor-level, shed light on the innovators of the past. Comparing early modern chronicles and twentieth-century parliamentary debate we aim to investigate several dimensions of innovation in historical language records.</p></abstract><langUsage><language ident="en">English</language></langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="category">
                    <term>Paper</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="subcategory">
                    <term>Long Presentation</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="keywords">
                    <term>entropy</term>
                    <term>novelty</term>
                    <term>resonance</term>
                    <term>top2vec</term>
                    <term>doc2vec</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="topics">
                    <term>cultural analytics</term>
                    <term>manuscripts description</term>
                    <term>representation</term>
                    <term>and analysis</term>
                    <term>rhetorical analysis</term>
                    <term>text mining and analysis</term>
                    <term>History</term>
                    <term>Political science</term>
                    
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div type="div1">
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <p>Studies in the humanities are increasingly incorporating methods from information
                    theory, which are based on dynamics in word usage and measures of relative
                    entropy. We know from previous work that word usage in newspapers and chronicles
                    is sensitive to the dynamics of socio-cultural events. (Wevers, Kostkan, and
                    Nielbo 2021; Gao et al. 2012; Daems et al. 2019) Entropy measures have for
                    example been used to detect differences between opposite political movements in
                    French politics, and between distinct historical periods. (Barron et al. 2018;
                    Guldi 2019) More specifically, several studies have applied windowed relative
                    entropy to thematic text representations to generate signals that capture
                    information novelty, which is the content difference from the past, and
                    information resonance, which is the degree to which future information conforms
                    to novelty. The methods have been successfully applied to parliamentary debates
                    from the French Revolution, to Dutch newspapers from the second half of the 20st
                    century, to Danish newspapers from the COVID-19 pandemic, and to early modern
                    Dutch chronicles.(Barron et al. 2018; Wevers, Kostkan, and Nielbo 2021; Nielbo
                    et al. 2021; Lassche, Kostkan, and Nielbo 2022)</p>
                <p>This study builds further on these existing studies, by using methods for novelty
                    and resonance detection to measure innovation of individual historical actors.
                    To explore to what extent this method can be applied to corpora with different
                    characteristics, we use two historical Dutch corpora from different periods and
                    with different features. We investigate the novelty and resonance scores on the
                    aggregated actor-level in our corpora to identify historical figures responsible
                    for innovative and resonant texts. We ask who is responsible for innovation, how
                    the actor-level distribution of novelty behaves (over time) and to what extent
                    the ‘novelty bias’ observed in earlier studies holds on the level of actors.
                    Comparing different corpora helps us to critically interrogate the information
                    theoretical measures. Building on existing applications of the method and our
                    comparison, we hope to work towards more general arguments about novelty and
                    resonance in historical language data.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="div1">
                <head>Corpora</head>
                <p>In our study, we distinguish the <hi rend="italic">Chronicles Corpus</hi> and the
                        <hi rend="italic">Parliament Corpus</hi>, of which the characteristics are
                    included in Table 1. The <hi rend="italic">Chronicles Corpus</hi> consists of early modern Dutch chronicles, written
                    between 1500 and 1850. Chronicles are manuscripts written by middle-class
                    people, in which they report on current events in their communities, and on what
                    they consider interesting or relevant. These texts are ordered chronologically,
                    providing both the date and a report of a certain event. They were rarely
                    printed in the lifetime of their authors, but, despite their scribal form, they
                    could still circulate in the localities, be read and continued by other authors,
                    influencing future generations. (Pollmann 2016, 2011) The <hi rend="italic">Chronicles Corpus</hi> was scanned and transcribed with the HTR tool
                    Transkribus.(Kahle et al. 9AD) The corpus is enriched with a date label that is
                    essential in this study in order to create time series of chronicle fragments. </p>
                <p>Previous research in which novelty and resonance signals were computed over the
                        <hi rend="italic">Chronicles Corpus</hi> already showed how changes in the
                    novelty signal coincide with times of political uncertainty. The resonance
                    signal, however, remained flat over time, which suggested that future
                    information did not conform to the introduced novelty.(Lassche, Kostkan, and
                    Nielbo 2022) An investigation of actor-level novelty and resonance scores, as
                    will be done in this paper, will provide more insight in the level of innovation
                    of individual chroniclers. </p>
                <table xml:id="d280e210">
                    <head>Table 1:</head>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Corpus</cell>
                        <cell># Texts</cell>
                        <cell># Authors</cell>
                        <cell># Tokens</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Chronicles</cell>
                        <cell>144</cell>
                        <cell>109</cell>
                        <cell>6.103.765</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Parliament</cell>
                        <cell>1493</cell>
                        <cell>410</cell>
                        <cell>18.050.303</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>The Parliament Corpus consists of proceedings of the Dutch Lower House from the
                    period between 1945 and 1963. The proceedings contain speeches delivered in
                    parliament by members of parliament, the chair, and government ministers. They
                    record the day-to-day practices of legislation, the filing of motions, and
                    question answering. Proceedings are not verbatim reports, but edited
                    transcriptions of the speeches. The digitized proceedings are tokenized and
                    lemmatized and contain metadata on speaker party affiliations and debate topics.
                    The corpus consists of all sessions held between 1945 and 1963. In this period,
                    parliament would meet several days a week, with the exception of the summer
                    months and campaign periods. From the perspective of parliamentary language,
                    actor-level novelty and resonance appear as promising metrics to evaluate the
                    standard depiction of the period as one during which parliament was ‘docile’ and
                    largely overshadowed by the expanding administration.(Hemerijck 1994; Daalder
                    and Berg 1990) Especially the differences in novelty and resonance between
                    government members and representatives of coalition and opposition parties would
                    be an innovative way of looking at postwar parliamentary history.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="div1">
                <head>Methods</head>
                <p>We use Top2Vec as a means to generate document (chronicle or speech)
                    representations.(Angelov 2020) Top2Vec learns joint word and document
                    representation and uses document cluster centroids and word embeddings to
                    generate topics. The cosine similarity between a document and the identified
                    cluster centroids can be used to generate document-topic distributions that
                    serve as the basis for novelty detection.</p>
                <p>With novelty, we refer to an event’s S(j) reliable difference from past events
                    S(j-1), S(j-2), S(j-n) in window <hi rend="italic">w</hi> and resonance as the
                    degree to which future events S(j+1), S(j+2), S(j+n) conform to an event’s S(j)
                    novelty. Where T is the transience of S(j). This model for novelty and resonance
                    was originally proposed by Barron et al., but here we use the symmetrized and
                    smooth version with the Jensen-Shannon divergence. </p>
                <p>(Unfortunately, the Digital Humanities 2023 software is not able to properly
                    display mathematical formulae)</p>
            </div>
            <div type="div1">
                <head>Preliminary Results</head>
                <p>As an example of our approach, Figures 1 and 2 show the aggregated novelty scores
                    on the actor level plotted against the resonance scores, both for the Chronicles
                    Corpus and the Parliament Corpus. Figure 1 shows a decrease in novelty over
                    time, suggesting that earlier chronicles consist of more novel content than
                    later chronicles. Figure 2 shows the variation in novelty and resonance across
                    parliamentary speakers, with additional information on parliamentary roles
                    indicated by colours and information on the number of speeches represented by
                    scatter size. The figure points to the relatively low resonance of government
                    members compared to members of parliament and the relatively high novelty of
                    chairs (grey). The latter observation can be explained by the institutional
                    function of the parliament chair, who is responsible for opening and introducing
                    debates and their topics. However, the low resonances of government members as
                    well as high-scoring members are not so easily explained. Our paper will discuss
                    these and other findings in more detail.</p>
                <p><figure>
                        <graphic url="Pictures/85a0b1a3ac3b915252b27c9f4209121f.png"/>
                        <head>Figure 1. Novelty and Resonance in the Chronicles Corpus. Top Left:
                            Violin plots of the resonance actor resonance distribution grouped by
                            century. Top Right: Violin plots of the resonance actor novelty
                            distribution grouped by century. Bottom: Scatter plot of novelty vs.
                            resonance on the aggregate level of chroniclers at scale =30. The
                            colours correspond to the century in which the chronicle was finished,
                            the size of the scatters refers to the size of the chronicle.</head>
                    </figure></p>
                <p><figure>
                        <graphic url="Pictures/159dbc13388cd1cd22f8b995ed1c3996.png"/>
                        <head>Figure 2. Novelty and Resonance in the Parliament Corpus. Top Left:
                            Violin plots of the resonance actor resonance distribution grouped by
                            role. Top Right: Violin plots of the resonance actor novelty
                            distribution grouped by role. Bottom: A scatter plot of novelty vs.
                            resonance on the aggregate level of parliamentary speakers at scale =30.
                            The colours correspond to the role metadata tag in the parliamentary
                            proceedings. Roles can be “government" (blue), “mp" (red), and “chair"
                            (gray). The plot shows the relatively low resonance of government
                            speakers compared to members of parliament (mp’s) as well as the high
                            novelty of chairs. The size of the scatters refers to the number of
                            unique speeches by the speakers</head>
                    </figure></p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliogr">
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <bibl><author>Angelov, Dimo. </author>2020. “Top2Vec: Distributed
                        Representations of Topics,” nos. arXiv:2008.09470 [cs, stat] (August).
                        http://arxiv.org/abs/2008.09470.</bibl>
                    <bibl><author>Barron, Alexander T. J., Jenny Huang, Rebecca L. Spang,
                            and Simon DeDeo. </author>2018. “Individuals, Institutions, and Innovation
                        in the Debates of the French Revolution.” Proceedings of the National
                        Academy of Sciences 115 (18): 4607–12.
                        https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.1717729115.</bibl>
                    <bibl><author>Daalder, Hans, and Johannes T. van den Berg. </author>1990.
                        Politiek en historie: opstellen over Nederlandse politiek en vergelijkende
                        politieke wetenschap. Amsterdam: Bakker.</bibl>
                    <bibl><author>Daems, Joke, Thomas D’haeninck, Simon Hengchen, Tecle
                            Zere, and Christophe Verbruggen. </author>2019. “‘Workers of the World’? A
                        Digital Approach to Classify the International Scope of Belgian Socialist
                        Newspapers, 1885.” Journal of European Periodical Studies 4 (1): 99–114.
                        https://doi.org/10.21825/jeps.v4i1.10187.</bibl>
                    <bibl><author>Gao, Jianbo, Jing Hu, Xiang Mao, and Matjaž Perc.
                        </author>2012. “Culturomics Meets Random Fractal Theory: Insights into
                        Long-Range Correlations of Social and Natural Phenomena over the Past Two
                        Centuries.” Journal of the Royal Society Interface 9 (73): 1956–64.
                        https://doi.org/10.1098/rsif.2011.0846.</bibl>
                    <bibl><author>Guldi, Jo. </author>2019. “The Measures of Modernity: The New
                        Quantitative Metrics of Historical Change over Time and Their Critical
                        Interpretation.” International Journal for History, Culture and Modernity 7
                        (1): 899–939. https://doi.org/10.18352/hcm.589.</bibl>
                    <bibl><author>Hemerijck, A. C. </author>1994. “Hardnekkigheid van
                        Corporatisch Beleid in Nederland.” Beleid En Maatschappij 21 (1-2):
                        23–47.</bibl>
                    <bibl><author>Kahle, P., S. Colutto, H. Hackl, and H. Mühlberger.
                        </author>9AD. “Transkribus - A Service Platform for Transcription, Recognition
                        and Retrieval of Historical Documents.” In 2017 14th IAPR International
                        Conference on Document Analysis and Recognition (ICDAR), 04:19–24.
                        https://doi.org/10.1109/ICDAR.2017.307.</bibl>
                    <bibl><author>Lassche, Alie, Jan Kostkan, and Kristoffer Nielbo.
                        </author>2022. “Chronicling Crises: Event Detection in Early Modern Chronicles
                        from the Low Countries.” In Computational Humanities Research.
                        Antwerp.</bibl>
                    <bibl><author>Nielbo, Kristoffer L., Frida Haestrup, Kenneth C.
                            Enevoldsen, Peter B. Vahlstrup, Rebekah B. Baglini, and Andreas
                            Roepstorff. </author>2021. “When No News Is Bad News – Detection of Negative
                        Events from News Media Content.” arXiv.
                        http://arxiv.org/abs/2102.06505.</bibl>
                    <bibl><author>Pollmann, Judith. </author>2011. Catholic Identity and the
                        Revolt of the Netherlands, 1520-1635. The Past &amp; Present Book Series.
                        Oxford; New York: Oxford University Press.</bibl>
                    <bibl><author>Pollmann, Judith.</author> 2016. “Archiving the Present and
                        Chronicling for the Future in Early Modern Europe.” Past &amp; Present 230
                        (suppl 11): 231–52. https://doi.org/10.1093/pastj/gtw029.</bibl>
                    <bibl><author>Wevers, Melvin, Jan Kostkan, and Kristoffer Nielbo.
                        </author>2021. “Event Flow - How Events Shaped the Flow of the News, 1950-1995.”
                        In Computational Humanities Research Conference, 62–76. Amsterdam.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text></TEI>