<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_allPlus.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_allPlus.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Can Machine Translation of Literary Texts Fool Stylometry?</title>
                <author n="RybickiJanRYBICKI_Jan_Can_Machine_Translation_of_Literary_Texts_Fool_S.xml"><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2504-9372" n="RybickiJan">
                        <surname>Rybicki</surname>
                        <forename>Jan</forename>
                    </persName><affiliation>Uniwersytet Jagielloński, Poland</affiliation><email>jan.rybicki@uj.edu.pl</email></author><meeting><date from-iso="2023-07-10" to-iso="2023-07-14"/><title>Digital Humanities 2023. Collaboration as Opportunity</title><placeName>Graz</placeName></meeting>
            </titleStmt>
            
            <publicationStmt><publisher><orgName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1137284463">Zentrum für Informationsmodellierung
                    - Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities, Karl-Franzens-Universität
                    Graz</orgName></publisher><date when="2023">2023</date><pubPlace>Graz</pubPlace><availability><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">Creative Commons BY
                    4.0</licence></availability></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title>Digital Humanities 2023: Book of Abstracts</title><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-9256-0958"><forename>Walter</forename><surname>Scholger</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>University of Graz</orgName><placeName>Graz, Austria</placeName></affiliation><email>walter.scholger@uni-graz.at</email></editor><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-1726-1712"><forename>Georg</forename><surname>Vogeler</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>University of Graz</orgName><placeName>Graz, Austria</placeName></affiliation><email>georg.vogeler@uni-graz.at</email></editor><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-3919-993X"><forename>Toma</forename><surname>Tasovac</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>Belgrade Center for Digital Humanities</orgName><placeName>Belgrade, Serbia</placeName></affiliation><email>ttasovac@humanistika.org</email></editor><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-4593-059X"><forename>Anne</forename><surname>Baillot</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>Le Mans Université</orgName><placeName>Le Mans, France</placeName></affiliation><email>anne.baillot@univ-lemans.fr</email></editor><respStmt><resp>Data Management</resp><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0009-0007-9019-8215"><forename>Elisabeth</forename><surname>Raunig</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Management</resp><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-1438-3236"><forename>Martina</forename><surname>Scholger</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Management</resp><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-9116-0402"><forename>Elisabeth</forename><surname>Steiner</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Curation</resp><persName><forename>Johanna</forename><surname>Ofenauer</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Curation</resp><persName><forename>Christina</forename><surname>Burgstaller</surname></persName></respStmt><idno type="DOI">10.5281/zenodo.7961822</idno></seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="DHCONVALIDATOR" version="1.22">
                    <label>DHConvalidator</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc><abstract><p>This paper shows results of an experiment on 50 French literary texts in human translations into English, and two corresponding corpora translated by Google Translate and DeepL. It shows that the stylometric behavior of machine translations is similar to that of those done by humans – with some notable exceptions.</p></abstract><langUsage><language ident="en">English</language></langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="category">
                    <term>Paper</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="subcategory">
                    <term>Long Presentation</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="keywords">
                    <term>machine translation</term>
                    <term>human translation</term>
                    <term>stylometry</term>
                    <term>cluster analysis</term>
                    <term>network analysis</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="topics">
                    <term>attribution studies and stylometric analysis</term>
                    <term>network analysis and graphs theory and application</term>
                    <term>Literary studies</term>
                    <term>Translation studies</term>
                    
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <div>
                    <head>Introduction</head>
                    <p>Not so long ago, machine translation systems served as a butt of jokes among
                        their human competitors. In fact, the “first and longer standing
                        perspective” on MT dealing with literary texts tended “to see machine
                        translation outputs as a kind of ‘found poetry’, … often prized for their
                        alienating, ungrammatical, anti-narrative or even comical effects” (Kenny
                        and Winters 2021). But now MT has turned to Neural Networks/Deep Learning;
                        and while its use in literary translation is still not widespread practice,
                        this seems to be looming over the horizon. </p>
                    <p>Stylometric research on machine translation of literature is virtually
                        non-existent. There is a growing body of qualitative case studies on MT in
                        literary translation (Toral and Way 2015, 2018, Kenny and Winters 2020,
                        Schmidt 2021, Zhang 2021), but only two texts mix quantitative/stylometric
                        authorship attribution techniques with MT (Caliskan and Greenstadt 2012,
                        Caliskan 2013).</p>
                    <p>Human literary translations have fared only slightly better in stylometric
                        research. The notion of the invisible (literary) translator, criticized by
                        Lawrence Venuti (1995), has been found to persist, to some extent, in
                        stylometric studies (Rybicki 2012). Translators’ stylometric traces may be
                        visible when they are followed in collaborative translations of the same
                        text (Rybicki and Heydel 2013) or in texts of the same author translated by
                        different humans (Rybicki 2006). Dependence of translators’ stylistic
                        visibility was studied in relation to language combinations (Lee 2018) and
                        individual translators’ styles (Burrows 2002a, Mastropierro 2018). Lee
                        (2021) used a variety of linguistic features to show “a clear-cut divide in
                        writing style between human and machine translators” and to observe that
                        different MT systems are becoming more alike to each other in their output
                        of literary translation.</p>
                    <p>The main focus of this experiment is to see whether machine translation
                        systems now produce literary translations that do not depart in their
                        stylometric features from those made by humans. </p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Methods</head>
                    <p>In this study, the originals and the English translations: human, Google
                        Translate, and DeepL, are compared via stylometry based on very frequent
                        words according to Burrows’s Delta (Burrows 2002b), combined with cluster
                        analysis of distance measures (Smith and Aldridge 2011, Evert et al. 2017)
                        and network analysis (Eder 2017), using the “stylo” package (Eder et al.
                        2016) for R (R Core Team 2021). This standard authorship attribution
                        procedure will be adopted through a consensus cluster analysis and its
                        network analysis visualizations.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Material</head>
                    <p>The 52 texts for this study were selected from classical 19 <hi rend="superscript">th</hi>- and early 20 <hi rend="superscript">th</hi>-century French literature and included 2-10 novels each by 10
                        writers. In the corresponding set of English translations, not a single
                        author was translated by a single translator; also, no translator dealt with
                        more than one original author. In all, 23 named translators were represented
                        in the English set; 16 translations were anonymous. Full texts of the
                        original novels were also translated into English with Google Translate and
                        DeepL. Altogether, 157 human and machine translations were compared. </p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Results</head>
                    <p>Figure 1 shows a network analysis of cluster-analysed Cosine Delta distances
                        between the French originals. As expected, the individual authors form their
                        own communities.</p>
                    <figure>
                        <head>Figure 1. Network based on cluster analysis of Cosine Delta distances
                            between the French originals.</head>
                        <graphic n="1001" width="10cm" height="7.61cm" url="Pictures/563f3203167427f675551ce130dcea48.png" rend="inline"/>
                    </figure>
                    <p>The same diagram for the English translations shows the persistence of the
                        signal of the original author (Figure 2); the networked patterns of
                        similarity and difference between human and machine translations of the same
                        texts come in two main forms.</p>
                    <figure>
                        <head>Figure 2.</head>
                        <graphic n="1002" width="10cm" height="8.93cm" url="Pictures/6779b177d0342907e39afc5f271b7c4d.png" rend="inline"/>
                    </figure>
                    <p>Usually, human and machine translations of the same texts are strongly
                        connected with each other, resulting in a tightly-knit community for human
                        and machine translations of the same original author. Note, for instance,
                        what happens to Flaubert’s <hi rend="italic">Un cœur simple</hi> when it
                        becomes <hi rend="italic">A Simple Heart</hi>: its single anonymous human
                        translation forms a close triangle with its translations by Google Translate
                        and DeepL (Figure 3, top left). </p>
                    <figure>
                        <head>Figure 3. Network based on cluster analysis of Cosine Delta distances
                            between the English translations of Flaubert and Zola made by humans
                            (dark grey) and machines (light grey).</head>
                        <graphic n="1003" width="10cm" height="7.28cm" url="Pictures/44a2a64788e407061cd6fe54a1ba9ab9.png" rend="inline"/>
                    </figure>
                    <p>Sometimes, however, this pattern is broken. Translations of Balzac by Ellen
                        Marriage form a sub-community of their own in the otherwise mixed group of
                        other human and machine translations (Figure 4, bottom centre). And the
                        human translations of Proust, especially those by C. K. Scott Moncrieff,
                        depart even more clearly from their machine rivals (Figure 5).</p>
                    <figure>
                        <head>Figure 4. Network based on cluster analysis of Cosine Delta distances
                            between the English translations of Balzac made by humans (dark grey)
                            and machines (light grey).</head>
                        <graphic n="1004" width="10cm" height="5.07cm" url="Pictures/5b35bb246b9e64fffdff9491d3c95b77.png" rend="inline"/>
                    </figure>
                    <figure>
                        <head>Figure 5. Network based on cluster analysis of Cosine Delta distances
                            between the English translations of Proust made by humans (dark grey)
                            and machines (light grey).</head>
                        <graphic n="1005" width="9.863686111111111cm" height="8.229616666666667cm" url="Pictures/6c37af907992be84f38b79120bdd519e.png" rend="inline"/>
                    </figure>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Discussion</head>
                    <p>Let’s face it: machine translations of literature are slowly becoming a match
                        for those made by humans, at least in terms of stylometric authorship
                        (and/or translator) attribution. It cannot be a coincidence that only Proust
                        and his version of the stream of consciousness characteristic in its highly
                        complex sentences is too much for machine translations to successfully fool
                        stylometry, while machine-translated traditional storytelling by Dumas is
                        stylometrically much more similar to the human result, except perhaps for
                        the absence of exoticization of the original <hi rend="italic">Monsieur</hi>
                        that human translators invariably used: “’What!’ cried D'Artagnan, ‘your
                        first witness is Mr. Porthos?’" In Proust, machine translation often loses
                        the thread of the narrative, even in his most famous passage: </p>
                    <p>She
                        sent for one of those short, <hi rend="bold">dodgy</hi> cakes called Petites
                        Madeleines… </p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">I carried a spoonful of tea on my lips where I had let a
                            piece of madeleine soften</hi>. But at the very moment when the sip
                        mixed with the crumbs of the cake touched my palate, <hi rend="bold">I
                            trembled, attentive to what was happening in me that was
                            extraordinary</hi>. </p>
                    <p>A
                        delicious pleasure had invaded me…. <hi rend="bold">He</hi> immediately made
                        me indifferent to the vicissitudes of life. </p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Acknowledgement</head>
                    <p>The research has been supported by a grant from the Priority Research
                        Areas</p>
                    <p>“DigiWorld” and “Heritage” under the Strategic Programme Excellence
                        Initiative at</p>
                    <p>Jagiellonian University.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliogr">
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Burrows, John F.</author> (2002a): “The Englishing of Juvenal:
                        computational stylistics and translated texts”, in: <hi rend="italic">Style</hi> 36, 4: 677–99. </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Burrows, John F.</author> (2002b): “‘Delta’: a measure of
                        stylistic difference and a guide to likely authorship”, in: <hi rend="italic">Literary and Linguistic Computing</hi> 17, 3: 267–87. </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Caliskan, Aylin</author> / <author>Greenstadt, Rachel</author>  (2012): “Translate
                        Once, Translate Twice, Translate Thrice and Attribute: Identifying Authors
                        and Machine Translation Tools in Translated Text”, in: IEEE (ed.): <hi rend="italic">ICSC ’12 Proceedings of the 2012 IEEE Sixth International
                            Conference on Semantic Computing, (Palermo,Italy)</hi>, 121–25. </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Constantine, Peter</author> (2019): “Google Translate Gets
                        Voltaire: Literary Translation and the Age of Artificial Intelligence”, in:
                            <hi rend="italic">Contemporary French and Francophone Studies</hi> 23,
                        4: 471-479, DOI: 10.1080/17409292.2019.1694798 </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Eder, Maciej</author> (2017): “Visualization in stylometry:
                        cluster analysis using networks”, in: <hi rend="italic">Digital Scholarship
                            in the Humanities</hi> 32, 1: 50-64. </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Eder, Maciej</author> / <author>Rybicki, Jan</author> / <author>Kestemont, Mike</author>  (2016):
                        “Stylometry with R: a package for computational text analysis”, in: <hi rend="italic">The R Journal</hi> 8, 1: 107–121. </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Evert, Stefan</author> / <author>Proisl, Thomas</author> / <author>Jannidis, Fotis</author> / <author>Reger, Isabella</author> / <author>Pielström, Steffen</author> / <author>Vitt, Thorsten</author>  (2017):
                        “Understanding and explaining Delta measures for authorship attribution”,
                        in: <hi rend="italic">Digital Scholarship in the Humanities</hi> 32 suppl.
                        2: ii4-ii16. </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Kenny, Dorothy</author> / <author>Winters, Marion</author>  (2021): “Machine
                        Translation in Literary Translation: A Case Study”, in: <hi rend="italic">Computer-Assisted Literary Translation Conference CALT2021@Swansea
                            (11-13 May 2021) Book of Abstracts</hi>, Swansea: Swansea University. </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Lee, Changsoo</author> (2018): “Do language combinations affect
                        translators’ stylistic visibility in translated texts?”, in: <hi rend="italic">Digital Scholarship in the Humanities</hi> 33, 3: 592–603. </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Lee, Changsoo</author> (2021): “How do machine translators
                        measure up to human literary translators in stylometric tests?”, in: <hi rend="italic">Digital Scholarship in the Humanities</hi> 37, 3: 813–829. </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Mastropierro, Lorenzo</author> (2018): <hi rend="italic">Corpus
                            Stylistics in Heart of Darkness and its Italian Translations</hi>.
                        London: Bloomsbury. </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>R Core Team</author> (2021): <hi rend="italic">R: A language and
                            environment for statistical computing</hi>. R Foundation for Statistical
                        Computing, Vienna, Austria. <ref target="https://www.R-project.org/">https://www.R-project.org/</ref>. </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Rybicki, Jan</author> (2006): “Burrowing into Translation:
                        Character Idiolects in Henryk Sienkiewicz's Trilogy and its Two English
                        Translations”, in: <hi rend="italic">Literary and Linguistic Computing</hi>
                        21: 91-103. </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Rybicki, Jan</author> (2012): “The Great Mystery of the (Almost)
                        Invisible Translator. Stylometry in Translation”, in: Oakes, Michael P. /
                        Ji, Meng (eds): <hi rend="italic">Quantitative Methods in Corpus-Based
                            Translation Studies</hi>, Amsterdam: John Benjamins 231–48. </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Rybicki, Jan</author> (2021): “Stylometry 0, Machine Translation
                        1. Deep Learning Based MT Scores Important Away Win”, <hi rend="italic">Computer-Assisted Literary Translation Conference CALT2021@Swansea
                            (11-13 May 2021) Book of Abstracts</hi>, Swansea: Swansea University. </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Rybicki, Jan</author> / <author>Heydel, Magda</author>  (2013): “The Stylistics
                        and Stylometry of Collaborative Translation: Woolf’s Night and Day in
                        Polish”, in: <hi rend="italic">Literary and Linguistic Computing</hi> 28, 4:
                        708–17. </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Schmidt, Bradley</author> (2021): “Ghosts in the Machine”, <hi rend="italic">Computer-Assisted Literary Translation Conference
                            CALT2021@Swansea (11-13 May 2021) Book of Abstracts</hi>, Swansea:
                        Swansea University. </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Smith, Peter W. H.</author> / <author>Aldridge, William</author>  (2011):
                        “Improving Authorship Attribution: Optimizing Burrows' Delta Method”, in:
                            <hi rend="italic">Journal of Quantitative Linguistics</hi> 18, 1: 63-88. </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Toral, Antonio</author> / <author>Way, Andy</author>  (2015): “Machine-assisted
                        translation of literary text: a case study”, in: <hi rend="italic">Translation Spaces</hi> 4, 2: 240-267. </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Toral, Antonio</author> / <author>Way, Andy</author>  (2018):  “What level of
                        quality can Neural Machine Translation attain on literary text?”, in:
                        Moorkens, Joss / Castilho, Sheila / Gaspari, Federico / Doherty, Stephen
                        (eds): <hi rend="italic">Translation Quality Assessment: From Principles to
                            Practice</hi>. Heidelberg: Springer International Publishing 263–287. </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Venuti, Lawrence</author> (1995): <hi rend="italic">The
                            Translator's Invisibility: A History of Translation</hi>. Oxford:
                        Routledge. </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Zhang, Shuyin</author> (2021): “On discussion of the machine
                        translation of Chinese Xianxia novels”, <hi rend="italic">Computer-Assisted
                            Literary Translation Conference CALT2021@Swansea (11-13 May 2021) Book
                            of Abstracts</hi>, Swansea: Swansea University. </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text></TEI>