<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_allPlus.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_allPlus.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Non-representational approaches to visualise complex information in the
                    Cultural Heritage domain</title>
                <author n="PasqualValentinaSCHIMMENTI_Andrea_Non_representational_approaches_to_visuali.xml"><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-5931-5187" n="PasqualValentina">
                        <surname>Pasqual</surname>
                        <forename>Valentina</forename>
                    </persName><affiliation>Università di Bologna, Italy</affiliation><email>valentina.pasqual2@unibo.it</email></author><meeting><date from-iso="2023-07-10" to-iso="2023-07-14"/><title>Digital Humanities 2023. Collaboration as Opportunity</title><placeName>Graz</placeName></meeting>
                <author n="PedrettiCarloTeoSCHIMMENTI_Andrea_Non_representational_approaches_to_visuali.xml"><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-4115-0078" n="PedrettiCarloTeo">
                        <surname>Pedretti</surname>
                        <forename>Carlo Teo</forename>
                    </persName><affiliation>Università La Sapienza di Roma, Italy</affiliation><email>carloteo.pedretti@uniroma1.it</email></author><meeting><date from-iso="2023-07-10" to-iso="2023-07-14"/><title>Digital Humanities 2023. Collaboration as Opportunity</title><placeName>Graz</placeName></meeting>
                <author n="SchimmentiAndreaSCHIMMENTI_Andrea_Non_representational_approaches_to_visuali.xml"><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7865-7537" n="SchimmentiAndrea">
                        <surname>Schimmenti</surname>
                        <forename>Andrea</forename>
                    </persName><affiliation>Università di Bologna, Italy</affiliation><email>andrea.schimmenti2@unibo.it</email></author><meeting><date from-iso="2023-07-10" to-iso="2023-07-14"/><title>Digital Humanities 2023. Collaboration as Opportunity</title><placeName>Graz</placeName></meeting>
                <author n="TomasiFrancescaSCHIMMENTI_Andrea_Non_representational_approaches_to_visuali.xml"><persName n="TomasiFrancesca">
                        <surname>Tomasi</surname>
                        <forename>Francesca</forename>
                    </persName><affiliation>Università di Bologna, Italy</affiliation><email>francesca.tomasi@unibo.it</email></author><meeting><date from-iso="2023-07-10" to-iso="2023-07-14"/><title>Digital Humanities 2023. Collaboration as Opportunity</title><placeName>Graz</placeName></meeting>
                <author n="VitaliFabioSCHIMMENTI_Andrea_Non_representational_approaches_to_visuali.xml"><persName n="VitaliFabio">
                        <surname>Vitali</surname>
                        <forename>Fabio</forename>
                    </persName><affiliation>Università di Bologna, Italy</affiliation><email>fabio.vitali@unibo.it</email></author><meeting><date from-iso="2023-07-10" to-iso="2023-07-14"/><title>Digital Humanities 2023. Collaboration as Opportunity</title><placeName>Graz</placeName></meeting>
            </titleStmt>
            
            <publicationStmt><publisher><orgName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1137284463">Zentrum für Informationsmodellierung
                    - Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities, Karl-Franzens-Universität
                    Graz</orgName></publisher><date when="2023">2023</date><pubPlace>Graz</pubPlace><availability><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">Creative Commons BY
                    4.0</licence></availability></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title>Digital Humanities 2023: Book of Abstracts</title><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-9256-0958"><forename>Walter</forename><surname>Scholger</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>University of Graz</orgName><placeName>Graz, Austria</placeName></affiliation><email>walter.scholger@uni-graz.at</email></editor><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-1726-1712"><forename>Georg</forename><surname>Vogeler</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>University of Graz</orgName><placeName>Graz, Austria</placeName></affiliation><email>georg.vogeler@uni-graz.at</email></editor><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-3919-993X"><forename>Toma</forename><surname>Tasovac</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>Belgrade Center for Digital Humanities</orgName><placeName>Belgrade, Serbia</placeName></affiliation><email>ttasovac@humanistika.org</email></editor><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-4593-059X"><forename>Anne</forename><surname>Baillot</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>Le Mans Université</orgName><placeName>Le Mans, France</placeName></affiliation><email>anne.baillot@univ-lemans.fr</email></editor><respStmt><resp>Data Management</resp><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0009-0007-9019-8215"><forename>Elisabeth</forename><surname>Raunig</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Management</resp><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-1438-3236"><forename>Martina</forename><surname>Scholger</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Management</resp><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-9116-0402"><forename>Elisabeth</forename><surname>Steiner</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Curation</resp><persName><forename>Johanna</forename><surname>Ofenauer</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Curation</resp><persName><forename>Christina</forename><surname>Burgstaller</surname></persName></respStmt><idno type="DOI">10.5281/zenodo.7961822</idno></seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="DHCONVALIDATOR" version="1.22">
                    <label>DHConvalidator</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc><abstract><p>RDF formalisations are spreading and offer support for describing complex information such as provenance, contexts and uncertainty, while visualisation paradigms able to represent them efficiently are still lacking. This gap offers the opportunity to build onto the standard visualisations using non-representational approaches, user-centred design, and evaluation methodologies.</p></abstract><langUsage><language ident="en">English</language></langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="category">
                    <term>Paper</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="subcategory">
                    <term>Long Presentation</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="keywords">
                    <term>Data Visualisation</term>
                    <term>RDF</term>
                    <term>Linked Data</term>
                    <term>Critical Design</term>
                    <term>User Experience</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="topics">
                    <term>Interface design</term>
                    <term>development</term>
                    <term>and analysis</term>
                    <term>linked (open) data</term>
                    <term>spatial &amp; spatio-temporal analysis</term>
                    <term>modeling and visualization</term>
                    <term>user experience design and analysis</term>
                    <term>Computer science</term>
                    <term>Cultural studies</term>
                    <term>Humanities computing</term>
                    
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div type="div1">
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <p>Data visualisation tools help users explore
                    connections in a dataset, discover new meanings and foster an understanding of a
                    domain. They are considered crucial epistemic aids <ref target="https://www.zotero.org/google-docs/?i8O73c">(Windhager, Salisu, and
                        Mayr 2019)</ref>, especially for Linked Data (LD) collections on the
                    Semantic Web. In recent years, semantic models have been subject to new
                    formalisations that can effectively convey complex information, including
                    meta-information (provenance, reliability) and contexts (concerning a graph or
                    subgraph), which are especially relevant in the cultural heritage (CH) domain.
                    Traditionally, some of the most common RDF data visualisation metaphors employ
                    graphs or tables. Most online tools support graphs, while most knowledge bases
                    (e.g. DBpedia, Wikidata, etc.) employ tables <ref target="https://www.zotero.org/google-docs/?MaBFlw">(Desimoni and Po
                        2019)</ref>. A pretty limited panorama in respect of the heterogeneity of CH
                    data. </p>
                <p>Nonetheless, in the humanities, uncertainty is an
                    integral part of the domain, and it is a scholarly appropriate habit to include
                    both preferred as well as contested assertions <ref target="https://www.zotero.org/google-docs/?pFcOCr">(Daquino et al. 2021;
                        Barabucci, Tomasi, and Vitali 2021)</ref>.  </p>
                <p>By introducing uncertainty and contextuality in the
                    data modelling pipeline, it becomes more evident that they are not data, they
                    are not natural representations of facts: the non-representational paradigm in
                    Drucker <ref target="https://www.zotero.org/google-docs/?okFrRz">(2011)</ref>
                    calls them <hi rend="italic">capta</hi>, stressing that data is always
                    interpreted, situated and constructed from a perspective. This paradigm shift
                    must also affect the traditional visualisation approaches for LD collections. </p>
                <p>Furthermore, most tools available for visualising
                    RDF data fail to consider the differences between end-users and employ identical
                    visualisation metaphors for their datasets regardless of their audiences' goals,
                    interests and proficiency. In particular, while those metaphors may be evident
                    to experienced RDF users, they may fall flat and sometimes be incomprehensible
                    to other users. </p>
                <p>Henceforth, we need new approaches for visualising
                    complex semantic data while considering the different competencies of intended
                    users: we must identify a broader set of evaluation metrics for this
                    purpose. </p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Some examples of novel visualisation models</hi></p>
                <p>The following are some examples of visualisation
                    models which have yet to be explored by the semantic community to tackle the
                    challenge of effectively communicating complex information to users. While we
                    have not implemented these visualisation models, they represent potential
                    approaches that could be applied to different domains and datasets.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Higraphs</hi>: Graphs are suited for power users: they offer an
                    overview of the graph content and are essential for discerning clusters of
                    linked data. Yet they offer little structures for complex concepts such as
                    provenance or uncertainty. Hypergraphs (or higraphs) use closed curves around
                    graphs, creating sets that can have, in turn, edges to each other or other
                    nodes. A graph can become a structure, delimited by its area, appropriate for
                    naming and labelling purposes <ref target="https://www.zotero.org/google-docs/?IMFax8">(Harel 1988)</ref>. This
                    graph formalism is particularly apt to describe Named Graphs and several
                    approaches to meta-information about entities and relationships (including RDF
                    Star and Nanopublications), efficiently conveying fairly complex information in
                    a clean visual format.  </p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic n="1001" width="13.604394444444445cm" height="6.603297222222222cm" url="Pictures/b50735460f8d59046b71d37563ae1dfc.png" rend="inline"/>
                    <head><hi rend="bold">Figure 1: </hi>Graph as displayed by isSemantic (left) and Higraph
                        (right).</head>
                </figure>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Maps</hi><hi rend="bold">: </hi>Domain experts and non-experienced users can benefit from
                    visual metaphors that stretch across different semantic fields while supporting
                    qualitative information that enables distortions, fuzziness or blurriness of an
                    otherwise plain surface. For example, <hi rend="italic">emotional maps</hi>
                    allow places to be shown as a space indicated by geographic coordinates and as
                    symbols where pivotal historical or fictional episodes took place, or authors
                    lived. At the same time, topographical representations can be distorted by
                    emotional factors concerning distance travelling <ref target="https://www.zotero.org/google-docs/?g2nY7M">(Drucker 2011)</ref>.
                    This creates a dialogue between the end-user and the system via a
                    non-representational approach. </p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic n="1002" width="11.77636388888889cm" height="9.774383333333333cm" url="Pictures/c88e1acdc7779275113ba8a9f645c1ed.jpg" rend="inline"/>
                    <head><hi rend="bold">Figure 2:</hi> Map with space warped by the experience of travel
                    so that the standard distances are distorted by effect of emotion and
                    infrastructure (Drucker, 2011). </head>
                </figure>
                <p>In particular, complex information such as
                    uncertainty can be conveyed in maps using techniques that alter existing
                    symbology through manipulating visual variables (e.g. colour) or adding new
                    objects (e.g. glyphs). Moreover, adjacent views between certain and uncertain
                    data and dynamic interfaces (e.g. popup) could be employed for the same purposes
                        <ref target="https://www.zotero.org/google-docs/?n5gdmt">(Kinkeldey,
                        MacEachren, and Schiewe 2014)</ref>. </p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Text</hi>: The text translation of RDF can be considered a type
                    of extractive visualisation, i.e. the transformation of content into another
                    form, which is more in the register of non-experienced users than traditional
                    RDF linearisations. Natural Language Generation techniques to transform RDF into
                    text have been explored since 2006 <ref target="https://www.zotero.org/google-docs/?Bw87Nh">(Sun and Mellish
                        2006)</ref>. The WebNLG+ challenge explored translation possibilities from
                    RDF datasets to text and vice-versa. However, so far, they have yet to be used
                    to represent RDF  <ref target="https://www.zotero.org/google-docs/?9Zi6cS">(Castro Ferreira et al. 2020)</ref>. Rendering RDF as text can be a new
                    medium for non-experienced users to perform CRUD operations on RDF databases and
                    provide a widely understandable visualisation. </p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic n="1003" width="14.536891666666667cm" height="4.0793944444444445cm" url="Pictures/f69e97d03e8e831a0579a29222782915.png" rend="inline"/>
                    <head><hi rend="bold">Figure 3:</hi> A subgraph regarding writer Olga Tokarczuk
                    (Q254032) from Wikidata, with a possible corresponding “visualisation” in
                    natural language. </head>
                </figure>
                <p>Text may be paired with other visualisations (e.g.
                    maps, timelines etc.) and question-answering interfaces. For example, any
                    uncertainty modelled in RDF can be shown in natural language texts through
                    adverbs, footnotes or multiple competing statements and represented according to
                    well-known linguistic patterns.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">User-oriented metrics for visualisation approaches</hi></p>
                <p>Complex information may increase the noise of a
                    visualisation in a given interface and affect the cognitive load of users based
                    on their competencies and tasks. Evaluation for information visualisation tools
                    is only partially suited to capture the conceptual impact of uncertainty-based
                    systems <ref target="https://www.zotero.org/google-docs/?IDAh7A">(Hullman
                        2020)</ref>. We propose an evaluation matrix based on four metrics,
                    considering users’ needs and motivations to measure the effectiveness of varying
                    visualisation approaches. These parameters reflect a more holistic and
                    user-centred approach to evaluating the effectiveness of information
                    visualisation tools. </p>
                <list type="unordered">
                    <item>Comprehension metric: verify if the tester can infer simple information
                        from the visualisation; targets any user. </item>
                    <item>Retention metric: verify if the tester can remember simple information
                        from the visualisation after a given time; targets any user.</item>
                    <item>Weirdness detection metric: verify if the tester can notice apparent
                        inconsistencies in the visualisation; targets data curators and
                        owners.</item>
                    <item>Drafting metric: verify if the tester can (rapidly) produce a record about
                        a new entity according to existing models and syntaxes of the current
                        visualisation; targets data curators and owners. </item>
                </list>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Conclusions</hi></p>
                <p>While new paradigms for RDF data modelling have
                    spread, there still needs to be more effective approaches and tools for
                    visualising complex, contextual and uncertain information. In this paper, we
                    proposed novel non-representational approaches to support complex information
                    visualisations while also trying to meet the needs of diverse user types.
                    Higraphs, emotional maps and textual representations expand existing visual
                    metaphors and standards while enabling novel ways of exploring datasets and
                    complex information. Non-representational approaches can be adopted without
                    disrupting standard visualisation by building onto them, especially to represent
                    uncertainty, provenance and contextual information. By incorporating a more
                    user-centred set of evaluation metrics, our proposed evaluation matrix provides
                    a more thorough quality assessment of visualisation interfaces and their
                    representativeness of complex, contextual, and uncertain information. Although
                    the proposed models have yet to be fully implemented, it is essential to move in
                    this direction, as a humanistic approach to data visualisation can provide
                    greater complexity and depth to users.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliogr">
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Barabucci, Gioele, Francesca Tomasi, and Fabio Vitali.
                        </author>2021. “Supporting Complexity and Conjectures in Cultural Heritage
                        Descriptions.” 104-115.
                        https://ntnuopen.ntnu.no/ntnu-xmlui/handle/11250/2736994.</bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Castro Ferreira, Thiago, Claire Gardent, Nikolai Ilinykh,
                            Chris van der Lee, Simon Mille, Diego Moussallem, and Anastasia
                            Shimorina, eds. </author>2020. Proceedings of the 3rd International Workshop
                        on Natural Language Generation from the Semantic Web (WebNLG+). Dublin,
                        Ireland (Virtual): Association for Computational Linguistics.
                        https://aclanthology.org/2020.webnlg-1.0.</bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Daquino, Marilena, Valentina Pasqual, Francesca Tomasi, and
                            Fabio Vitali. </author>2021. “Expressing Without Asserting in the
                        Arts.”</bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Desimoni, Federico, and Laura Po. </author>2019. Empirical
                        Evaluation of Linked Data Visualization Tools.</bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Drucker, Johanna. </author>2011. “Humanities Approaches to
                        Graphical Display.” Digital Humanities Quarterly 005 (1).</bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Harel, David. </author>1988. “On Visual Formalisms.”
                        Communications of the ACM 31 (5): 514–30.
                        https://doi.org/10.1145/42411.42414.</bibl>
                    <bibl><author>Hullman, Jessica. </author>2020. “Why Authors Don’t Visualize
                        Uncertainty.” IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics 26
                        (1): 130–39. https://doi.org/10.1109/TVCG.2019.2934287.</bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Kinkeldey, Christoph, Alan MacEachren, and Jochen Schiewe.
                        </author>2014. “How to Assess Visual Communication of Uncertainty? A Systematic
                        Review of Geospatial Uncertainty Visualisation User Studies.” The
                        Cartographic Journal 51 (September): 1743277414Y.0000000099.</bibl>
                    <bibl><author>Sun, Xiantang, and C. Mellish. </author>2006. “Domain
                        Independent Sentence Generation from RDF Representations for the Semantic
                        Web.”</bibl>
                    <bibl><author>Windhager, Florian, Saminu Salisu, and Eva Mayr.
                        </author>2019. “Exhibiting Uncertainty: Visualizing Data Quality Indicators for
                        Cultural Collections.” Informatics 6 (3): 29.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text></TEI>