<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_allPlus.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_allPlus.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Uncovering Principles of Sustainability in Literature</title>
                <author n="SchumacherMareikeKatharinaSCHUMACHER_Mareike_Katharina_Uncovering_Principles_of_Sustai.xml"><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-7952-4194" n="SchumacherMareikeKatharina">
                        <surname>Schumacher</surname>
                        <forename>Mareike Katharina</forename>
                    </persName><affiliation>Technical University of Darmstadt, Germany</affiliation><email>schumacher@linglit.tu-darmstadt.de</email></author><meeting><date from-iso="2023-07-10" to-iso="2023-07-14"/><title>Digital Humanities 2023. Collaboration as Opportunity</title><placeName>Graz</placeName></meeting>
                <author n="GiusEvelynSCHUMACHER_Mareike_Katharina_Uncovering_Principles_of_Sustai.xml"><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-8888-8419" n="GiusEvelyn">
                        <surname>Gius</surname>
                        <forename>Evelyn</forename>
                    </persName><affiliation>Technical University of Darmstadt, Germany</affiliation><email>Evelyn.gius@tu-darmstadt.de</email></author><meeting><date from-iso="2023-07-10" to-iso="2023-07-14"/><title>Digital Humanities 2023. Collaboration as Opportunity</title><placeName>Graz</placeName></meeting>
            </titleStmt>
            
            <publicationStmt><publisher><orgName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1137284463">Zentrum für Informationsmodellierung
                    - Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities, Karl-Franzens-Universität
                    Graz</orgName></publisher><date when="2023">2023</date><pubPlace>Graz</pubPlace><availability><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">Creative Commons BY
                    4.0</licence></availability></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title>Digital Humanities 2023: Book of Abstracts</title><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-9256-0958"><forename>Walter</forename><surname>Scholger</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>University of Graz</orgName><placeName>Graz, Austria</placeName></affiliation><email>walter.scholger@uni-graz.at</email></editor><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-1726-1712"><forename>Georg</forename><surname>Vogeler</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>University of Graz</orgName><placeName>Graz, Austria</placeName></affiliation><email>georg.vogeler@uni-graz.at</email></editor><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-3919-993X"><forename>Toma</forename><surname>Tasovac</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>Belgrade Center for Digital Humanities</orgName><placeName>Belgrade, Serbia</placeName></affiliation><email>ttasovac@humanistika.org</email></editor><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-4593-059X"><forename>Anne</forename><surname>Baillot</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>Le Mans Université</orgName><placeName>Le Mans, France</placeName></affiliation><email>anne.baillot@univ-lemans.fr</email></editor><respStmt><resp>Data Management</resp><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0009-0007-9019-8215"><forename>Elisabeth</forename><surname>Raunig</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Management</resp><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-1438-3236"><forename>Martina</forename><surname>Scholger</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Management</resp><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-9116-0402"><forename>Elisabeth</forename><surname>Steiner</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Curation</resp><persName><forename>Johanna</forename><surname>Ofenauer</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Curation</resp><persName><forename>Christina</forename><surname>Burgstaller</surname></persName></respStmt><idno type="DOI">10.5281/zenodo.7961822</idno></seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="DHCONVALIDATOR" version="1.22">
                    <label>DHConvalidator</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc><abstract><p>In this study, we are looking for early mentions of basic principles of sustainability in literary texts using machine learning. With a trained CRF-classifier we automatically annotated a corpus of about 70 novels from German romanticism and singled out passages with a high frequency of annotations, which we analysed in terms of a concept of sustainability. We thus test whether the application of machine learning used to operationalise high-frequency phenomena can also help uncover less frequent and highly interpretive aspects of narrative texts.</p></abstract><langUsage><language ident="en">English</language></langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="category">
                    <term>Paper</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="subcategory">
                    <term>Long Presentation</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="keywords">
                    <term>Sustainability</term>
                    <term>Computational Literary Studies</term>
                    <term>Romanticism</term>
                    <term>Machine Learning</term>
                    <term>Annotation</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="topics">
                    <term>cultural analytics</term>
                    <term>eco-criticism and environmental analysis</term>
                    <term>text mining and analysis</term>
                    <term>Cultural studies</term>
                    <term>Literary studies</term>
                    <term>Environmental</term>
                    <term>ocean</term>
                    <term>and waterway studies</term>
                    
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <p>The climate crisis and the potential way out of it through sustainability has been an
                important discourse in the last few years. In 1987 the Brundtland commission stated
                that “[s]ustainable development is a development that meets the needs of the present
                without compromising the ability of future generations to meet their own needs.”
                (cf. Brundtland 1987, 41) However first ideas of using nature in a sustainable way
                date back to 1713 when German forester Hannß Carl von Carlowitz wrote in
                Sylvicultura oeconomica that the forest should be used in a sustainable, i.e.
                renewable way (von Carlowitz 1713: 105). Our main interest lies in an (upcoming)
                cultural anchorage of principles of sustainability. Thus, in this study, we are
                looking for early mentions of basic principles of sustainability in literary texts
                using machine learning. We trained a conditional random fields classifier
                (CRF-classifier) to automatically detect, classify and annotate mentions of nature
                and nature-related phenomena in narratives (we used the StanfordNER implementation
                by Finkel et al.). Using this CRF-classifier we annotated a corpus of about 70
                novels from German romanticism <ref target="#SCHUMACHER_Mareike_Katharina_Uncovering_Principles_of_Sustai.xml_ftn1" n="1"/>. We chose romanticism as an epoch that a) temporarily closely followed the
                work of Carlowitz and b) is known to use references to nature in a high frequency
                (cf. e.g. Bühler 2016, 85, Ulshöfer 2010, Wanning 2005, Kremer 2003, Langer et al.
                2021). We then analysed passages with frequent references to nature in order to find
                hints on ideas of sustainability. We thus test whether the application of machine
                learning used to operationalise high-frequency phenomena can also help uncover less
                frequent and highly interpretive aspects of narrative texts. </p>
            <div type="div1">
                <head>Sustainability and Literary Studies</head>
                <p>With Ecocriticism (cf. e.g. Bühler 2016, Dürbeck and Stobbe 2015) and
                    econarratology (James 2015 and 2020) in literary studies there already has been
                    substantial work on descriptions and narrations of nature. As Bühler (2016)
                    shows this field of research has analysed representations of the interplay
                    between humanity and nature in various forms and on various research objects.
                    Recent computational approaches focus on biodiversity (Langer et al. 2021 and
                    2022) and the potential agency of nature in narratives (Gius and Uglanova
                    forthcoming). However, the environmental science concept of sustainability has
                    not yet been analysed in Computational Literary Studies. In our study we take
                    the first step in this direction, concentrating on two fundamental principles of
                    sustainability: </p>
                <p>1. the aforementioned renewability brought up by Carlowitz (2000 [1713]) and </p>
                <p>2. intergenerational equity which has been most prominently discussed by the
                    World Commission on Environment and Development (Brundtland 1987). </p>
            </div>
            <div type="div1">
                <head>Narrating Nature</head>
                <p>In order to single out literary texts dealing with ideas of sustainability we
                    first concentrate on descriptions of nature. To automate the annotation of
                    references to nature in literary texts, we developed a category system in a
                    bottom-up approach by annotating test texts. We thus came up with the seven
                    categories habitat, living nature, non-living nature, cultivated nature,
                    industrialised nature, weather, and natural catastrophes.</p>
                <p>We trained the CRF-classifier for these categories using an annotated training
                    corpus consisting of the first 10.000-token passages from 15 sample texts that
                    were made out to be especially rich in referencing nature by preceding research
                    (cf. Gius and Uglanova forthcoming). We then tested the CRF-classifier on
                    20.000-token initial passages taken from two texts. Overall, the CRF-classifier
                    reaches an accuracy of 0.69 (F1-Score). Using this CRF-classifier we
                    automatically annotated our corpus of about 70 romantic novels. Afterwards, we
                    analysed passages with a high density of references to nature annotated by the
                    CRF-classifier in order to find mentions of ideas of sustainability. </p>
                <p>In our corpus mentions of habitats are most frequent. The most common habitats
                    are the world, the sky, the earth, nature, the countryside, and the area. The
                    second most frequent category is the one of non-living nature containing e.g.
                    mentions of plants or stones. Animals as a form of living nature are reaching
                    the third highest frequency in the corpus. Relevant in this context is also that
                    habitats as a mostly untouched form of nature are much more frequently mentioned
                    than cultivated nature such as gardens or fields. One passage that shows traits
                    of the idea of renewability and thus can be read with regard to the first
                    principle of sustainability outlined above can be found in Dorothea Schlegel’s
                    Florentin (cf. Fig. 1).</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic n="1001" width="15.92cm" height="7.231944444444444cm" url="Pictures/4b6db73a8a94d10075ee0c9c00cf3b88.png" rend="inline"/>
                    <head>Fig. 1: Passage of Dorothea Schlegel’s Florentin showing a narrative
                        variation of the principle of renewability</head>
                </figure>
                <p>In this passage, the protagonist gets off his tired horse in order to spare its
                    power so that he can still use it as riding horse for a long time in the future.
                    This reasoning is similar to Carlowitz’s idea of renewable forestry. As can be
                    seen from Fig. 1 the CRF-classifier annotated references to living nature, i.e.
                    mentions of the horse of the protagonist, but in the passage which actually
                    shows traits of the principle of renewability (in bold letters) nothing is
                    annotated. Also, the principle of renewability is not mentioned very implicitely
                    in this passage. Based on these examples from our study, we developed a
                    heuristic to single out passages with a high frequency of automatically
                    classified annotations followed by passages without any of such annotations. We
                    then analysed those passages with regard to the two principles of sustainability
                    named above. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="div1">
                <head>Conclusion</head>
                <p>In our contribution, we will present deeper insights into this case study on
                    descriptions of nature and ideas of sustainability in literary texts from German
                    romanticism. We will show that the application of machine learning used to
                    operationalise high-frequency phenomena can also help uncover less frequent and
                    highly interpretive aspects of narrative texts such as mentions of ideas of
                    sustainability. We will thus make an attempt at a corpus-based approach to
                    sustainability in literature. With romanticism, we use a period in literary
                    history that developed in close temporal proximity to the first mention of the
                    term “sustainable” in a German written text. We see this as the first step in
                    the investigation of historical precursors of the concept of sustainability in
                    literary texts</p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="notes"><note n="1" xml:id="SCHUMACHER_Mareike_Katharina_Uncovering_Principles_of_Sustai.xml_ftn1">
                    We used the d-RoRo corpus of novels from German
                            romanticism, integrating into our research the core corpus and the
                            additional corpus I, so that we cover a timespan from 1790-1841 and
                            canonized as well as non-canonized texts and authors (cf. Schumacher,
                            Gius and Uglanova 2022).
                </note></div><div type="bibliogr">
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Brundtland, G.H. </author>(1987) Our common future. Oxford:
                        Oxford Univ. Press (Oxford paperbacks).</bibl>
                    <bibl><author>Bühler, B. </author>(2016) Ecocriticism. Eine Einführung.
                        Stuttgart: J.B. Metzler Verlag (SpringerLink: Bücher: Springer eBook
                        Collection). </bibl>
                    <bibl><author>Carlowitz, H.C. von </author>(2000) Sylvicultura oeconomica
                        Anweisung zur wilden Baum-Zucht. Reprint der Ausg. Leipzig: Braun, 1713. TU
                        Bergakademie (Veröffentlichungen der Bibliothek ‘Georgius Agricola’ der TU
                        Bergakademie Freiberg).</bibl>
                    <bibl><author>Finkel, J.R., Grenager, T. and Manning, C. </author>(2005)
                        ‘Incorporating Non-local Information into Information Extraction Systems by
                        Gibbs Sampling.’, Proceedings of the 43nd Annual Meeting of the Association
                        for Computational Linguistics, pp. 363–370.</bibl>
                    <bibl><author>Gius, E. and Uglanova, I. </author>(forthcoming) ‘Natur als
                        Agens. Versuch einer computationellen Betrachtung romantischer Texte’, in R.
                        Borgards, F. Middelhoff, and B. Thums (eds) Romantische Ökologien.
                        Stuttgart: J.B. Metzler (Neue Romantikforschung).</bibl>
                    <bibl><author>James, E. </author>(2015) The Storyworld Accord:
                        Econarratology and Postcolonial Narratives. Edited by J.E. Matz and D.
                        Herman. Lincoln: University of Nebraska Press. Available at:
                        https://doi.org/10.2307/j.ctt1d9898m.</bibl>
                    <bibl><author>James, E. </author>(2020) ‘The Value of “Old” Stories. A
                        Response to Marco Caracciolo’s “Negotiating Stories in the Anthropocene”’,
                        DIEGESIS, 9(2). Available at:
                        https://www.diegesis.uni-wuppertal.de/index.php/diegesis/article/view/385
                        (Accessed: 14 September 2022).</bibl>
                    <bibl><author>Kremer, D. </author>(2003) Romantik. 2., überarb. und
                        aktualisierte Aufl. Stuttgart: J.B. Metzler (Lehrbuch Germanistik).
                        Available at: https://swbplus.bsz-bw.de/bsz105570184cov.jpg.</bibl>
                    <bibl><author>Langer, L. et al. </author>(2021) ‘The rise and fall of
                        biodiversity in literature: A comprehensive quantification of historical
                        changes in the use of vernacular labels for biological taxa in Western
                        creative literature’, People and Nature, 3(5), pp. 1093–1109. Available at:
                        https://doi.org/10.1002/pan3.10256.</bibl>
                    <bibl><author>Langer, L. et al. </author>(2022) ‘Digital Environmental
                        Humanities - Zum Potential von “Computational and Literary Biodiversity
                        Studies” (CoLiBiS)’. Available at:
                        https://doi.org/10.5281/ZENODO.6327940.</bibl>
                    <bibl><author>Schumacher, M., Uglanova, I., &amp; Gius, E. </author>(2022).
                        d-Romane-Romantik (d-RoRo) (1.0) [Data set]. Zenodo.
                        https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.7223544</bibl>
                    <bibl><author>Ulshöfer, R. </author>(2010) Die Literatur des 18.
                        Jahrhunderts und der Romantik in neuer Sicht der Anstoß der
                        Naturwissenschaften des 17./18. Jahrhunderts zur Entstehung der Literatur
                        der Moderne und zum Entwurf eines Weltfriedensplans. Würzburg: Königshausen
                        &amp; Neumann. Available at:
                        http://deposit.d-nb.de/cgi-bin/dokserv?id=3200353&amp;prov=M&amp;dok_var=1&amp;dok_ext=htm.</bibl>
                    <bibl><author>Wanning, B. </author>(2005) Die Fiktionalität der Natur:
                        Studien zum Naturbegriff in Erzähltexten der Romantik und des Realismus. 1.
                        Aufl. Berlin: Weidler (Natur, Literatur, Ökologie, Bd. 2).</bibl>
                    <bibl><author>Dürbeck, G. and Stobbe, U. </author>(2015) Ecocriticism.
                        Weimar, Köln: Böhlau Verlag.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text></TEI>