<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_allPlus.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_allPlus.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Workshop CATMA featuring GitMA and Vis-A-Vis</title>
                <author n="SchumacherMareikeKatharinaSCHUMACHER_Mareike_Katharina_Workshop_CATMA_featuring_GitMA_.xml"><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-7952-4194" n="SchumacherMareikeKatharina">
                        <surname>Schumacher</surname>
                        <forename>Mareike Katharina</forename>
                    </persName><affiliation>Technical University of Darmstadt, Germany</affiliation><email>schumacher@linglit.tu-darmstadt.de</email></author><meeting><date from-iso="2023-07-10" to-iso="2023-07-14"/><title>Digital Humanities 2023. Collaboration as Opportunity</title><placeName>Graz</placeName></meeting>
                <author n="GerstorferDominikSCHUMACHER_Mareike_Katharina_Workshop_CATMA_featuring_GitMA_.xml"><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-8095-2540" n="GerstorferDominik">
                        <surname>Gerstorfer</surname>
                        <forename>Dominik</forename>
                    </persName><affiliation>Technical University of Darmstadt, Germany</affiliation><email>dominik.gerstorfer@tu-darmstadt.de</email></author><meeting><date from-iso="2023-07-10" to-iso="2023-07-14"/><title>Digital Humanities 2023. Collaboration as Opportunity</title><placeName>Graz</placeName></meeting>
                <author n="GiusEvelynSCHUMACHER_Mareike_Katharina_Workshop_CATMA_featuring_GitMA_.xml"><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-8888-8419" n="GiusEvelyn">
                        <surname>Gius</surname>
                        <forename>Evelyn</forename>
                    </persName><affiliation>Technical University of Darmstadt, Germany</affiliation><email>evelyn.gius@tu-darmstadt.de</email></author><meeting><date from-iso="2023-07-10" to-iso="2023-07-14"/><title>Digital Humanities 2023. Collaboration as Opportunity</title><placeName>Graz</placeName></meeting>
                <author n="MeisterMalteSCHUMACHER_Mareike_Katharina_Workshop_CATMA_featuring_GitMA_.xml"><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-9670-3573" n="MeisterMalte">
                        <surname>Meister</surname>
                        <forename>Malte</forename>
                    </persName><affiliation>Technical University of Darmstadt, Germany</affiliation><email>malte.meister@tu-darmstadt.de</email></author><meeting><date from-iso="2023-07-10" to-iso="2023-07-14"/><title>Digital Humanities 2023. Collaboration as Opportunity</title><placeName>Graz</placeName></meeting>
                <author n="MnzManorOphirSCHUMACHER_Mareike_Katharina_Workshop_CATMA_featuring_GitMA_.xml"><persName n="MnzManorOphir">
                        <surname>Münz-Manor</surname>
                        <forename>Ophir</forename>
                    </persName><affiliation>The Open University of Israel</affiliation><email>ophirmm@openu.ac.il</email></author><meeting><date from-iso="2023-07-10" to-iso="2023-07-14"/><title>Digital Humanities 2023. Collaboration as Opportunity</title><placeName>Graz</placeName></meeting>
            </titleStmt>
            
            <publicationStmt><publisher><orgName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1137284463">Zentrum für Informationsmodellierung
                    - Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities, Karl-Franzens-Universität
                    Graz</orgName></publisher><date when="2023">2023</date><pubPlace>Graz</pubPlace><availability><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">Creative Commons BY
                    4.0</licence></availability></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title>Digital Humanities 2023: Book of Abstracts</title><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-9256-0958"><forename>Walter</forename><surname>Scholger</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>University of Graz</orgName><placeName>Graz, Austria</placeName></affiliation><email>walter.scholger@uni-graz.at</email></editor><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-1726-1712"><forename>Georg</forename><surname>Vogeler</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>University of Graz</orgName><placeName>Graz, Austria</placeName></affiliation><email>georg.vogeler@uni-graz.at</email></editor><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-3919-993X"><forename>Toma</forename><surname>Tasovac</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>Belgrade Center for Digital Humanities</orgName><placeName>Belgrade, Serbia</placeName></affiliation><email>ttasovac@humanistika.org</email></editor><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-4593-059X"><forename>Anne</forename><surname>Baillot</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>Le Mans Université</orgName><placeName>Le Mans, France</placeName></affiliation><email>anne.baillot@univ-lemans.fr</email></editor><respStmt><resp>Data Management</resp><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0009-0007-9019-8215"><forename>Elisabeth</forename><surname>Raunig</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Management</resp><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-1438-3236"><forename>Martina</forename><surname>Scholger</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Management</resp><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-9116-0402"><forename>Elisabeth</forename><surname>Steiner</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Curation</resp><persName><forename>Johanna</forename><surname>Ofenauer</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Curation</resp><persName><forename>Christina</forename><surname>Burgstaller</surname></persName></respStmt><idno type="DOI">10.5281/zenodo.7961822</idno></seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="DHCONVALIDATOR" version="1.22">
                    <label>DHConvalidator</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc><abstract><p>This CATMA (Computer Assisted Text Markup and Analysis) workshop is intended for users with some preliminary experience with manual digital annotation who (want to) operate with larger amounts of annotation data in the context of their own work or research projects. It will demonstrate the basic features of CATMA and how annotation data can be processed using either the Python package GitMA (Vauth et al. 2021) or the web-based visualization tool vis-À-vis (Münz-Manor et al. 2020). The workshop will provide answers to questions like: How do I access my CATMA annotation data via GitMA? How do I calculate the agreement between multiple annotators? How do I generate advanced visualizations of the texts and annotations in vis-À-vis? How do I visualize collaboratively created annotation data stored in multiple collections?</p></abstract><langUsage><language ident="en">English</language></langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="category">
                    <term>Paper</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="subcategory">
                    <term>Pre-Conference Workshop and Tutorial</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="keywords">
                    <term>Annotation</term>
                    <term>collaboration</term>
                    <term>inter-annotator-agreement</term>
                    <term>visualization</term>
                    <term>analysis</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="topics">
                    <term>annotation structures</term>
                    <term>systems</term>
                    <term>and methods</term>
                    <term>Cultural studies</term>
                    <term>History</term>
                    <term>Literary studies</term>
                    
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <p>This CATMA (Computer Assisted Text Markup and Analysis) workshop is intended for
                users with some preliminary experience with manual digital annotation who (want to)
                operate with larger amounts of annotation data in the context of their own work or
                research projects. It will demonstrate the basic features of CATMA and how
                annotation data can be processed using either the Python package GitMA (Vauth et al.
                2021) or the web-based visualization tool vis-À-vis (Münz-Manor et al. 2020). The
                workshop will provide answers to questions like: How do I access my CATMA annotation
                data via GitMA? How do I calculate the agreement between multiple annotators? How do
                I generate advanced visualizations of the texts and annotations in vis-À-vis? How do
                I visualize collaboratively created annotation data stored in multiple
                collections?</p>
            <div type="div1">
                <head>Annotation in CATMA</head>
                <p>Annotation is a core cultural and research practice that has been practiced
                    non-digitally for a very long time (cf. Moulin 2010) before being transferred to
                    the digital in the context of the Digital Humanities. Text markup and
                    enrichment, free-text annotation, and taxonomy-based annotation are forms of
                    annotation that overlap to some extent (cf. Jacke 2018, § 9). All of these forms
                    are digitally supported by CATMA. CATMA (Gius et al. 2022) is a web-based
                    collaborative text annotation and analysis platform that has been in development
                    since 2008. With the release of CATMA 6 in 2019, a Git-based backend was
                    introduced for the platform. GitMA builds on top of that to facilitate access to
                    and further processing of annotation data. For many projects already using CATMA
                    at an advanced level, as well as for people with experience using Git and a
                    basic knowledge of Python, this opens up a number of new possibilities for
                    working on and with annotations. The most important of these will be introduced
                    during this workshop.</p>
                <p>In CATMA, with the help of self-created tagsets or tagsets provided on the
                    forTEXT.net platform (e.g. Flüh 2020), taxonomy-based annotation can be
                    performed individually or in teams in a project-centered manner. To begin your
                    work with CATMA, you create a project with any number of documents to be
                    analyzed and any number of team members who want to work on them. You can make
                    single and multiple, overlapping or even contradictory annotations in CATMA. You
                    can integrate open questions, interpretation approaches that have not been
                    thought through to the end, or even exchanges with other team members into your
                    annotation process by using annotations or the comment function. Both
                    annotations and comments can be searched, tabulated, or visualized via CATMA's
                    analysis functions.</p>
                <p>We will introduce the functionalities of the CATMA GUI in the first part of the
                    workshop.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic n="1001" width="15.92cm" height="17.074444444444445cm" url="Pictures/6909951b3069027742de7b125ca54789.png" rend="inline"/>
                    <head>Figure 1: Workflow for annotation evaluation and revision with the CATMA backend,
                    taught during the workshop.</head>
                </figure>
            </div>
            <div type="div1">
                <head>Processing annotations with GitMA</head>
                <p>Although the scope of what can be achieved with the CATMA GUI is quite large, the
                    introduction of the Git-based backend makes the tool even more interesting for
                    Digital Humanities practices of text analysis. The undogmatic access that was
                    previously only provided to annotations and annotation taxonomies now extends to
                    annotation data and its further processing (see Fig. 1). </p>
                <p>A low barrier to entry and proximity to the established (analog) methods in the
                    humanities remain central principles implemented in CATMA (cf. Schumacher and
                    Gius 2022). In addition to the possibility for text analysis using diverse
                    methods or theories of interpretation (cf. Piez 2010), adherence to best
                    practices and standards developed within the Digital Humanities community is
                    important. "GitMA", the combination of CATMA GUI functionalities with direct
                    data access via Git, enables both. For example, the data created in the
                    annotation process can be evaluated for inter-annotator-agreement. It is
                    possible to specify one of the annotators as the 'silver standard' and measure
                    annotations of the others against it. The detected disagreement can form the
                    basis of a disagreement tagset, which can also be fed back into the frontend of
                    the CATMA GUI via the backend (see Fig. 1). The same applies to the passages
                    showing disagreement, which in turn can themselves be represented by annotations
                    in the GUI. In addition, this workflow enables the creation of gold annotations
                    (cf. Wissler et al. 2014). Both workflows, inter-annotator-agreement evaluation
                    and gold standard creation, will be shown during the second part of the
                    workshop.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="div1">
                <head>Visualizing annotations with vis-À-vis</head>
                <p>While CATMA offers basic visualizations of the annotations created within the
                    system, vis-À-vis is a comprehensive visualization tool designed to assist
                    scholars in recognizing patterns in annotated texts. vis-À-vis automatically
                    imports the tagged corpora from CATMA, (re)presents them in various graphs and
                    charts, provides comparative graphical tools for grouping the texts, and offers
                    aggregative tools for inter- and intra-corpora relations. vis-À-vis offers five
                    visualization possibilities: Small multiple distribution charts of annotation
                    categories within a text, an aggregated Stacked Area chart, a Sunburst chart
                    showing the proportions and quantities associated with each tag in the text, a
                    force-directed network of annotation categories and a bubble visualization. In
                    addition, a dynamic visualization of the logical structure of a tagset as well
                    as its manifestations in specific annotated texts is offered. </p>
                <p>The vis-À-vis backend provides easy connectivity with CATMA, connecting it to its
                    GitLab backend through user-provided API keys. The user is prompted for a key
                    and receives information on all of the user’s projects from CATMA. Projects can
                    then be imported, or updated if they were imported previously. vis-À-vis uses a
                    similar data model to CATMA, although compartmentalized: Users have Projects,
                    which are composed of Texts and Annotations. Annotations associate parts of a
                    text with a Tag, and tags belong to a Tagset. The last part of the workshop will
                    demonstrate the possibilities of visualizing annotations with vis-À-vis.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="div1">
                <head>Format and workshop schedule</head>
                <p>The workshop will be offered as a half-day hands-on tutorial (four hours). With
                    our group of experienced instructors, we will be able to provide close
                    assistance to the participants. </p>
                <div type="div2">
                    <head>Procedure:</head>
                    <list type="unordered">
                        <item>CATMA (90 minutes)</item>
                        <item>Short introduction to the CATMA frontend</item>
                        <item>Create tagsets</item>
                        <item>Annotate documents </item>
                        <item>Analyze annotations</item>
                    </list>
                    <p>Break (20 minutes)</p>
                    <list type="unordered">
                        <item>Access to annotation data via GitMA (55 minutes)</item>
                        <item>Access to annotation collections, documents and tagsets</item>
                        <item>Exploratory annotation evaluations</item>
                        <item>Visualizing annotation data</item>
                        <item>Inter-annotator-agreement, Silver &amp; Gold Standard</item>
                    </list>
                    <p>Break (20 minutes)</p>
                    <list type="unordered">
                        <item>Visualizations of annotation data with vis-À-vis (55 minutes)</item>
                    </list>
                </div>
                <div type="div2">
                    <head>Target audience</head>
                    <p>Users who manage annotations with CATMA in research projects or in teaching
                        situations, as well as anyone who needs a fast workflow between manual
                        annotation or annotation editing and annotation evaluation. Users without
                        prior CATMA experience are welcome, though we would kindly ask them to
                        prepare by working through the manual annotation tutorial at
                        https://catma.de/how-to/tutorials/manual-annotation/ in advance. </p>
                </div>
                <div type="div2">
                    <head>Number of possible participants</head>
                    <p>50</p>
                </div>
                <div type="div2">
                    <head>Technical requirements</head>
                    <p>To prepare for the workshop, participants should have already created a CATMA
                        account (at https://app.catma.de/catma/). The required pre-installations of
                        Git, Anaconda and GitMA (as well as its dependencies) can be avoided by
                        using a provided Docker image. Participants should have Docker Desktop
                        installed on their own laptop (touch devices are not supported) and bring it
                        to the workshop.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="div2">
                    <head>Required previous knowledge</head>
                    <p>Participants should have basic knowledge of CATMA, Python, and Jupyter
                        Notebooks.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="div2">
                    <head>Contributors</head>
                    <div type="div3">
                        <head>Dominik Gerstorfer</head>
                        <p>Technical University of Darmstadt, Institute of Linguistics and
                            Literature, Residenzschloss 1, 64283 Darmstadt, Germany</p>
                        <p>Dominik Gerstorfer is doing his PhD on "Philosophical Issues in the
                            Digital Humanities" at the University of Stuttgart. He is currently
                            working in the KatKit project, and previously worked in the DFG project
                            forTEXT in Darmstadt and in the Digital Humanities project CRETA in
                            Stuttgart. Dominik studied philosophy, political science, and sociology
                            (M.A.) at the University of Tübingen. His research interests lie in the
                            areas of philosophy of science, formal methods, and argumentation
                            analysis. In the context of KatKit and forTEXT, Dominik is working on
                            intertextuality, ontologies, and the development of category systems,
                            among other topics.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="div3">
                        <head>Evelyn Gius</head>
                        <p>Technical University of Darmstadt, Institute of Linguistics and
                            Literature, Residenzschloss 1, 64283 Darmstadt, Germany</p>
                        <p>Evelyn Gius is a professor for digital philology and modern German
                            literature at Technical University of Darmstadt. She received her PhD
                            from the University of Hamburg with a thesis on the narrative structure
                            of conflict narration. Her research is focused on manual annotation,
                            operationalization, narrative theory, segmentation and conflicts. She is
                            the PI of several Digital Humanities projects (EvENT, KatKit, CATMA,
                            forTEXT) and serves as chair of the Digital Humanities association in
                            the German-speaking area (DHd), co-editor of the Journal of
                            Computational Literary Studies (JCLS) and co-editor of the book series
                            “Digitale Literaturwissenschaft” (Digital Literary Studies).</p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="div3">
                        <head>Malte Meister</head>
                        <p>Technical University of Darmstadt, Institute of Linguistics and Literary
                            Studies, Residenzschloss 1, 64283 Darmstadt, Germany</p>
                        <p>Malte Meister earned his computer science degree (B.Sc.) in Cape Town in
                            2009. As part of the final project for his diploma, he was commissioned
                            to create the text annotation and analysis tool CATMA, for the
                            University of Hamburg. He contributed to the team working on CATMA until
                            early 2010, before focusing on his career in the private sector. After
                            more than ten years of professional experience as a software developer
                            and team leader, he decided to rejoin the CATMA development team. He has
                            been a technical staff member at the TU Darmstadt since 2021, where he
                            is mainly involved in the operation and further development of CATMA and
                            related systems as part of forTEXT.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="div3">
                        <head>Ophir Münz-Manor</head>
                        <p>The Open University of Israel, Department of History, Philosophy and
                            Judaic Studies, 1 University Road, Ra’anana 4353701, Israel</p>
                        <p>Ophir Münz-Manor is associate professor of Rabbinic Culture and a
                            specialist in Jewish liturgy and liturgical poetry from Late Antiquity
                            and the early Middle Ages. His studies focus on the intersections with
                            contemporary Christian texts as well as questions of ritual, performance
                            and gender in late antique Near Eastern cultures. In recent years, Prof.
                            Münz-Manor has embarked on several projects that combine traditional
                            literary analysis with quantitative and computerized methods from the
                            realm of Computational Literary Studies. </p>
                        <p>He is the PI of two recent Digital Humanities projects (Critique of Pure
                            Digital Knowledge and Algorithmic Detections of Metaphors in Pre-Modern
                            Hebrew Poetry) and the creator of vis-À-vis. Recently, he edited a
                            special issue of Jewish Studies Quarterly published by Mohr Siebeck on
                            Digital Humanities and Jewish Studies and published (together with Itay
                            Marienberg-Milikowsky) the first Hebrew annotated reader of fundamental
                            essays in the realm of DH, translated from English. </p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="div3">
                        <head>Mareike Schumacher</head>
                        <p>University of Regensburg, Institute of Language, Literature and Culture,
                            Universitätsstraße 31, 93053 Regensburg, Germany</p>
                        <p>Mareike Schumacher is Juniorprofessor of Digital Humanities. Before she
                            coordinated the DFG project forTEXT (https://fortext.net), in which, in
                            addition to the dissemination of digital routines, resources and tools
                            to the more traditional disciplines, the further development of CATMA
                            plays an essential role. She handed in her PhD-thesis about “Place and
                            Space in the Novel. A contribution to Computational Literary Studies” in
                            2021. She is particularly interested in distant reading methods
                            (including named entity recognition or stylometry), digital humanities
                            theory, and the connection between digital methods and theory-based
                            literary and cultural studies research. </p>
                    </div>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliogr">
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Flüh, Marie. </author>
                        2020. „Emotionsanalyse“. In forTEXT.
                            https://fortext.net/ressourcen/tagsets/emotionsanalyse.</bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Gius, Evelyn, Jan Christoph Meister, Malte Meister, Marco
                            Petris, Christian Bruck, Janina Jacke, Mareike Schumacher, Dominik
                            Gerstorfer, Marie Flüh, and Jan Horstmann. </author>
                        2021. “CATMA 6 (Version 6.5)”. Zenodo. DOI: 10.5281/zenodo.1470118. URL:
                            https://catma.de/</bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Münz-Manor, O. et al. </author>
                        (2020) ‘ViS-Á-ViS : Detecting Similar Patterns in Annotated Literary
                            Text’. Available at:
                        https://doi.org/10.48550/ARXIV.2009.02063.</bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Piez, Wendell.</author>
                        2010. „Towards Hermeneutic Markup. An Architectural Outline“. In Digital
                            Humanities 2010. Conference Abstracts, 202–5. London.
                            http://dh2010.cch.kcl.ac.uk/academic-programme/abstracts/papers/html/ab-743.html.</bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Schumacher, Mareike and Evelyn Gius. </author>
                        2022. ‘forTEXT.net – Literatur digital erforschen’, Mitteilungen des
                            Deutschen Germanistenverbandes, 69(2), pp. 121–126. Available at:
                            https://doi.org/10.14220/mdge.2022.69.2.121.</bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Michael Vauth, Malte Meister, Hans Ole Hatzel, Dominik
                            Gerstorfer, and Evelyn Gius. </author>
                        (2022). GitMA (1.4.9). Zenodo.
                            https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.6330464</bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Wissler, Lars, Mohammed Almashraee, Dagmar Monett, and
                            Adrian Paschke. </author>
                        2014. „The Gold Standard in Corpus Annotation“.
                            https://doi.org/10.13140/2.1.4316.3523.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text></TEI>