<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_allPlus.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_allPlus.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Collaborative Visualizations and Visualizing Collaboration</title>
                <author n="SutherlandSerenitySUTHERLAND_Serenity_Collaborative_Visualizations_and_Visuali.xml"><persName n="SutherlandSerenity">
                        <surname>Sutherland</surname>
                        <forename>Serenity</forename>
                    </persName><affiliation>SUNY Oswego, United States of America</affiliation><email>serenity.sutherland@oswego.edu</email></author><meeting><date from-iso="2023-07-10" to-iso="2023-07-14"/><title>Digital Humanities 2023. Collaboration as Opportunity</title><placeName>Graz</placeName></meeting>
                <author n="NelsonDavidRagnarSUTHERLAND_Serenity_Collaborative_Visualizations_and_Visuali.xml"><persName n="NelsonDavidRagnar">
                        <surname>Nelson</surname>
                        <forename>David Ragnar</forename>
                    </persName><affiliation>American Philosophical Society, United States of
                        America</affiliation><email>dnelson@amphilsoc.org</email></author><meeting><date from-iso="2023-07-10" to-iso="2023-07-14"/><title>Digital Humanities 2023. Collaboration as Opportunity</title><placeName>Graz</placeName></meeting>
                <author n="OhgeChristopherSUTHERLAND_Serenity_Collaborative_Visualizations_and_Visuali.xml"><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-6410-8692" n="OhgeChristopher">
                        <surname>Ohge</surname>
                        <forename>Christopher</forename>
                    </persName><affiliation>School of Advanced Study, University of London</affiliation><email>christopher.ohge@sas.ac.uk</email></author><meeting><date from-iso="2023-07-10" to-iso="2023-07-14"/><title>Digital Humanities 2023. Collaboration as Opportunity</title><placeName>Graz</placeName></meeting>
                <author n="BernardiJoanneSUTHERLAND_Serenity_Collaborative_Visualizations_and_Visuali.xml"><persName n="BernardiJoanne">
                        <surname>Bernardi</surname>
                        <forename>Joanne</forename>
                    </persName><affiliation>University of Rochester, United States of America</affiliation><email>joanne.bernardi@rochester.edu</email></author><meeting><date from-iso="2023-07-10" to-iso="2023-07-14"/><title>Digital Humanities 2023. Collaboration as Opportunity</title><placeName>Graz</placeName></meeting>
                <author n="HaakCandisSUTHERLAND_Serenity_Collaborative_Visualizations_and_Visuali.xml"><persName n="HaakCandis">
                        <surname>Haak</surname>
                        <forename>Candis</forename>
                    </persName><affiliation>SUNY Oswego, United States of America</affiliation><email>candis.haak@oswego.edu</email></author><meeting><date from-iso="2023-07-10" to-iso="2023-07-14"/><title>Digital Humanities 2023. Collaboration as Opportunity</title><placeName>Graz</placeName></meeting>
            </titleStmt>
            
            <publicationStmt><publisher><orgName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1137284463">Zentrum für Informationsmodellierung
                    - Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities, Karl-Franzens-Universität
                    Graz</orgName></publisher><date when="2023">2023</date><pubPlace>Graz</pubPlace><availability><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">Creative Commons BY
                    4.0</licence></availability></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title>Digital Humanities 2023: Book of Abstracts</title><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-9256-0958"><forename>Walter</forename><surname>Scholger</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>University of Graz</orgName><placeName>Graz, Austria</placeName></affiliation><email>walter.scholger@uni-graz.at</email></editor><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-1726-1712"><forename>Georg</forename><surname>Vogeler</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>University of Graz</orgName><placeName>Graz, Austria</placeName></affiliation><email>georg.vogeler@uni-graz.at</email></editor><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-3919-993X"><forename>Toma</forename><surname>Tasovac</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>Belgrade Center for Digital Humanities</orgName><placeName>Belgrade, Serbia</placeName></affiliation><email>ttasovac@humanistika.org</email></editor><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-4593-059X"><forename>Anne</forename><surname>Baillot</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>Le Mans Université</orgName><placeName>Le Mans, France</placeName></affiliation><email>anne.baillot@univ-lemans.fr</email></editor><respStmt><resp>Data Management</resp><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0009-0007-9019-8215"><forename>Elisabeth</forename><surname>Raunig</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Management</resp><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-1438-3236"><forename>Martina</forename><surname>Scholger</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Management</resp><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-9116-0402"><forename>Elisabeth</forename><surname>Steiner</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Curation</resp><persName><forename>Johanna</forename><surname>Ofenauer</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Curation</resp><persName><forename>Christina</forename><surname>Burgstaller</surname></persName></respStmt><idno type="DOI">10.5281/zenodo.7961822</idno></seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="DHCONVALIDATOR" version="1.22">
                    <label>DHConvalidator</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc><abstract><p>This panel examine four different approaches to creating digital visualizations: database-driven networks, encoded TEI network analysis using IIIF, a material culture digital archive, and spatial analysis using GIS. Presentations will outline the details of each project and the collaborations necessary for each methodological appraoch to creating visualizations.</p></abstract><langUsage><language ident="en">English</language></langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="category">
                    <term>Paper</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="subcategory">
                    <term>Panel</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="keywords">
                    <term>visualization</term>
                    <term>networks</term>
                    <term>material culture</term>
                    <term>spatial analysis</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="topics">
                    <term>database creation</term>
                    <term>management</term>
                    <term>and analysis</term>
                    <term>network analysis and graphs theory and application</term>
                    <term>spatial &amp; spatio-temporal analysis</term>
                    <term>modeling and visualization</term>
                    <term>text encoding and markup language creation</term>
                    <term>deployment</term>
                    <term>and analysis</term>
                    <term>Gender and sexuality studies</term>
                    <term>History of science</term>
                    <term>Media studies</term>
                    <term>South Asian studies</term>
                    
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div type="div1">
                <head>Panel Description</head>
                <p>Given the multimodality of digital research, many digital humanists use
                    visualization in some form in their work. These visual outputs are diverse in
                    form, and can range from network visualizations, curated digital exhibitions,
                    spatial analysis, and of course the website infrastructure that houses our
                    products. These visualizations are also nearly always interdisciplinary: no
                    single person can scope and design our visual products, so
                    visualizations require collaboration across disciplines to create and sustain.
                    Additionally, these projects are often inter-institutional, as Sutherland and
                    Nelson demonstrate with their collaboration at the American Philosophical
                    Society and Ohge with his collaboration with the John Rylands Library and
                    Research Institute, and even transnational, as demonstrated by the work of
                    Bernardi with her Japanese material culture archive and Haak with her work on
                    spatial analysis in Southern India with GIS and Google Street View. The
                    visualizations proposed for this panel also reflect collaborations that happened
                    in their contextual moments: Sutherland and Nelson’s network analysis of the
                    lineages and connections between women of science demonstrate how crucial
                    publication and lab time with other scientist were to building women scientists’
                    careers, and it was often women themselves who created and sustained these
                    networks. Ohge’s network visualization portrays similar types of collaboration
                    among anti-slavery print culture in 1830s England. </p>
                <p>Condensing data into visual forms is one key way to engage the public, whether in
                    a museum, stand-alone digital exhibit, or online archive. But not all
                    visualizations have the same public. Indeed, the setting and intended audience
                    influence the final product. For example, a museum exhibit demonstrating a
                    visualization about women in science to people of all ages (Nelson and
                    Sutherland’s project) will have different requirements than a material culture
                    digital archive that’s full of tactile objects related to Japanese culture that
                    can only be rendered in 2D (Bernardi’s project). Furthermore, some
                    visualizations address sacred spaces that have significant religious meaning to
                    some and may require sensitivity to how the visualization portrays the space
                    (Haak’s spatial analysis). </p>
                <p>Despite their utility in engaging the public, the methodologies of data
                    visualization remain controversial – and depending on usage, limited. At worst,
                    they can be unreadable, and sometimes they oversimplify complex information.
                    Scholars have referred to visualizations as “sandcastles” - “tailored, unique,
                    often stunning yet also transient and unstable interactive visualizations” (
                        <ref target="https://academic.oup.com/dsh/article/34/Supplement_1/i80/5146726?login=true#190967719">Hinrichs, et. al</ref>., 2019); static portrayals of dynamic data that potentially oversimplify
                    ( <ref target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/5/1/000091/000091.html">Drucker</ref>, 2011); and rhetorical framing devices that steer a viewer’s
                    interpretation ( <ref target="https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/abstract/document/6064988">Hullman</ref><ref target="https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/abstract/document/6064988"> / </ref><ref target="https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/abstract/document/6064988">Diakopolous</ref>, 2011). In this panel, presenters will use their own visualizations that
                    rely on a variety of methods, collaborations and praxis to interrogate how
                    visualizations contribute to increased collaboration and discovery within the
                    humanities at large. While acknowledging the media affordances and limitations
                    of visualizations, the panel will present how their own approach to
                    visualization through collaboration has helped to craft meaningful narratives
                    about their research and reach a wider public.  </p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic n="1001" width="16.002cm" height="11.516430555555555cm" url="Pictures/aa49aec26dab698398544fd29b465f8e.png" rend="inline"/>
                   
                    <lb/>
                </figure>
                <div>
                    <head>Individual Papers</head>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Visualizing the Network of Women in Science at the American
                            Philosophical Society Archives</hi></p>
                    <p><hi rend="italic">Presenters: David Ragnar Nelson, American Philosophical
                            Society and Serenity Sutherland, SUNY Oswego</hi></p>
                    <p>The American Philosophical Society contains substantial archival records
                        related to women and gender in science. Creating a network visualization
                        with this material demonstrates the lineages formed between women scientists
                        in the 19th through 20th centuries. Using the collections of Florence Sabin,
                        Florence Seibert, Barbara McClintock, Rose Mooney Slater, and Mildred Cohn
                        the network visualization demonstrates nearly 500 relationships between
                        women of science that revolve around correspondence, writing letters of
                        recommendation, publishing together, studying and collaborating with, and
                        working in the same lab and institution. The presentation will portray the
                        visualization as a praxis site of collaboration, public engagement, and
                        scholarship while also interrogating the limitations of this specific
                        network visualization. </p>
                    <p>The ultimate goal of the visualization is to contribute to ongoing
                        discussions about women’s scientific accomplishments. Each entry in the
                        visualization is accompanied by a short, detailed, individual biography
                        (about the length of a wiki entry). Many of the entries are of women
                        scientists not found in scholarship and online wikipedias. The individual
                        biographies help the project move beyond the “heroine” model of women in
                        science by looking at women who are often not considered in major
                        biographies, but who were nonetheless supported by high-profile women with
                        letters of recommendation or unofficial mentorships.  The project was
                        produced in conjunction with a public exhibition on women in science in the
                        APS museum and offers an opportunity to reflect on the various affordances
                        and limitations of visualizations for different audiences. The paper will
                        comment on the forms of collaboration between librarians, archivists,
                        education specialists, developers and researchers necessary to achieve
                        this.</p>
                   
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Visualizing the Literary Collaborations of Women
                            Anti-Slavery Activists in Nineteenth-Century Britain: Genetic Pathways
                            and Social Network Analysis</hi></p>
                    <p><hi rend="italic">Christopher Ohge, School of Advanced Study, University of
                            London</hi></p>
                    <p>How can digital editing recover under-examined collaborative anti-slavery
                        literature anthologies and introduce new paths for critical interpretation
                        and historical scholarship? I am proposing to address this challenge by
                        producing a digital scholarly edition of
                        <hi rend="italic">The Bow in the Cloud </hi>(hereafter
                            <hi rend="italic">BC</hi>), an 1834 anti-slavery anthology edited by
                        Mary Anne Rawson, an activist from Sheffield, England. This project uses
                        editorial and network analysis principles to make accessible the genesis and
                        historical significance of this anthology and its neglected manuscript
                        archive, and to visualize the social networks and underlying themes of
                        transatlantic anti-slavery print culture and rhetoric between 1826 and 1834,
                        when Rawson was preparing the anthology. Using the semantic web authoring
                        tool Scalar, the project combines a TEI XML workflow, network analysis
                        tools, and linked open data standards to attempt to model relationships
                        between archival documents as well as creative-critical potentials. </p>
                    <p>The project’s pioneering use of textual “paths” and network analysis tools
                        leverage computation to facilitate critical analysis. This digital
                        publication employs an integrative and interdependent approach by featuring
                        new modes of presentation, enriching library catalogs and digital image
                        collections with IIIF ( <ref target="https://eur03.safelinks.protection.outlook.com/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fiiif.io%2F&amp;data=05%7C01%7Cchristopher.ohge%40sas.ac.uk%7C83089bb13c4a46a34f2008da68aca5c0%7C185280ba7a0042ea940819eafd13552e%7C0%7C0%7C637937387977681649%7CUnknown%7CTWFpbGZsb3d8eyJWIjoiMC4wLjAwMDAiLCJQIjoiV2luMzIiLCJBTiI6Ik1haWwiLCJXVCI6Mn0%3D%7C3000%7C%7C%7C&amp;sdata=wVH%2B2giWXDMyEWVQK71zJgIgxGEuwikbdEs4Y4QItgA%3D&amp;reserved=0">https://iiif.io/</ref>) technology, in collaboration with the John Rylands Library and
                        Research Institute, and collaboratively building an edition with network
                        analysis tools. The edition lays the groundwork for a detailed, dynamic, and
                        flexible engagement with the making of a significant anti-slavery publishing
                        event. </p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Title: “Observing 12th Century Cultic Change through Devotee
                            Movement and Corporeal Experience: a Spatial Investigation of Early
                            Medieval Hampi, Southern India”</hi></p>
                    <p><hi rend="italic">Presenter: Candis Haak, Assistant Professor, SUNY
                            Oswego</hi></p>
                    <p>This paper presents a two-part digital spatial
                            analysis methodology and its application to a 12th-century Virupaksha
                            temple within an early Shaivite pilgrimage center in South India. I
                            developed this methodology to investigate ritual change in the early
                            medieval period of the Hemakuta Hill landscape in Hampi, using a
                            geographic information system (GIS) coupled with the immersive panoramic
                            capabilities of Google Street View. By combining these digital
                            platforms, changes to devotee movement and sensorial experiences over
                            time can be detected. Devotee movement through the pilgrimage space was
                            modeled on time-sensitive maps created using Esri’s ArcMap. Pathways of
                            movement across the site that devotees traveled were then subsequently
                            explored in the immersive panoramic imagery captured in Google Street
                            View. The nature of Google’s Street View technology and imagery enables
                            a ground-based assessment of visual and physical accessibility, and
                            sensorial engagement with non-ephemeral pilgrimage landscape features to
                            be assessed. By combining these digital tools, a historicized analysis
                            of the character and qualities of place, born from the organization of
                            the site, are identifiable. To illustrate, I will discuss the Mula
                            Virupaksha temple as it captures a moment of innovation and heightened
                            concern for devotee experience management. Google Street View imagery
                            captures the importance of the devotee visual experience in the
                            innovative temple design by limiting and directing devotee sightlines.
                            Such novel architecture and use of space thus naturalized and elevated
                            the Virupaksha cult in an already established sacred pilgrimage
                            landscape. </p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Title: “Re-animating Objects: Collaborative Visualizations
                            of Lost Landscapes, Lives, and Transcultural Encounters in 20th Century
                            Japan”</hi></p>
                    <p><hi rend="italic">Presenter: Joanne Bernardi, University of Rochester</hi></p>
                    <p><hi rend="italic">Re-Envisioning Japan: Japan as Destination in 20 Century Visual and Material Culture </hi>(REJ)
                        conjoins an original collection of early- to mid-20 <hi rend="superscript">th</hi> century multimedia ephemera with a
                        collaboratively built open access digital archive that dynamically displays
                        these objects in digital space. By allowing curated access to resources
                        documenting representations of Japan and its place in the world, REJ draws
                        on Carole Palmer’s idea of a Thematic Research Collection, a web-based
                        resource in which scholarship is embedded in both the product and its use.
                        The collaborative dimension of envisioning and assembling the collection,
                        designing REJ’s parameters, and reiteratively building a digital archive
                        that functions as a versatile tool for re-envisioning Japan’s past on a
                        granular level is integral to the project’s success. The interdisciplinary
                        backgrounds of REJ’s team (faculty and library colleagues, postdoctoral,
                        graduate, and undergraduate students) and students in REJ’s dedicated course
                        enhance its value as a tool for interrogating enduring and dominant
                        historical narratives by opening up alternative approaches to understanding
                        how Japan defined itself and was defined by others through the material
                        evidence of personal experience and transcultural change. I focus on the
                        processes behind the schema and curatorial features that such
                        interdisciplinarity engenders: features for collective object analysis,
                        contextual metadata management, and online multimedia exhibition and
                        curation that enable collaborative classroom assignments. These include:
                        “Object Encounters” (visual explorations of objects inspired by Prownian
                        analysis); a customized streaming media window; and a media annotation tool
                        for contextualizing locations and events, and marking formal elements that
                        reveal visual patterns. </p>
                </div>
                
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliogr">
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Bernardi, Joanne</author> / <author>Dimmock, Nora</author> 
                        (2017): “Creative Curating: The Digital Archive
                            as Argument”, in: Sayers, Jentery (ed.):
                        <hi rend="italic"> Making Things and Drawing Boundaries: Experiments in the Digital Humanities</hi>
                        , Minneapolis: University of Minnesota Press,
                            187-197.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Bernardi, Joanne</author>
                        (2013-2016a, 2017b):
                         Re-Envisioning Japan: Japan as Destination in 20
                        <hi rend="superscript">th</hi>
                         Century Visual and Material Culture, Rochester, NY: University of Rochester Digital Scholarship, River Campus Libraries. First WordPress edition, second Omeka edition. 
                        <ref target="https://rej.lib.rochester.edu">https://rej.lib.rochester.edu</ref>
                        [03.05.2023].
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Drucker, Johanna</author>
                         (2011): “Humanities Approaches to Graphical Display” in 
                        <hi rend="italic">Digital Humanities Quarterly</hi>
                         5,1: 
                        <ref target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/5/1/000091/000091.html">http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/5/1/000091/000091.html</ref>
                        [03.05.2023].
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Hinrichs, Uta</author> / <author>Forlini, Stefania</author> / <author>Moynihan, Bridget</author> 
                         (2019): “In Defense of Sandcastles: Research Thinking Through Visualization in Digital Humanities”, in 
                        <hi rend="italic">Digital Scholarship in the
                            Humanities</hi>
                         34, 1: 80-99.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Hullman, Jessica</author> / <author>Diakopoulos, Nick</author> 
                         (2011): “Visualization Rhetoric: Framing Effects in Narrative Visualization”, in 
                        <hi rend="italic">IEEE Transactions on Visualization
                            and Computer Graphics</hi>
                         17, 12: 2231-2240. 
                        DOI: 
                        <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1109/TVCG.2011.255">10.1109/TVCG.2011.255</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Miller, Peter N</author>
                        (2014):
                         “How Objects Speak,” in:
                        <hi rend="italic">The Chronicle of Higher
                            Education</hi>
                        , August 11.
                            http://chronicle.com/article/How-Objects-Speak/148177.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Palmer, Carole L.</author>
                        (2004): “Thematic Research Collections”, in
                            Schreibman, Susan/ Ray Siemens/ John Unsworth, (eds.):
                        <hi rend="italic">A Companion to Digital
                            Humanities</hi>
                        , Oxford: Blackwell.
                        <ref target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/companion">http://www.digitalhumanities.org/companion</ref>
                        [03.05.2023].
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Prown, Jules David</author>
                         (1982): “Mind in Matter: An Introduction to Material Culture Theory and Method”, in:
                        <hi rend="italic">Winterthur Portfolio</hi>
                         17,1: 1-19.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Whalen, Catherine</author>
                         (2020): “Collecting as Historical Practice and the Conundrum of the Unmoored Object”, in: Gaskell, Ivan/ Sarah Anne Carter (eds):
                        <hi rend="italic">The Oxford Handbook of History and
                            Material Culture</hi>
                        , New York: Oxford University Press:
                            593-618.
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text></TEI>