<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_allPlus.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_allPlus.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Visualizing Cities: H.P. Lovecraft's Providence, Rhode Island</title>
                <author n="SzaboVictoriaSZABO_Victoria_Visualizing_Cities__H_P__Lovecraft_s_Providen.xml"><persName n="SzaboVictoria">
                        <surname>Szabo</surname>
                        <forename>Victoria</forename>
                    </persName><affiliation>Duke University, United States of America</affiliation><email>ves4@duke.edu</email></author><meeting><date from-iso="2023-07-10" to-iso="2023-07-14"/><title>Digital Humanities 2023. Collaboration as Opportunity</title><placeName>Graz</placeName></meeting>
                <author n="MonteleoneCosimoSZABO_Victoria_Visualizing_Cities__H_P__Lovecraft_s_Providen.xml"><persName n="MonteleoneCosimo">
                        <surname>Monteleone</surname>
                        <forename>Cosimo</forename>
                    </persName><affiliation>University of Padova, Italy</affiliation><email>cosimo.monteleone@unipd.it</email></author><meeting><date from-iso="2023-07-10" to-iso="2023-07-14"/><title>Digital Humanities 2023. Collaboration as Opportunity</title><placeName>Graz</placeName></meeting>
            </titleStmt>
            
            <publicationStmt><publisher><orgName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1137284463">Zentrum für Informationsmodellierung
                    - Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities, Karl-Franzens-Universität
                    Graz</orgName></publisher><date when="2023">2023</date><pubPlace>Graz</pubPlace><availability><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">Creative Commons BY
                    4.0</licence></availability></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title>Digital Humanities 2023: Book of Abstracts</title><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-9256-0958"><forename>Walter</forename><surname>Scholger</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>University of Graz</orgName><placeName>Graz, Austria</placeName></affiliation><email>walter.scholger@uni-graz.at</email></editor><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-1726-1712"><forename>Georg</forename><surname>Vogeler</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>University of Graz</orgName><placeName>Graz, Austria</placeName></affiliation><email>georg.vogeler@uni-graz.at</email></editor><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-3919-993X"><forename>Toma</forename><surname>Tasovac</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>Belgrade Center for Digital Humanities</orgName><placeName>Belgrade, Serbia</placeName></affiliation><email>ttasovac@humanistika.org</email></editor><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-4593-059X"><forename>Anne</forename><surname>Baillot</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>Le Mans Université</orgName><placeName>Le Mans, France</placeName></affiliation><email>anne.baillot@univ-lemans.fr</email></editor><respStmt><resp>Data Management</resp><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0009-0007-9019-8215"><forename>Elisabeth</forename><surname>Raunig</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Management</resp><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-1438-3236"><forename>Martina</forename><surname>Scholger</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Management</resp><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-9116-0402"><forename>Elisabeth</forename><surname>Steiner</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Curation</resp><persName><forename>Johanna</forename><surname>Ofenauer</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Curation</resp><persName><forename>Christina</forename><surname>Burgstaller</surname></persName></respStmt><idno type="DOI">10.5281/zenodo.7961822</idno></seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="DHCONVALIDATOR" version="1.22">
                    <label>DHConvalidator</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc><abstract><p>The imagined urban landscapes, structures, and environments of writer H.P. Lovecraft’s Providence, RI play a central role in the development of his tales of horror, abomination, and wonder. This project repurposes the tools of digital art history and urbanism to create imaginative reconstructions of these locales across space and time.</p></abstract><langUsage><language ident="en">English</language></langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="category">
                    <term>Paper</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="subcategory">
                    <term>Short Presentation</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="keywords">
                    <term>immersion</term>
                    <term>visualization</term>
                    <term>interaction</term>
                    <term>literature</term>
                    <term>media</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="topics">
                    <term>public humanities collaborations and methods</term>
                    <term>spatial &amp; spatio-temporal analysis</term>
                    <term>modeling and visualization</term>
                    <term>user experience design and analysis</term>
                    <term>virtual and augmented reality creation</term>
                    <term>systems</term>
                    <term>and analysis</term>
                    <term>Communication studies</term>
                    <term>Literary studies</term>
                    <term>Media studies</term>
                    
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <p>HP Lovecraft is an early 20th century writer famous for his tales of horror and dark
                imagination. His tombstone famously reads “I am Providence" and the city and its
                environs figure prominently in his work. This project repurposes the tools of
                digital art history and urbanism we have used in our collaborative,
                interdisciplinary Visualizing Cities projects (Huffman et al. 2018) to create
                spatialized imaginative reconstructions of some of these locales. Our interest in
                focusing on fictive places is both because this approach offers a new way to engage
                with literary texts and their imagined places, and because experimenting with an
                imagined city frees us to explore techniques for representation and interpretation
                that rely not only upon strict measurement and precise translation but also allow
                for the affective, storytelling elements of spatial and immersive media forms. It
                allows us to explore Mikhail Bakhtin’s literary chronotopes and theories of genre
                and adaptation (Bakhtin 1982) in digital media, building on related work in literary
                and film adaptation studies (Collington 2010). We draw upon the conceptual
                organizational categories developed in work such as that of the <hi rend="italic">Chronotopic Topographies</hi> (U of Lancaster) project team (Bushall et al.
                2021), but with an emphasis on historic maps, archives, 3D, and augmented reality
                immersive experience design. </p>
            <p>Lovecraft’s literary works promotes an unreal universe; one generated by the fears of
                the unconscious that re-emerge in an apparent atmosphere of familiarity. By
                deconstructing Lovecraft’s work, visualizing its scenes, and exploring its broader
                symbolic landscape, our goal is to explore both the literature itself and the
                hidden, vanished, counterfactual, and obscured past places and spaces that he
                engages. Cities and architecture play a predominant role in Lovecraftian tales, and
                he conducted extensive research for his tales (Joshi 2013, Poole 2016, Sederholm et
                al. 2016). He fills crowded urban centers with magical and sinister vestiges, and
                the natural environment with eerie and malevolent actors; what is more familiar
                hides horror, abomination and wonder. Lovecraft’s writing reflects change over time
                at varying scales: rooms, cells, hidden corners, corridors and halls; but also
                squares, roads, countryside and woods. All of these places are described in size and
                shape and by wall covering materials, floors and ceilings, and mobile and fixed
                furniture. Through visual, haptic and olfactory experiences, the encounters the
                maximum power of the perturbing imaginary. </p>
            <p>Further, Lovecraft’s tales have also already been adapted, interpreted, and
                re-imagined through various media - films, images, comics, games. They form a part
                of the history of science fiction and the inheritance of the gothic. They are a rich
                source of inspiration to fans and pilgrims, as local guidebooks and specialty press
                publications show (Beckwith 1986; Pearsall and Franks 2005; Poole 2016). In our own
                adaptation we are interested into tapping into additional states of cognition and
                experience borne of such adaptation, remediation and fan fervor in order to
                complement a more analytical and critically distant approach to the work. In
                creating our visualizations, we draw upon Robert Talley’s discussion of spatial
                anxiety and tophrenia in literature (Talley 2018), and take inspiration from critics
                like Janet Murray (Murray 2017) and Marie-Laure Ryan (Ryan 2015) and through guides
                to virtual reality and digtal storytelling authorship (Bucher 2017; McEarlean 2018;
                Alexander 2017).</p>
            <p>We begin with <hi rend="italic">The Case of Charles Dexter Ward</hi>. CDW tells the
                story of a scholarly young man who conjures a famous ancestor, Joseph Curwen, whose
                necromancy had horrified his hometown of Providence 150 years earlier. Lovecraft
                describes layers of urban history and architecture, the characters who inhabit it,
                and the feelings these elements evoke in his protagonists. We are exploring these
                levels and layers by creating maps, apps, images, texts, audio, and models based
                upon them. Like others in his oeuvre, this tale operates at the scales of buildings
                and rooms; city and neighborhood; region: world and the various interior states of
                key characters, and across time. This project unpacks and presents these narrative
                elements through complementary modalities of comprehension and apprehension;
                immersive experience design; adaptation through sensory experience; visual
                perception and memory; and the conjunction of reality and imagination. The complex,
                layered plotting of the tale allows for thick description of a world in which the
                presence of the past haunts lived experience in the everyday, and in which
                antiquarian enthusiasm literally and figuratively channel unexpected ghosts. We
                argue that the underlying patterns of the narrative are revealed through a
                visualization process that foregrounds spatiality and temporal re-ordering –
                rendering them visible for both critical examination and enhanced affective
                response. </p>
            <figure>
                <graphic n="1001" width="16.002cm" height="9.001125cm" url="Pictures/1d45c006a7284b73cfaae7ff8c37c55e.png" rend="inline"/>
                <head>Figure 1: Perspectives on visualizing the spaces and places of Lovecraft’s
                    Providence in Charles Dexter Ward. Interactive historical GIS map with text
                    locales; contemporary panorama and MS reference insets; 3D building
                    reconstruction juxtaposed with relevant text; location-based augmented reality
                    immersive 3D walk-in environment and site map inferred from the text.</head>
            </figure>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliogr">
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <bibl><author>Alexander, Bryan </author>(2017):
                            <hi rend="italic">The New Digital Storytelling: Creating Narratives with
                            New Media</hi>. New York: Praeger. </bibl>
                    <bibl><author>Bakhtin, Mikhail </author>(1981):
                        “Forms of Time and the Chronotope of the Novel.” <hi rend="italic">The
                            Dialogic Imagination</hi>. Texas. </bibl>
                    <bibl><author>Beckwith, Henry </author>(1986):
                            <hi rend="italic">Lovecraft's Providence and Adjacent Parts</hi>.
                        Hampton Fall, NH: Donald Grant. </bibl>
                    <bibl><author>Bucher, John </author>(2017): <hi rend="italic">Storytelling for Virtual Reality Methods and Principles
                            for Crafting Immersive Narratives</hi>. New York: Routledge. </bibl>
                    <bibl><author>Bushell, Sally</author> / <author>Butler, James</author> / <author>Hay, Duncan</author> / <author>Hutcheon, Rebecca</author> / <author>Butterworth, Alex</author> (2021).
                        “Chronotopic Cartography: Mapping Literary Time-Space.” <hi rend="italic">Journal of Victorian Culture</hi> 26,2: 310–325. </bibl>
                    <bibl><author>Collington, Tara </author>(2010):
                        “The Chronotope and the Study of Literary Adaptation:The Case of Robinson
                        Crusoe.”
                        <hi rend="italic">Bakhtin’s Theory of the Literary Chronotope Reflections, Applications, Perspectives. </hi>Gent:
                        Academic Press. </bibl>
                    <bibl><author>Huffman, Kristin L.</author> / <author>Giordano, Andrea</author> / <author>Bruzelius, Caroline eds.</author> (2018
                        <hi rend="italic">) Visualizing Venice: Mapping and Modeling Time and Change in a City. </hi>New
                        York: Routledge. </bibl>
                    <bibl><author>Joshi, S.T. </author>(2013):
                        <hi rend="italic">I Am Providence: The Life and Times of H. P. Lovecraft. </hi>New
                        York: Hippocampus Press. </bibl>
                    <bibl><author>McErlean, Kelly </author>(208): <hi rend="italic">Interactive Narratives and Transmedia Storytelling:
                            Creating Immersive Stories Across New Media Platforms</hi>. New York:
                        Routledge. </bibl>
                    <bibl><author>Murray, Janet H. </author>(2017):
                            <hi rend="italic">Hamlet on the Holodeck: The Future of Narrative in
                            Cyberspace</hi> . Cambridge: MIT Press.. </bibl>
                    <bibl><author>Pearsall, Anthony</author> / <author>Franks, Linda Joyce</author> (2005): <hi rend="italic">The Lovecraft Lexicon: A
                            Reader's Guide to Persons, Places and Things in the Tales of H.P.
                            Lovecraft</hi>. New Falcon </bibl>
                    <bibl><author>Poole, W. Scott </author>(2016):
                            <hi rend="italic">In the Mountains of Madness: The Life and
                            Extraordinary Afterlife of H.P. Lovecraft</hi>. New York: Soft Skull
                        Press . </bibl>
                    <bibl><author>Ryan, Marie-Laure </author>(2015):
                            <hi rend="italic">Narrative as Virtual Reality 2</hi>. Baltimore: Johns
                        Hopkins University Press. </bibl>
                    <bibl><author>Sederholm, Carl.</author> / <author>Jeffrey Andrew Weinstock, editors</author> (2016). <hi rend="italic">The Age of
                            Lovecraft</hi> . Minneapolis: U of Minnesota Press. </bibl>
                    <bibl><author>Tally, Robert. </author>(2018): <hi rend="italic">Topophrenia: Place, Narrative, and the Spatial
                            Imagination</hi>. Bloomington, IN: Indiana University Press. </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text></TEI>