<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_allPlus.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_allPlus.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="full">
                    <title type="main">Mapping German Fiction in Translation</title>
                    <title type="sub"> Visualizing Translationalism in the German National Library
                        Catalogue</title>
                </title>
                <author n="TeichmannLisaTEICHMANN_Lisa_Mapping_German_Fiction_in_Translation.xml"><persName n="TeichmannLisa">
                        <surname>Teichmann</surname>
                        <forename>Lisa</forename>
                    </persName><affiliation>Université de Montréal, Canada</affiliation><email>lisa.teichmann@mail.mcgill.ca</email></author><meeting><date from-iso="2023-07-10" to-iso="2023-07-14"/><title>Digital Humanities 2023. Collaboration as Opportunity</title><placeName>Graz</placeName></meeting>
            </titleStmt>
            
            <publicationStmt><publisher><orgName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1137284463">Zentrum für Informationsmodellierung
                    - Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities, Karl-Franzens-Universität
                    Graz</orgName></publisher><date when="2023">2023</date><pubPlace>Graz</pubPlace><availability><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">Creative Commons BY
                    4.0</licence></availability></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title>Digital Humanities 2023: Book of Abstracts</title><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-9256-0958"><forename>Walter</forename><surname>Scholger</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>University of Graz</orgName><placeName>Graz, Austria</placeName></affiliation><email>walter.scholger@uni-graz.at</email></editor><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-1726-1712"><forename>Georg</forename><surname>Vogeler</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>University of Graz</orgName><placeName>Graz, Austria</placeName></affiliation><email>georg.vogeler@uni-graz.at</email></editor><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-3919-993X"><forename>Toma</forename><surname>Tasovac</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>Belgrade Center for Digital Humanities</orgName><placeName>Belgrade, Serbia</placeName></affiliation><email>ttasovac@humanistika.org</email></editor><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-4593-059X"><forename>Anne</forename><surname>Baillot</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>Le Mans Université</orgName><placeName>Le Mans, France</placeName></affiliation><email>anne.baillot@univ-lemans.fr</email></editor><respStmt><resp>Data Management</resp><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0009-0007-9019-8215"><forename>Elisabeth</forename><surname>Raunig</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Management</resp><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-1438-3236"><forename>Martina</forename><surname>Scholger</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Management</resp><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-9116-0402"><forename>Elisabeth</forename><surname>Steiner</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Curation</resp><persName><forename>Johanna</forename><surname>Ofenauer</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Curation</resp><persName><forename>Christina</forename><surname>Burgstaller</surname></persName></respStmt><idno type="DOI">10.5281/zenodo.7961822</idno></seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="DHCONVALIDATOR" version="1.22">
                    <label>DHConvalidator</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc><abstract><p>In this paper I present a bibliographic dataset of German fiction in translation consisting of over 35,000 translated titles and 6,000 authors extracted from the German National Library. I further propose a quantitative model for visualizing translationalism in the catalogue by combining social network analysis, descriptive statistics, and geomapping.
            </p></abstract><langUsage><language ident="en">English</language></langUsage>
            <abstract><p>In this paper I present a bibliographic dataset of German fiction in translation consisting of over 35,000 translated titles and 6,000 authors extracted from the German National Library. I further propose a quantitative model for visualizing translationalism in the catalogue by combining social network analysis, descriptive statistics, and geomapping.
            </p></abstract>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="category">
                    <term>Paper</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="subcategory">
                    <term>Long Presentation</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="keywords">
                    <term>geomapping</term>
                    <term>bibliographic data models</term>
                    <term>German National Library catalogue</term>
                    <term>German fiction in translation</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="topics">
                    <term>bibliographic analysis</term>
                    <term>cultural analytics</term>
                    <term>network analysis and graphs theory and application</term>
                    <term>spatial &amp; spatio-temporal analysis</term>
                    <term>modeling and visualization</term>
                    <term>Book and print history</term>
                    <term>Cultural studies</term>
                    <term>Literary studies</term>
                    <term>Translation studies</term>
                    
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <p>According to the Index Translationum, German is one of the most translated languages
                worldwide (Index Translationum, “Statistics”). To this date, however, tools to map
                and explore the routes of literary transfer of German literature through translation
                have only been marginally developed (Rühl and Bold 2016; Ivanovic and Seidl 2016;
                Gerber 2008, Reynolds and Vitali 2021) and comprehensive datasets on German fiction
                in translation are yet to be curated. Furthermore, even though a methodological
                framework for the analysis of translation as a network of transfer has long taken
                shape within the field of translation sociology (Bachleitner and Wolf 2004, Heilbron
                1999, Sapiro 2016) and especially polysystem theory (Even-Zohar 1979), to date there
                is still a lack of quantitative models for bibliographic translation data and a “Big
                Translation History” (Fólica et al. 2020) of German fiction. </p>
            <p>In response to the sparsity of translation datasets and models of analysis, I have
                curated a dataset and developed a quantitative model for German fiction in
                translation as part of my doctoral thesis and a research internship with the German
                National Library Datenshop. Due to its collection policies and data accessibility,
                the German National Library catalogue is an immensely rich open resource for
                bibliographic data with translations of German fiction accounting for 3.5% of
                catalogued fiction titles. To visualize and analyze translation data of German
                fiction – that is German fiction translated into other languages – geographically
                and as a network, I used the library catalogue’s data fields on language, author,
                and publication place ­within the RStudio environment.</p>
            <p>I extracted all the titles of translated German fiction between 1980 and 2020 from
                the catalogue with the help of a customized search query. The resulting dataset, the
                first of its kind for this library catalogue, consists of over 35,000 translated
                titles and 6,000 translated authors. By presenting the first quantitative study of
                German fiction in translation, with visualizations of the bibliographic data from
                the German National Library catalogue, this project contributes to making this rich
                resource of bibliographic data as well as a quantitative model of analysis
                accessible within and beyond the field of Digital Humanities (DH), German and
                Translation Studies, and Comparative Literature.</p>
            <p>I argue that making use of the wealth of bibliographic data available and modeling
                German fiction in translation is long overdue, especially since the possible
                findings have important implications for the core arguments in literary studies at
                large and German Studies specifically — canonization, world literature versus
                national literatures, and literary communities. In line with scholars such as Susan
                Bassnett (2014), Doris Bachmann-Medick (2009), Emily Apter (2013), and Rebecca
                Walkowitz (2017), my aim is to widen the theoretical implications to focus on
                transfer, literary networks, and the global distribution of works of literature by
                drawing on translation as an analytical category. The underlying hypothesis of my
                model of analysis is that the translations’ languages connect places by shared
                authors. Visualizing the language network by shared, translated authors reveals
                connections between literary communities that transgress unilingual canons and
                therefore challenges categories of “national”, “canonical”, and “world” literature.
                Accordingly, I see this project contributing to the translational turn in German
                Studies, expanding the concept of literary transfer by applying a language network
                model and visualizing connections between linguistic communities of translated
                authors.</p>
            <p>For this paper, I will present my dataset and model of analysis, a combination of
                social network analysis, descriptive statistics, and geomapping aiming to discuss
                where, into which languages, and which authors’ German fiction is most frequently
                translated. I further ask, what are the roles of canonical authors in the global
                circulation of German fiction in translation and those of non-canonical
                (translational) authors in connecting linguistic and literary communities in
                geographic space? My results indicate that routes of literary transfer through
                translation are highly centralized and interconnected in few languages but have also
                revealed the importance of peripheral languages and non-canonical authors in these
                processes. As I argue, factoring in translation as its own analytical category and
                visualizing the roles it plays in the national and global canonization of an author
                or work of fiction challenges our understanding of the national and the world
                literary canons of German fiction.</p>
            <p>By curating and making available the dataset as well as the code scripts for
                analysis, this project further adds to the quantitative turn in translation studies
                as well as multilingual DH by presenting a multilingual dataset and offering
                solutions in working with bibliographic translation data across different languages.
                Within translation sociology, this project draws heavily on field theory by
                conceptualizing the translational field as a space where translationalism — the
                notion that characterizes authors whose work in translation connects multiple
                linguistic communities in geographic space — takes shape. Thereby, my analysis not
                only addresses the roles of specific languages and authors, but also utilizes their
                connections and routes of transfer to visualize their positionings in the field of
                translation. Additionally, pointing out catalogue-specific features that pose
                limitations for extracting and analyzing translations opens up a discussion on the
                (in)visibility of translations in literary studies, library and information
                sciences, critical archival studies, and DH.</p>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliogr">
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Apter, Emily S. </author>
                        <hi rend="italic">Against World Literature: On the Politics of
                            Untranslatability</hi>. London ; New York: Verso, 2013. </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Bachleitner, Norbert, and Michaela Wolf. </author>
                        “Auf dem Weg zu einer Soziologie der literarischen Übersetzung im
                            deutschsprachigen Raum.” 
                        <hi rend="italic">Internationales Archiv für Sozialgeschichte der deutschen
                            Literatur (IASL)</hi> 29, no. 2 (December 2004): 1–25. <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1515/IASL.2004.2.1">https://doi.org/10.1515/IASL.2004.2.1</ref>. </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Bachmann-Medick, Doris. </author>
                        “Introduction: The Translational Turn.” 
                        <hi rend="italic">Translation Studies</hi> 2, no. 1 (January 2009): 2–16.
                            <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1080/14781700802496118">https://doi.org/10.1080/14781700802496118</ref>. </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Bassnett, Susan. </author>
                        “From Cultural Turn to Translational Turn: A Transnational Journey.” In 
                        <hi rend="italic">World Literature in Theory</hi>, edited by David Damrosch,
                        234–45. Chichester, England: Wiley-Blackwell, 2014. <ref target="https://ebookcentral.proquest.com/lib/nottingham/detail.action?docID=1566390">https://ebookcentral.proquest.com/lib/nottingham/detail.action?docID=1566390</ref>. </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Even-Zohar, Itamar. </author>
                        “Polysystem Theory.” 
                        <hi rend="italic">Poetics Today</hi> 1, no. 1/2 (1979): 287. <ref target="https://doi.org/10.2307/1772051">https://doi.org/10.2307/1772051</ref>. </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Gerber, Leah. </author>
                        “Building Bridges, Building a Bibliography of Australian Children’s
                            Fiction in German Translation 1854–2007.” 
                        <hi rend="italic">New Review of Children’s Literature and Librarianship</hi>
                        14, no. 2 (September 2008): 141–57. <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1080/13614540902835186">https://doi.org/10.1080/13614540902835186</ref>. </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Heilbron, Johan. </author>
                        “Towards a Sociology of Translation: Book Translations as a Cultural
                            World-System.” <hi rend="italic">European Journal of Social
                            Theory</hi> 2, no. 4 (November 1999): 429–44. <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1177/136843199002004002">https://doi.org/10.1177/136843199002004002</ref>. </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Index Translationum. </author>
                        “Statistics on Whole Index Translationum Database: Top 50 Original
                            Language.” Accessed January 28, 2021. <ref target="https://www.unesco.org/xtrans/bsstatexp.aspx?crit1L=3&amp;nTyp=min&amp;topN=50&amp;lg=0">https://www.unesco.org/xtrans/bsstatexp.aspx?crit1L=3&amp;nTyp=min&amp;topN=50&amp;lg=0</ref>. </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Ivanovic, Christine, and Barbara Seidl. </author>
                        “What Is Translational Literature and How to Classify It?:
                            Crowd-Sourcing as a Starting Point for Corpus Building and Type
                            Distinction in Comparative Literature.” In <hi rend="italic">Proceedings of the Fourth International Conference on Technological
                            Ecosystems for Enhancing Multiculturality - TEEM ’16</hi>, 957–63.
                        Salamanca, Spain: ACM Press, 2016. <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1145/3012430.3012632">https://doi.org/10.1145/3012430.3012632</ref>. </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Norrick-Rühl, Corinna, and Melanie Ramdarshan Bold. </author>
                        “Crossing the Channel: Publishing Translated German Fiction in the UK.”
                            <hi rend="italic">Publishing Research Quarterly</hi> 32, no. 2
                        (June 2016): 125–38. <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1007/s12109-016-9458-3">https://doi.org/10.1007/s12109-016-9458-3</ref>. </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Reynolds, Matthew, and Giovanni Pietro Vitali. </author>
                        “Mapping and Reading a World of Translations: Prismatic Jane Eyre.”
                            <hi rend="italic">Modern Languages Open</hi> 1 (December 17, 2021):
                        23. <ref target="https://doi.org/10.3828/mlo.v0i0.375">https://doi.org/10.3828/mlo.v0i0.375</ref>. </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Sapiro, Gisèle. </author>
                        “How Do Literary Works Cross Borders (or Not)?” <hi rend="italic">Journal of World Literature</hi> 1, no. 1 (2016): 81–96. <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1163/24056480-00101009">https://doi.org/10.1163/24056480-00101009</ref>. </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Walkowitz, Rebecca. </author><hi rend="italic">Born
                            Translated</hi>. S.l.: Columbia University Press, 2017. </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text></TEI>