<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_allPlus.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_allPlus.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>ÚRSCÉAL: Building and Analysing a Corpus of the early Irish-language
                    Novel.</title>
                <author n="TonraJustinTONRA_Justin__RSC_AL__Building_and_Analysing_a_Corpus_of_the.xml"><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-2579-4367" n="TonraJustin">
                        <surname>Tonra</surname>
                        <forename>Justin</forename>
                    </persName><affiliation>University of Galway, Ireland</affiliation><email>justin.tonra@universityofgalway.ie</email></author><meeting><date from-iso="2023-07-10" to-iso="2023-07-14"/><title>Digital Humanities 2023. Collaboration as Opportunity</title><placeName>Graz</placeName></meeting>
            </titleStmt>
            
            <publicationStmt><publisher><orgName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1137284463">Zentrum für Informationsmodellierung
                    - Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities, Karl-Franzens-Universität
                    Graz</orgName></publisher><date when="2023">2023</date><pubPlace>Graz</pubPlace><availability><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">Creative Commons BY
                    4.0</licence></availability></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title>Digital Humanities 2023: Book of Abstracts</title><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-9256-0958"><forename>Walter</forename><surname>Scholger</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>University of Graz</orgName><placeName>Graz, Austria</placeName></affiliation><email>walter.scholger@uni-graz.at</email></editor><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-1726-1712"><forename>Georg</forename><surname>Vogeler</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>University of Graz</orgName><placeName>Graz, Austria</placeName></affiliation><email>georg.vogeler@uni-graz.at</email></editor><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-3919-993X"><forename>Toma</forename><surname>Tasovac</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>Belgrade Center for Digital Humanities</orgName><placeName>Belgrade, Serbia</placeName></affiliation><email>ttasovac@humanistika.org</email></editor><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-4593-059X"><forename>Anne</forename><surname>Baillot</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>Le Mans Université</orgName><placeName>Le Mans, France</placeName></affiliation><email>anne.baillot@univ-lemans.fr</email></editor><respStmt><resp>Data Management</resp><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0009-0007-9019-8215"><forename>Elisabeth</forename><surname>Raunig</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Management</resp><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-1438-3236"><forename>Martina</forename><surname>Scholger</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Management</resp><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-9116-0402"><forename>Elisabeth</forename><surname>Steiner</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Curation</resp><persName><forename>Johanna</forename><surname>Ofenauer</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Curation</resp><persName><forename>Christina</forename><surname>Burgstaller</surname></persName></respStmt><idno type="DOI">10.5281/zenodo.7961822</idno></seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="DHCONVALIDATOR" version="1.22">
                    <label>DHConvalidator</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc><abstract><p>This presentation describes the development and analysis of a corpus of the early Irish-language novel: one that strengthens existing resources for the comparative computational analysis of Europe’s multilingual literary history and clears a path for dedicated computational analysis of the early novel tradition in Irish.</p></abstract><langUsage><language ident="en">English</language></langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="category">
                    <term>Paper</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="subcategory">
                    <term>Short Presentation</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="keywords">
                    <term>corpus</term>
                    <term>Irish-language</term>
                    <term>novels</term>
                    <term>TEI</term>
                    <term>ELTeC</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="topics">
                    <term>digital libraries creation</term>
                    <term>management</term>
                    <term>and analysis</term>
                    <term>digitization (2D &amp; 3D)</term>
                    <term>text encoding and markup language creation</term>
                    <term>deployment</term>
                    <term>and analysis</term>
                    <term>Literary studies</term>
                    
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div type="div1">
                <p> ÚRSCEAL is a project to build an open-access TEI-encoded collection of the
                    Irish-language novel for inclusion in the European Literary Text Collection
                    (ELTeC), the state-of-the-art and standards-led multilingual corpus of the
                    European novel (1840-1920) (Schöch et al. 2021). ELTeC provides a collection of
                    novel corpora that are comparable in nature, scope, and quality across several
                    European languages: an essential condition for the creation of multilingual
                    tools and methods of computational literary analysis. To date, twenty European
                    languages are represented in ELTeC, but Irish is not. This short presentation
                    reports on the challenges and opportunities of developing an Irish-language
                    corpus for ELTeC and considers questions for preliminary computational analysis
                    of the collection. </p>

                <p>ÚRSCÉAL’s contribution to ELTeC solves a gap by completing and submitting a
                    collection of the Irish-language novel collection to the corpus, providing the
                    data and motivation for computational literary analysis of the Irish-language
                    novel and its European comparators. Moreover, it seeks to remedy broader gaps in
                    the availability of crucial texts from the early Irish-language novel tradition
                    by publishing new and accurate digital texts in a range of accessible formats
                    and examining the potential for developing an expanded corpus of the
                    Irish-language novel beyond 1920.</p>

                <p> Compared to other European languages, the tradition of the novel in Irish begins
                    relatively late: in 1901. Renowned for a rich oral literary culture, the
                    development of an Irish-language prose culture was delayed until the beginning
                    of the twentieth century owing to a variety of complex and interlinked causes
                    which lie in “the turbulent disjunctions of Irish colonial history” (O’Leary
                    1994). Warfare, famine, and penal legislation to suppress the use of Irish led
                    to such an impoverished bibliographical culture that many of the founding
                    authors of the late nineteenth-century Gaelic Revival movement had never read a
                    book in the Irish language. </p>

                <p>Irish, thus, is an outlier in the linguistic history of the European novel, but
                    that uniqueness offers analytical opportunities of its own: how does a
                    newly-developing novel culture compare to the more mature traditions of its
                    European neighbours? How does it reflect its encounters with novels in English
                    and other languages, as well as its own vernacular literature in established
                    forms such as poetry? The presentation considers how computational analyses
                    might be deployed to address these research questions.</p>

                <p> Many of these computational analyses have been used by colleagues from
                    South-Eastern Europe during and after COST Action CA16204 Distant Reading for
                    European Literary History. Computational analysis of novel collections from
                    Romania, Serbia, and Croatia prove instructive for making preliminary
                    assessments of representative national novel corpora, while a study exploring
                    titling practices in literary discourse which examined Romanian, Serbian,
                    Slovenian, and Ukrainian collections alongside those of more culturally
                    hegemonic Western European languages deliveres a model for genuine comparative
                    multilingual analysis of the European novel (Patras et al. 2019; Stanković et
                    al. 2022; Krstev et al. 2019; Primorac 2019; Marinescu 2019; Patras et al.
                    2021). </p>
                <p> This short presentation provides a report on the development of an important new
                    resource that will act as a model, describing opportunities and challenges, for
                    others who wish to a build a corpus in a minority or minoritised language. At
                    the same time, it links to the broader collaborative development of ELTeC and,
                    in considering questions for computational analysis of the collection,
                    demonstrates fruitful exchanges and collaborations with South-Eastern European
                    colleagues and their research, while offering advice for initial computational
                    analysis of similar corpora. The opportunities presented by these collaborations
                    will strengthen ELTeC as the basis for comparative analysis of the European
                    novel and clear a path for dedicated computational analysis of the early
                    tradition of the novel in Irish. </p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliogr">
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Krstev, Cvetana, et al.</author> (2019): “Analysis of the First
                        Serbian Literature Corpus of the Late 19th and Early 20th Century with the
                        TXM Platform”, in: Pálko, Gábor (ed.): <hi rend="italic">DH_Budapest_2019</hi>, 2019, 36–37
                        <ref target="http://elte-dh.hu/wp-content/uploads/2019/09/DH_BP_2019-Abstract-Booklet.pdf">http://elte-dh.hu/wp-content/uploads/2019/09/DH_BP_2019-Abstract-Booklet.pdf</ref>. </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Marinescu, Luiza</author> (2019): “From Close to Distant Reading
                        of 100 Romanian Novels”, in: <hi rend="italic">Studia Ubb Philologia</hi>
                        LXIV, 2: 239–50. DOI: 10.24193/subbphilo.2019.2.19. </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>O’Leary, Philip</author> (1994): <hi rend="italic">The Prose
                            Literature of the Gaelic Revival, 1881-1921: Ideology and
                            Innovation</hi>. University Park: Pennsylvania State University Press. </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Patras, Roxana et al.</author> (2019): “The Splendors and
                        Mist(Eries) of Romanian Digital Literary Studies: A State-of-the-Art Just
                        before Horizons 2020 Closes Off”, in: <hi rend="italic">Hermeneia</hi> 23:
                        207–22. </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Patras, Roxana et al.</author> (2021): “Thresholds to the ‘Great
                        Unread’: Titling Practices in Eleven ELTeC Collections”, in: <hi rend="italic">Interférences Littéraires/Literaire Interferenties</hi>
                        25: 163–87. </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Primorac, Antonija</author> (2019): “Infrastructural Challenges
                        for Large Scale Digital Text Corpora: A View From the European Margins”,
                        Humanities, Arts and Culture Data Summit and DARIAH Beyond Europe workshop,
                        National Library of Australia, Canberra, 2019
                        <ref target="https://www.humanities.org.au/special-event-1903/">https://www.humanities.org.au/special-event-1903/</ref>. </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Schöch, Christof, et al.</author> (2021): “Creating the European
                        Literary Text Collection (ELTeC): Challenges and Perspectives”, in: <hi rend="italic">Modern Languages Open</hi> 1: 1-19. DOI:
                        10.3828/mlo.v0i0.364. </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Stanković, Ranka, et al.</author> (2022): “Distant Reading in
                        Digital Humanities: Case Study on the Serbian Part of the ELTeC Collection”,
                        in: European Language Resources Association (ed.): <hi rend="italic">Proceedings of the Language Resources and Evaluation Conference</hi>,
                        2022, 3337–45 <ref target="https://aclanthology.org/2022.lrec-1.356">https://aclanthology.org/2022.lrec-1.356</ref>. </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text></TEI>