<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_allPlus.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_allPlus.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Presence and Absence of Women in Early Modern Handwritten
                        News: Random Walks in the Medici Archive</title>
                <author n="TothGaborMihalyTOTH_Gabor_Mihaly_Presence_and_Absence_of_Women_in_Early_Mod.xml"><persName n="TothGaborMihaly">
                        <surname>Toth</surname>
                        <forename>Gabor Mihaly</forename>
                    </persName><affiliation>University of Luxembourg</affiliation><email>gabor.toth@maximilianeum.de</email></author><meeting><date from-iso="2023-07-10" to-iso="2023-07-14"/><title>Digital Humanities 2023. Collaboration as Opportunity</title><placeName>Graz</placeName></meeting>
            </titleStmt>
            
            <publicationStmt><publisher><orgName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1137284463">Zentrum für Informationsmodellierung
                    - Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities, Karl-Franzens-Universität
                    Graz</orgName></publisher><date when="2023">2023</date><pubPlace>Graz</pubPlace><availability><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">Creative Commons BY
                    4.0</licence></availability></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title>Digital Humanities 2023: Book of Abstracts</title><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-9256-0958"><forename>Walter</forename><surname>Scholger</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>University of Graz</orgName><placeName>Graz, Austria</placeName></affiliation><email>walter.scholger@uni-graz.at</email></editor><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-1726-1712"><forename>Georg</forename><surname>Vogeler</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>University of Graz</orgName><placeName>Graz, Austria</placeName></affiliation><email>georg.vogeler@uni-graz.at</email></editor><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-3919-993X"><forename>Toma</forename><surname>Tasovac</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>Belgrade Center for Digital Humanities</orgName><placeName>Belgrade, Serbia</placeName></affiliation><email>ttasovac@humanistika.org</email></editor><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-4593-059X"><forename>Anne</forename><surname>Baillot</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>Le Mans Université</orgName><placeName>Le Mans, France</placeName></affiliation><email>anne.baillot@univ-lemans.fr</email></editor><respStmt><resp>Data Management</resp><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0009-0007-9019-8215"><forename>Elisabeth</forename><surname>Raunig</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Management</resp><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-1438-3236"><forename>Martina</forename><surname>Scholger</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Management</resp><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-9116-0402"><forename>Elisabeth</forename><surname>Steiner</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Curation</resp><persName><forename>Johanna</forename><surname>Ofenauer</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Curation</resp><persName><forename>Christina</forename><surname>Burgstaller</surname></persName></respStmt><idno type="DOI">10.5281/zenodo.7961822</idno></seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from an OASIS Open Document</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="DHCONVALIDATOR" version="1.22">
                    <label>DHConvalidator</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc><abstract><p>In early modern Europe information circulated in the form of regular manuscript newsletters. However, most of the once existing news sheets did not survive. This study will present novel methods (random sampling with replacement, aka bootstrapping, and Bayesian statistics) to harness this lost corpus and to analyze its gender dimensions.</p></abstract><langUsage><language ident="en">English</language></langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="category">
                    <term>Paper</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="subcategory">
                    <term>Long Presentation</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="keywords">
                    <term>information culture</term>
                    <term>early modern history</term>
                    <term>randomness</term>
                    <term>Bayesian statistics</term>
                    <term>women's history</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="topics">
                    <term>artificial intelligence and machine learning</term>
                    <term>cultural analytics</term>
                    <term>information retrieval and querying algorithms and methods</term>
                    <term>text mining and analysis</term>
                    <term>Computer science</term>
                    <term>Gender and sexuality studies</term>
                    <term>History</term>
                    <term>Statistics</term>
                    
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <p>In February 1600 a peculiar news reached the Medici court: a Persian woman ambassador
                arrived at the Ottoman court in Constantinople. The report came from Wien in a
                handwritten news sheet (ASF MdP, 3087). How did contemporary news mongers receive
                this news? How often did they read about women? Did the presence of women increase
                or decrease over time? Since scholarship on early modern women history has not
                surveyed handwritten news sheets, there are no answers to these questions
                (Wiesner-Hanks 2019; Benson 2010; Rublack 2001). </p>
            <p>This paper will address them by presenting a completed computational study of a
                digitized corpus of transcribed handwritten news sheets in Italian from the Medici
                Archive (today in the Florentine State Archive). The corpus (published in Dooley et
                al. 2021), henceforth MIA-Euronews Corpus, consists of 1200 news sheets covering a
                period of 200 years and compiled in the major urban center of early modern Europe;
                each news sheet is a consecutive list of news items organized into distinct
                paragraphs. The paper will also present advanced statistical methods hitherto rarely
                applied in digital humanities: random sampling with replacement, aka bootstrapping
                (Bradley 1982), combined with Bayesian statistics (Lo 1986).</p>
            <p>First, the paper will offer an introduction into handwritten news. Early modern
                Europe witnessed an information revolution featured - in part - by the continual
                circulation of handwritten news sheets (Salmi-Niklander / Droste 2019; Davies /
                Fletcher 2014). From the 1600s handwritten news sheets were complemented with
                printed news, though they continued to play an important role (Infelise 2002). Even
                though handwritten newsletters that once circulated had a significant impact on the
                history of the continent, their study has remained challenging (Baron / Dooley,
                2005). Most of the once existing news sheets did not survive. Those that survived
                are dispersed in different collections such as for instance the Fugger Archive and
                the Medici Archive (Barker 2016; Bauer 2011). These collections are just <hi rend="italic">random </hi>and <hi rend="italic">incomplete </hi>samples from the
                once existing but today lost corpus of handwritten news. If surviving new sheets are
                random and incomplete, how can we use them to explore the presence of women in the
                lost whole of once existing new sheets? </p>
            <p>Second, the paper will address the problem of randomness and demonstrate how
                bootstrapping can harness it. I will draw on a thought experiment: </p>
            <p>Consider an AI-enabled robot that is literally a random walker. It keeps wandering in
                the Medici Archive; it keeps opening folders containing news sheets. It finds that
                sometimes women are mentioned, sometimes there is a complete silence on them. It
                thus concludes that women’s presence is random in the news sheets.</p>
            <p><figure>
                    <graphic url="Pictures/4be105e3d75fec5f9bf5ee3f4ab20e38.png"/>
                    <head>Figure 1. Probability of women occurring in news items randomly sampled
                        from the MIA-Euronews Corpus. Figure A shows the probability distribution as
                        a histogram. Figure B shows how the mean probability is reaching a stable
                        value throughout the repeating random sampling.</head>
                </figure></p>
            <p>However, I will point out that randomness can be investigated given that it is
                finite. I will demonstrate this by redesigning the thought experiment as a proper
                bootstrapping process (Aa et al., 1994):</p>
            <p>Imagine
                that our AI-enabled robot randomly selects 100 news sheets and 100 news items at
                once; then it reports us two pieces of information. First, it tells us in how many
                news sheets it found the occurrence of at least one woman. Second, it tells us how
                many news items mentioned at least one woman. Next, we ask our random walker robot
                to repeat the two tasks over thousands of times. </p>
            <p>I implemented this thought experiment algorithmically on the MIA-Euronews Corpus; in
                my talk I will present the implementation with a real time simulation (Figure 1 A
                and B) and by focusing on two aspects. First, with the bootstrapping we can map all
                possible outcomes (women mentioned 10,12, and so on times in hundred news sheets
                randomly selected) as well as their respective probabilities. Second, the random
                walk of the robot will sooner or later converge and reach a stable probability. I
                will point out that harnessing the randomness of a dataset involves studying that
                dataset from all possible angles (i.e. reshuffling and resampling as the
                bootstrapping does) and summarizing all possibilities with a probability
                distribution.</p>
            <p>Third, I will discuss the problem of how to get from the evidence collected in the
                Medici Archive to the lost whole of news sheets circulating in the early modern
                period. I will rely on an illustrative example:</p>
            <p>Consider an unfair coin; we do not know the prior probability of head and tail. We
                can toss the coin over thousands of times and gather evidence.</p>
            <p><figure>
                    <graphic url="Pictures/cfc65385eb14d0577a5072752ded1878.png"/>
                    <head>Figure 2. An illustrative example: assessing the bias of an unfair
                        (probability of Head: 0.3) coin by flipping it for a hundred times.</head>
                </figure> The
                two outcomes (Head and Tail) are modeled with a binomial random variable. Figure A
                shows the outcome of the tossing, i.e. the evidence. Figure B shows the most likely
                prior distribution that could give rise to the evidence gathered throughout the
                flipping; it renders the outcome of the tossing with the beta distribution, which
                maps the discrete values (number of Head and Tail) onto a continuous probability
                space between 0 and 1. The closer the mean value is to 0, the less likely that the
                coin is biased towards Head and more likely that it is biased towards Tail. The beta
                distribution on Figure B actually gives a correct guess of the prior probability of
                Head (i.e. 0.3). </p>
            <p><figure>
                    <graphic url="Pictures/8752d8568138adb9fc10ad9c4e8d9898.png"/>
                    <head>Figure 3. The probability of women’s and men’s presence or absence in news
                        items randomly selected from the MIA-Euroews Corpus.</head>
                </figure> Absence and presence are modeled with a binomial random variable; the plot
                renders the variable with the beta distribution, which maps the discrete values
                (absence or presence) onto a continuous probability space between 0 and 1. The
                closer the mean value is to 0, the more likely that the outcome of the random
                variable is absence (as in case of women); conversely, the closer the mean value is
                to 1, the more likely that the outcome of the random variable is presence (as in
                case of men). </p>
            <p><figure>
                    <graphic url="Pictures/47fe2e8f1eaa697a4fbc0e6c8be42990.png"/>
                    <head>Figure 4. The probability of women’s absence or presence in complete news sheets
                randomly selected from the MIA News Corpus. For further explanation of the plot, see
                the legend under Figure 3.</head>
                </figure></p>
            <p>I will accomplish a live simulation and show that the
                    prior probability of Head and Tail do condition the evidence we gather by
                    tossing the coin (Figure 2). Iwill transpose this idea to the study of women’s presence
                    and absence in the lost corpus of early modern news sheets; I will reframe the
                    problem in terms of Bayesian statistics as follows: women’s presence or absence
                    in the lost whole can be viewed as the prior; the result of bootstrapping is the
                    evidence, which is conditioned by the prior. I will then show how Bayesian
                    formula, Bayesian updating, and the beta distribution as conjugate prior, enable
                    us to develop a plausible model representing women’s presence or absence in the
                    lost whole of early modern news sheets (Gupta &amp; Nadarajah, 2004). I will
                    also demonstrate how this procedure can be used to compare the data corpus split
                    into two periods: pre and post 1600.</p>
            <p>As a
                conclusion, I will evaluate the insights gathered throughout the experiments
                described above in light of the current scholarship on early modern women history. I
                will argue that in handwritten news there was no complete silence about women
                (Figure 4) but the news world was still dominated by the presence of men. I will
                also show that women’s presence in the news did not change throughout the period. I
                will discuss the impact of the methodology presented by highlighting how different
                projects, such as for instance the Euronews Project and the Medici Archive Project,
                applied it to survey early modern information culture. Finally, I will reflect on
                the problem of “revolutionary potential” as framed in the Call: can we revolutionize
                historical research by studying the randomness of sources and archival assets with
                the help of methods from the AI toolbox ? </p>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliogr">
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Aa, Christopher Z. Mooney</author> / <author>Robert Duval</author>  (1994):
                        “Bootstrapping: A nonparametric approach to statistical inference”, in: <hi rend="italic">Journal of the American Statistical Association</hi> 89,
                            <ref target="https://doi.org/10.2307/2290969">https://doi.org/10.2307/2290969</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Barker, Sheila</author> (2016): “'Secret and Uncertain’: A
                        history of Avvisi at the court of the medici grand dukes.” in: Noah Moxham
                        (Ed.), <hi rend="italic">News Networks in Early Modern Europe.
                        </hi>Leiden:Brill 716–738. Brill.
                        http://dx.doi.org/10.1163/9789004277199_032 </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Baron, Sabrina Alcorn</author> / <author>Brendan, Dooley</author>  (2005): <hi rend="italic">The politics of information in early modern Europe</hi>.
                        London: Routledge. </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Bauer</author> / <author>Oswald</author>  (2011): <hi rend="italic">Zeitungen vor
                            der Zeitung: Die Fuggerzeitungen (1568-1605) und das frühmoderne
                            Nachrichtensystem. </hi>Berlin: Akademie Verlag. </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Benson, Pamela. Joseph </author>(2010): <hi rend="italic">Invention of the Renaissance Woman: The Challenge of Female
                            Independence in the Literature and Thought of Italy and England</hi>.
                        University Park, PA: Penn State Press. </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Bradley, Efron</author> (1982): <hi rend="italic">The jackknife,
                            the bootstrap, and other resampling plans.</hi> Society for Industrial
                        and Applied Mathematics. http://dx.doi.org/10.1137/1.9781611970319.ch5. </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Davies, Simon</author> / <author>Fletcher, Puck</author> (2014): <hi rend="italic">News in early modern Europe: Currents and
                        connections</hi>. Leiden: Brill. </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Dooley, Brendan</author> / <author>Kreuze, Wouter</author> / <author>Boerio, Davide</author> / <author>Allori, L.orenzo</author> / <author>Mansutti, Sara</author> / <author>Paltrinieri, Carlotta</author>  (2021): <hi rend="italic">Euronews XML corpus.</hi> 10.5281/zenodo.5524182. </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Droste, Heiko</author> / <author>Salmi-Niklander, Kirsti</author> (2019): <hi rend="italic">Handwritten newspapers: An alternative medium during the
                            early modern and modern periods</hi>. BoD - Books on Demand. </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Gupta, Arjun. K.</author> / <author>Nadarajah, Saralees</author>  (2004): <hi rend="italic">Handbook of beta distribution and its applications</hi>.
                        Boca, Raton: CRC Press. </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Infelise, Mario </author>(2002): <hi rend="italic">Prima dei
                            giornali: Alle origini della pubblica informazione, secoli XVI e XVII.
                        </hi>Rome: Laerza. </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Lo, Albert Y</author>. (1986): “Bayesian statistical inference
                        for sampling a finite population” in: <hi rend="italic">The Annals of
                            Statistics</hi>, 14:3: https://doi.org/10.1214/aos/1176350061 </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Rublack, Ulinka</author> (2001): <hi rend="italic">The crimes of
                            women in early modern Germany</hi>. Oxford: Oxford University Press. </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <hi rend="bold">Wiesner-Hanks, Merry E. </hi>(2019) <hi rend="italic">: Women and gender in early modern Europe.</hi> Cambridge University
                        Press. </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text></TEI>