<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_allPlus.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_allPlus.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Viewing Between the Lines: Representation of Age, Race, Class and Gender in
                    the Illustrations of Dutch-Language Children’s Literature (1800-1940)</title>
                <author n="VanderEeckenPaavoVAN_DER_EECKEN_Paavo_Viewing_Between_the_Lines__Representati.xml"><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-9494-8932" n="VanderEeckenPaavo">
                        <surname>Van der Eecken</surname>
                        <forename>Paavo</forename>
                    </persName><affiliation>University of Antwerp, Belgium</affiliation><email>Paavo.vandereecken@uantwerpen.be</email></author><meeting><date from-iso="2023-07-10" to-iso="2023-07-14"/><title>Digital Humanities 2023. Collaboration as Opportunity</title><placeName>Graz</placeName></meeting>
            </titleStmt>
            
            <publicationStmt><publisher><orgName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1137284463">Zentrum für Informationsmodellierung
                    - Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities, Karl-Franzens-Universität
                    Graz</orgName></publisher><date when="2023">2023</date><pubPlace>Graz</pubPlace><availability><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">Creative Commons BY
                    4.0</licence></availability></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title>Digital Humanities 2023: Book of Abstracts</title><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-9256-0958"><forename>Walter</forename><surname>Scholger</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>University of Graz</orgName><placeName>Graz, Austria</placeName></affiliation><email>walter.scholger@uni-graz.at</email></editor><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-1726-1712"><forename>Georg</forename><surname>Vogeler</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>University of Graz</orgName><placeName>Graz, Austria</placeName></affiliation><email>georg.vogeler@uni-graz.at</email></editor><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-3919-993X"><forename>Toma</forename><surname>Tasovac</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>Belgrade Center for Digital Humanities</orgName><placeName>Belgrade, Serbia</placeName></affiliation><email>ttasovac@humanistika.org</email></editor><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-4593-059X"><forename>Anne</forename><surname>Baillot</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>Le Mans Université</orgName><placeName>Le Mans, France</placeName></affiliation><email>anne.baillot@univ-lemans.fr</email></editor><respStmt><resp>Data Management</resp><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0009-0007-9019-8215"><forename>Elisabeth</forename><surname>Raunig</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Management</resp><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-1438-3236"><forename>Martina</forename><surname>Scholger</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Management</resp><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-9116-0402"><forename>Elisabeth</forename><surname>Steiner</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Curation</resp><persName><forename>Johanna</forename><surname>Ofenauer</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Curation</resp><persName><forename>Christina</forename><surname>Burgstaller</surname></persName></respStmt><idno type="DOI">10.5281/zenodo.7961822</idno></seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="DHCONVALIDATOR" version="1.22">
                    <label>DHConvalidator</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc><abstract><p>This research in progress studies how human characters are represented along the lines of age, race, class and gender in the illustrations of historical Dutch-language children's literature (1800-1940).</p></abstract><langUsage><language ident="en">English</language></langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="category">
                    <term>Paper</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="subcategory">
                    <term>Short Presentation</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="keywords">
                    <term>Children's Literature</term>
                    <term>Illustrations</term>
                    <term>Bias</term>
                    <term>Representation</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="topics">
                    <term>digital research infrastructures development and analysis</term>
                    <term>electronic literature production and analysis</term>
                    <term>image processing and analysis</term>
                    <term>Art history</term>
                    <term>Gender and sexuality studies</term>
                    <term>Literary studies</term>
                    
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <p>Recent debate about what to do with books that present
                    outdated or disfavored views has shown that literary representation is a highly
                    controversial issue. Children’s books often depict a fictional world, so one
                    could wonder why the content of those works matters at all. The answer lies in
                    the fact that books for children reflect specific worldviews. This turns the
                    process of reading into a contact zone, where readers engage with different
                    ideas about themselves and the world (Čermáková / Mahlberg 2021). It is a
                    dynamic process, where some social norms are internalized, while others are not
                    (Tatar 2009; Brown 2017). The books thus influence to a significant extent how
                    (young) readers perceive reality, themselves, and others (Van den Bossche /
                    Klomberg 2020).  </p>
            <p>Despite the significance of representation in books for
                    children, we are still missing key information on how it is given shape exactly.
                    To start with, studies on biased representation are scarce for Dutch-language
                    children’s literature. This often causes scholars to revert to research from the
                    Anglo-Saxon world. Furthermore, scholars have focused primarily on the textual
                    elements, with only occasional attention to the visuals (De Bodt / Kapelle
                    2003), despite research which has shown that visual biases are particularly hard
                    to shed (Joosen 2018; Nel 2017). Thirdly, previous studies have mainly relied on
                    the close reading of a limited number of mostly canonical works. In doing so,
                    they have overlooked the presence of other children’s books circulating the
                    literary market. Lastly, the roots of those biased representations have been
                    understudied. One often hears the argument that historical cultural artifacts
                    were “products of their time”, but this begs the question: how well do we
                    actually know that time period? As it turns out, we often lack the necessary
                    knowledge to make substantiated claims.  </p>
            <p>In this study, we strive for a better understanding of the
                    historical evolution of representation along the lines of age, race, class, and
                    gender. We do this by analyzing a diverse corpus of 1,000 illustrated children’s
                    books published in Dutch from the period 1800-1940. Taking a digital approach to
                    this question helps us to overcome the disciplinary canon and to fill in the
                    glaring gaps that have been mentioned above. Furthermore, it allows us to
                    analyze how results from a Dutch-speaking context compare to studies based on
                    other language areas. In doing so, this project answers the call by Mansour and
                    Martin for studies situated in different cultures to become conversant with one
                    another (2020). This form of collaborative action can help provide a solid basis
                    for the discussions on representation that are taking place in our current
                    societies. </p>
            <p>In the first phase of this research, a team of annotators
                has drawn bounding boxes around all human characters present in the illustrations
                and assigned them attributes according to their age, race, class, and gender. At a
                surface level, this provides us with numbers on the (under)representation of certain
                social groups in illustrated children’s literature. Our preliminary results show,
                for example, how the gender imbalance in the illustrations, with close to two male
                characters for every female character, in this period is analogous to the one
                reported for English books from the start of the 21st century (Hamilton et al.
                2006). In line with what Hamilton et al. found, this discrepancy is more pronounced
                for middle aged characters than it is for younger ones. By the time of the
                conference, we will complete a statistical analysis of the nominal data, where we
                will pay close attention to the intersectional nature of those different
                representations.  </p>
            <p>Furthermore, we will provide an analysis of the placement
                    of different characters, because representation goes beyond absolute numbers.
                    The positioning of characters in the illustration, for example, plays a big role
                    in what Goffman would call visual stereotyping (1976). By creating heat maps of
                    the annotated bounding boxes, we will analyze how prominent certain characters
                    are in the illustrations. Important elements in this regard are the sizes of the
                    bounding boxes and their centrality in the picture. By analyzing those features,
                    we can establish not only who is often portrayed in children’s literature, but
                    also shed light on how this portrayal is given shape.  </p>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliogr">
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Brown, Molly</author> (2017): “Children’s literature matters.”,
                        in <hi rend="italic">English Academy Review</hi> 34, 1: 8-22. </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Čermáková, Anna</author> / <author>Mahlberg, Michaela</author> (2021): “Gender
                        inequality and female body language in children’s literature.”, in <hi rend="italic">Digital Scholarship in the Humanities</hi> 36: ii72-ii77. </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>De Bodt, Saskia</author> / <author>Kapelle, Jeroen</author> (2003): <hi rend="italic">Prentenboeken, ideologie en illustratie</hi> 1890-1950.
                        Ludion. </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Goffman, Erving </author>(1976): <hi rend="italic">Gender
                            Commercials. In Gender advertisements</hi>. London: Palgrave. </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Hamilton, Mykol</author> / <author>Anderson, David</author> / <author>Broaddus, Michelle</author> / <author>Young, Kate</author> (2006): “Gender stereotyping and under-representation
                        of female characters in 200 popular children’s picture books: A twenty-first
                        century update.”, in  <hi rend="italic">Sex roles</hi> 55, 11: 757-765. </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Joosen, Vanessa </author>(2018): <hi rend="italic">Adulthood in
                            Children's Literature</hi>. Bloomsbury Publishing. </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Mansour, Nadia</author> / <author>Martin, Michelle H.</author> (2020): “What Can
                        Danish Multicultural Children’s Literature and African American Children’s
                        Literature Learn from Each Other?”, in <hi rend="italic">Literary Histories
                            in Dialogue. </hi>
                        <hi rend="italic">Barnboken</hi>, 43. </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Nel, Philip </author>(2017): <hi rend="italic">Was the Cat in the Hat Black? </hi>
                        <hi rend="italic">The hidden racism of children's literature, and the need
                            for diverse books</hi>. Oxford University Press. </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Van den Bossche, Sara</author> / <author>Klomberg, Anne</author>  (2020): <hi rend="italic">Jeugdliteratuur door de lens van etnisch-culturele
                            diversiteit</hi>. Eburon. </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Tatar, Maria </author>(2009): <hi rend="italic">Enchanted
                            hunters: The power of stories in childhood</hi>. WW Norton &amp;
                        Company. </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text></TEI>