<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_allPlus.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_allPlus.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Intersectional Feminist Revolutions in Digital Humanities – approaches,
                    histories, and methods </title>
                <author n="WebbSharonWEBB_Sharon_Intersectional_Feminist_Revolutions_in_Digital_H.xml"><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-4148-7324" n="WebbSharon">
                        <surname>Webb</surname>
                        <forename>Sharon</forename>
                    </persName><affiliation>University of Sussex, United Kingdom</affiliation><email>sharon.webb@sussex.ac.uk</email></author><meeting><date from-iso="2023-07-10" to-iso="2023-07-14"/><title>Digital Humanities 2023. Collaboration as Opportunity</title><placeName>Graz</placeName></meeting>
                <author n="ChevalierCcileWEBB_Sharon_Intersectional_Feminist_Revolutions_in_Digital_H.xml"><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-4764-1078" n="ChevalierCcile">
                        <surname>Chevalier</surname>
                        <forename>Cécile</forename>
                    </persName><affiliation>University of Sussex, United Kingdom</affiliation><email>c.chevalier@sussex.ac.uk</email></author><meeting><date from-iso="2023-07-10" to-iso="2023-07-14"/><title>Digital Humanities 2023. Collaboration as Opportunity</title><placeName>Graz</placeName></meeting>
                <author n="NajiJeneenWEBB_Sharon_Intersectional_Feminist_Revolutions_in_Digital_H.xml"><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-7479-0143" n="NajiJeneen">
                        <surname>Naji</surname>
                        <forename>Jeneen</forename>
                    </persName><affiliation>Maynooth University, Ireland</affiliation><email>jeneen.naji@mu.ie</email></author><meeting><date from-iso="2023-07-10" to-iso="2023-07-14"/><title>Digital Humanities 2023. Collaboration as Opportunity</title><placeName>Graz</placeName></meeting>
                <author n="FubaraManuelIreneWEBB_Sharon_Intersectional_Feminist_Revolutions_in_Digital_H.xml"><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-7373-5302" n="FubaraManuelIrene">
                        <surname>Fubara-Manuel</surname>
                        <forename>Irene</forename>
                    </persName><affiliation>University of Sussex, United Kingdom</affiliation><email>i.fubara-manuel@sussex.ac.uk</email></author><meeting><date from-iso="2023-07-10" to-iso="2023-07-14"/><title>Digital Humanities 2023. Collaboration as Opportunity</title><placeName>Graz</placeName></meeting>
                <author n="FoxIzzyWEBB_Sharon_Intersectional_Feminist_Revolutions_in_Digital_H.xml"><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-3705-1904" n="FoxIzzy">
                        <surname>Fox</surname>
                        <forename>Izzy</forename>
                    </persName><affiliation>Maynooth University, Ireland</affiliation><email>izzy.fox@mu.ie</email></author><meeting><date from-iso="2023-07-10" to-iso="2023-07-14"/><title>Digital Humanities 2023. Collaboration as Opportunity</title><placeName>Graz</placeName></meeting>
                <author n="HillLaurenceWEBB_Sharon_Intersectional_Feminist_Revolutions_in_Digital_H.xml"><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-6859-5106" n="HillLaurence">
                        <surname>Hill</surname>
                        <forename>Laurence</forename>
                    </persName><affiliation>University of Sussex, United Kingdom</affiliation><email>l.c.hill@sussex.ac.uk</email></author><meeting><date from-iso="2023-07-10" to-iso="2023-07-14"/><title>Digital Humanities 2023. Collaboration as Opportunity</title><placeName>Graz</placeName></meeting>
            </titleStmt>
            
            <publicationStmt><publisher><orgName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1137284463">Zentrum für Informationsmodellierung
                    - Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities, Karl-Franzens-Universität
                    Graz</orgName></publisher><date when="2023">2023</date><pubPlace>Graz</pubPlace><availability><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">Creative Commons BY
                    4.0</licence></availability></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title>Digital Humanities 2023: Book of Abstracts</title><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-9256-0958"><forename>Walter</forename><surname>Scholger</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>University of Graz</orgName><placeName>Graz, Austria</placeName></affiliation><email>walter.scholger@uni-graz.at</email></editor><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-1726-1712"><forename>Georg</forename><surname>Vogeler</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>University of Graz</orgName><placeName>Graz, Austria</placeName></affiliation><email>georg.vogeler@uni-graz.at</email></editor><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-3919-993X"><forename>Toma</forename><surname>Tasovac</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>Belgrade Center for Digital Humanities</orgName><placeName>Belgrade, Serbia</placeName></affiliation><email>ttasovac@humanistika.org</email></editor><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-4593-059X"><forename>Anne</forename><surname>Baillot</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>Le Mans Université</orgName><placeName>Le Mans, France</placeName></affiliation><email>anne.baillot@univ-lemans.fr</email></editor><respStmt><resp>Data Management</resp><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0009-0007-9019-8215"><forename>Elisabeth</forename><surname>Raunig</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Management</resp><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-1438-3236"><forename>Martina</forename><surname>Scholger</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Management</resp><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-9116-0402"><forename>Elisabeth</forename><surname>Steiner</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Curation</resp><persName><forename>Johanna</forename><surname>Ofenauer</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Curation</resp><persName><forename>Christina</forename><surname>Burgstaller</surname></persName></respStmt><idno type="DOI">10.5281/zenodo.7961822</idno></seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="DHCONVALIDATOR" version="1.22">
                    <label>DHConvalidator</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc><abstract><p>This panel provides a broad overview of the Full Stack Feminism project and its activities. It includes a detailed analysis of feminist approaches to practice-based research methodologies, interview collation, listening, and storytelling, that arise from our investigations into public DH creation processes from back end, to middleware, to front end.</p></abstract><langUsage><language ident="en">English</language></langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="category">
                    <term>Paper</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="subcategory">
                    <term>Panel</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="keywords">
                    <term>feminist digital humanities</term>
                    <term>queer digital humanities</term>
                    <term>intersectional feminism</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="topics">
                    <term>meta-criticism (reflections on digital humanities and humanities
                        computing)</term>
                    <term>public humanities collaborations and methods</term>
                    <term>Feminist studies</term>
                    <term>Gender and sexuality studies</term>
                    
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div type="div1">
                <head>Panel Overview</head>
                <p>How has, and how can, intersectional feminist methods,
                    praxis, and theories shape digital humanities?  How can we, as a digital
                    humanities community, embrace and embed feminist thinking into our everyday work
                    practices and in the projects we develop and collaborate on? What tools and
                    methods do we need to create more inclusive and socially aware technological
                    infrastructures, systems, and code? These are the questions being asked by ‘Full
                    Stack Feminism in Digital Humanities’ (FSFDH), a two-year project funded jointly
                    by UK and Irish research councils. Full Stack Feminism (FSF) is akin to Tara
                    McPherson’s (2018:27) approach and examination of ‘designing for difference’.
                    This includes thinking about and responding to feminist concerns, but also, as
                    Alan Liu (McPherson 2018:28) states, to the ‘full register of society,
                    economics, politics, and culture’. FSF is a trans, inter disciplinary research
                    project which develops an intersectional feminist framework for digital arts and
                    humanities (DH) practice and research.  The ‘Full Stack’ metaphor accounts for a
                    commitment to review and critique all stages of the development and data life
                    cycle – from design to implementation, from the processes of datafication to
                    dissemination, critiquing every stack from the code right through the
                    infrastructure layers above. This panel reflects upon the feminist revolution in
                    digital humanities and of the feminist foundations in DH upon which the project
                    is built.</p>
                <p>Digital humanities (DH) have a history of challenging
                    the status quo and of embracing alternative means of knowledge production. As
                    such, the panel explores how intersectional feminism methods and praxis can help
                    to develop a more open, and inclusive, DH. The opportunity for collaboration in
                    this space is vast and beneficiaries broad. This panel, and the project
                    discussed, is therefore a response to the varied calls within DH for more
                    inclusive practices, with broader community engagement across intersectional
                    lines of identity politics.  It explores how feminist epistemology, praxis and
                    methods can contribute to shaping DH as an intellectual field which responds to
                    structural inequalities within and beyond its boundaries</p>
                <p>The panel is comprised of members of the FSFDM team
                    and explores the various ways in which the research project collaborates across
                    academic disciplines and different communities of interest. We provide a broad
                    overview of the project and its activities as well as more detailed analysis of
                    feminist approaches to practice-based research methodologies, interview
                    collation, listening, and storytelling, that arise out of our investigations.
                    The panel will explore elements of our FSF framework, which consists of three
                    stacks: (1) data and archives; (2) infrastructure, tools and code; and (3)
                    dissemination, integration and access - specifically explored through Webb,
                    Chevalier and Naji’s contributions. From this foundation panel members,
                    Fubara-Manuel and Fox, discuss feminist methodologies and praxis such as
                    critical (con)fabulation and story-telling, both methods of decentrying and
                    narratorial recreation or empowerment. Lastly, given the central role of
                    critical digital arts practice within the project, the panel concludes with
                    Hill’s reflections on the curatorial role in remaking, or revisioning future
                    heritage. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Full Stack Histories and Foundations – Sharon Webb</hi></p>
                <p>Full Stack Feminism responds to calls across academia
                    and society to rethink the way in which we approach the production, creation,
                    development and roll out of technology. It stems from ongoing collaborations
                    between project partners in Ireland and the UK, and is part of a strategic
                    effort by Irish and UK funding councils for closer co-ordination on Digital
                    Humanities across the two political entities, across political divides. Webb’s
                    panel contribution therefore, describes the foundations of the project,
                    acknowledging its roots in feminist revolutions in DH, as well as in the history
                    of feminist interventions across the sub-discipline, Feminist Science and
                    Technology Studies, or STS.  As D’Ignazio and Klein (2016) state, feminist STS,
                    which developed in the 1970s and 1980s, ‘allows us to see how all knowledge is
                    situated, [and] how certain perspectives are excluded from the current knowledge
                    regime’. FSF takes seriously the history of exclusion from current knowledge
                    regimes, now embedded across our digital knowledge infrastructures, and takes
                    inspiration from bell hooks' (1984) 'from margin to centre' by aspiring to
                    include community voices as a location of expert knowledge within the project.
                    It reflects current work within DH and cognate fields that work to decentre
                    dominant voices and perspectives by embedding intersectional feminist praxis
                    across project life-cycles. Webb’s panel contribution will explore the “full
                    stack” metaphor utilised in this project and provide an overview of work within
                    Stack 1: Data and Archives. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Feminist Building and Listening - Cécile Chevalier</hi></p>
                <p>The second panel contribution introduces elements of
                    the work and rationale within stack 2, ‘infrastructures, tools and code’ . It
                    engages with deconstructing machine learning, and technological eco-systems
                    whilst exploring alternative computational systems as a mean to gain autonomy.
                    Chevalier’s presentation explores alternative forms of building, sustainable and
                    autonomous, collective memory and community-led heritage, specifically from
                    marginalized, oppressed, or altogether omitted histories. Collectively, we
                    understand that in the computational automomy is (im)possible. Autonomy requires
                    a sense of position and orientations, to be able to know where compromise can
                    take place, so one can have the ability shape alternative models and
                    pathways.</p>
                <p>Stack 2 recognises the need to return to a human foci
                    and for the basic need of listening to be considered as a necessary tool in
                    navigating inherited and future computational bias. In this respect,
                    Chevalier‘‘s panel contribution considers feminist listening as framework for
                    intersectional feminist thinking that is <hi rend="italic">making trouble</hi>
                    (hooks 1989, Butler 1999, Ahmed 2016); it creates resistance against oppressions
                    related to social identities, and contributes to forms of liberation as becoming
                    a <hi rend="italic">collectivity of trouble</hi> (Butler 1999, Ahmed 2016). This
                    can be seen as trouble as: a dislodgement of mechanisms of power; social and
                    cultural imaginary to an alternate past, present &amp;/or future; the
                    mobilisation of collective expressions and recognitions. Drawing from concepts
                    of 'freedom of listening' (Lacey, 2013, LaBelle,2021), feminist listening evokes
                    agency of 'trouble' as a conscious act, that requires shifting acoustic order
                    with orientation and politics of location. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Digital Art as a Feminist Interface - Jeneen Naji </hi></p>
                <p>The last stack in the FSF framework is concerned with
                    Access, Experience and Integration. Stack 3 can be considered the “front end”
                    and relates to the ways in which digital tools, resources, and ‘archives’ are
                    accessed and experienced by users, by consumers, by archivists, and ways in
                    which knowledge and digital cultural heritage is accessible or indeed
                    inaccessible. In all cases accessibility in digital archives is mediated through
                    the interface, interfaces matter and are an important entry point into DH for
                    the public. For example, Ruberg et. Al (2018: 110) note that, as feminist
                    scholars they recognise that computational tools are not apolitical, they have
                    an impact, they structure meaning, and visualisations craft interpretation. As
                    such an interface can be seen as a space in which meaningful embodied
                    interaction takes place in a networked environment, or an interface can be seen
                    as a component of a digital work in which case it operates more like an index to
                    specific content (Drucker 2019, 3). Naji’s panel contribution as such discusses
                    feminist HCI as a design methodology that seeks to incorporate feminist values
                    such as inclusion, diversity and social justice in the development of
                    interactive media. FSFDH’s stack 3 therefore proposes that as per McPherson
                    (2018) the use of feminist HCI methodologies (Bardzell 2010) can make the case
                    for digital art texts to operate as archival interfaces in order to maximise
                    public understanding in DH and create a milieux for intersectional cultural
                    heritage.  </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Critical (Con)Fabulations: Fabricating Other Worlds in the
                        Meantime - Irene Fubara-Manuel </hi></p>
                <p>There are gaps in archives that the collection of
                    artefacts will never close without addressing power relations. Power deepens the
                    gaps of the archive through the renarration of stories that then build and
                    mobilise ways of organising the world. Such ways of organising the world are
                    embedded in the design of technologies that continue the cycle of archival
                    violence. The theorist and historian Saidiya Hartman (2008) has posed critical
                    fabulation as a method to test the limits of archives through combining archival
                    renarration with fiction. To critically fabulate is to tell stories from
                    archives in ways that not only address the gaps but also speak truth to power in
                    the present and connect to other futures. Borrowing Hartman’s proposed method,
                    Fubara-Manuel’s panel contribution considers the opportunities of critical
                    (con)fabulation as an intersectional feminist intervention in digital
                    humanities. It asks what worlds might emanate when those othered through the
                    gaps of the archive, not only critically confabulate but also collaboratively
                    fabricate technologies that best serve them. Connecting stacks one (digital
                    archives) and two (code and infrastructure) this presentation will flesh out
                    intersectional feminist and queer theories of fabulation. It will then expand on
                    creative practices that implement the methods of critical confabulation. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Storytelling as Embodied Knowledge: De-centring Dominant
                        Perspectives in DH - Izzy Fox </hi></p>
                <p>Fox’ panel contribution explores how research project
                    recognises storytelling as a mode of knowledge production and collaborates with
                    communities traditionally marginalised within DH. This approach is one of the
                    ways in which the project actively serves to decentre dominant perspectives,
                    histories, technologies and practices. The importance of storytelling as a
                    feminist epistemology is also reflected in the findings from interviews with
                    digital practitioners, including artists, archivists, scholars and coders, whose
                    work reflects an intersectional feminist ethos. Furthermore, the interviewees
                    understand that the act of storytelling, through their archival, artistic or
                    scholarly practice, is an embodied endeavour, because: “In the process of
                    storytelling…The speech is seen, heard, smelled, tasted and touched” (Trinh
                    1989: 121). Archiving oral histories; documenting dance practice; and animating
                    archival artefacts represent some of the ways in which the interviewees
                    foreground embodiment through processes of digitally-mediated storytelling to
                    centre marginalised lives, experiences and knowledges. The interviewees are
                    drawn from community and scholarly contacts, as well as the diasporic
                    connections, of the research team. While the knowledge, or knowledges, of the
                    team is diverse and intersectional, we understand that biases and exclusions may
                    exist due to our own positionality, within academic institutions, living in the
                    UK and Ireland. In this sense, we draw on Donna Haraway’s term “situated
                    knowledges” (1988), which recognises that knowledge is shaped by who we are and
                    the contexts in which we exist. Acknowledging this allows us to better
                    understand and respond to the stories retold in our project interviews.  </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Curating an Unsettling: non-human assemblages and future
                        heritages - Laurence Hill</hi></p>
                <p>If the work of the project is in part to decentre
                    dominant narratives in the field of DH, the curatorial role requires reflection
                    on the state of the (digital) art. The decentring of the predominantly cishet,
                    male, technocentric and western-oriented epistemologies within which digital art
                    is largely situated invites an alternative curatorial collaboration. This
                    unseating (Preciado 2020: 20) in curatorial practice requires collaboration with
                    a non-human assemblage - a concept in which technology is allied with
                    individuals from groups whose identities have been historically categorised as
                    less than human through frameworks of social and scientific racism, homophobia,
                    transphobia, cissexism, disablism and neurotypicality. The curatorial
                    collaboration with the non-human assemblage does the work of decentring the
                    predominant epistemologies of digital art by ‘undoing and unsettling’ them, an
                    act of disruption and activism through curatorial practice. As such Hill’s panel
                    contributions draws upon the concept of ‘undoing and unsettling’ from Katherine
                    McKittrick’s work about the writer and cultural critic Sylvia Wynter (McKittrick
                    2015: 2). This ‘undoing and unsettling’ is generative in reconsidering the
                    frameworks and contexts in which digital art is produced and presented. As FSFDH
                    demonstrates, the market and cultural dominance of a small number of tech
                    companies requires a different approach than overnight coups - it requires acts
                    of undoing and unsettling, of unpicking. If the heritage to come is being
                    written now, the result of this interventive collaboration, which includes
                    curation, is a redoing, a revisioning of a future heritage that is
                    revolutionarily different.</p>
            </div>

        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliogr">
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Ahmed, Sara</author> (2016): “Interview with Judith Butler” in: 
                            <hi rend="italic">Sexualities</hi>,  <hi rend="italic">19</hi>(4),
                        482–492. </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Bardzell, Shaowen</author> (2010): “Feminist HCI: taking stock
                        and outlining an agenda for design” in: <hi rend="italic">Proceedings of the
                            SIGCHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI '10)</hi>.
                        Association for Computing Machinery: New York, USA, 1301–110 </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Butler, Judith</author> (1999): <hi rend="italic">Gender
                            Trouble: Feminism and the Subversion of Identity</hi>. London:
                        Routledge. </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>D’Ignazio, Catherine</author> / <author>Lauren F. Klein</author>  (2016):
                        “Feminist Data Visualization” in: <hi rend="italic">Workshop on
                            Visualization for the Digital Humanities at EEE VIS Conference</hi>. </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Haraway, Donna </author>(1988): “Situated
                        knowledges: the science question in feminism and the privilege of partial
                        perspective”, in:
                        <hi rend="italic">Feminist Studies </hi>14, 3: 575-599. </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Hartman, Saidiya</author> (2008): “Venus in two acts,” in: <hi rend="italic">Small Axe: A Caribbean Journal of Criticism</hi>, 12, 2:
                        1–14. </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>hooks, bell</author>
                         (1984
                        <hi rend="italic">)</hi>
                        :
                        <hi rend="italic"> Feminist Theory: From Margin to Center</hi>
                        . London: Pluto Press.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>hooks, bell </author>
                        (1989): 
                        <hi rend="italic">Thinking Feminist, Thinking Black</hi>
                        . Massachusetts: South End Press.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>LaBelle, Brandon</author> (2021): <hi rend="italic">Acoustic
                            Justice. Listening, Performativity, and the Work of Reorientation</hi>.
                        London: Bloomsbury Publishing. </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Lacey, Kate</author>
                         (2013): 
                        <hi rend="italic">Listening Publics: The Politics and
                            Experience of Listening in the Media Age</hi>
                        . Cambridge: Polity Press.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>McKittrick, Katherine </author>
                        (2015): 
                        <hi rend="italic">Sylvia Wynter: On Being Human as Praxis</hi>
                        . Durham: Duke University Press
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>McPherson, Tara</author> (2018):
                        <hi rend="italic">Feminist in a Software Lab: Difference + Design. </hi>Massachusetts
                        :Harvard University Press </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Preciado, Paul</author> (2020):
                        <hi rend="italic"> Can the Monster Speak?</hi> London:
                        Fitzcarraldo Editions </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Ruberg, Bonnie</author> / <author>Boyd, Jason</author> / <author>Howe, James</author>  (2018):
                        “Toward a Queer Digital Humanities”, in : Losh, Elizabeth/ Wernimont,
                        Jacqueline (eds): <hi rend="italic">Bodies of Information: Intersectional
                            Feminism and the Digital Humanities</hi>. Minneapolis: University of
                        Minnesota Press 108-128. </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Smith, Terry</author> (2021): <hi rend="italic">Curating the
                            Complex &amp; The Open Strike</hi>. London: Sternberg Press </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Trinh, Thi Minh-Ha</author> (1989): <hi rend="italic">Woman,
                            Native, Other: Writing Postcoloniality and Feminism</hi>. Vol. 503.
                        Indiana University Press.   </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text></TEI>