<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_allPlus.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_allPlus.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Tutorial - Collaborative approaches to discourse: Music scholarship using
                    performance recordings and Linked Data annotations</title>
                <author n="LewisDavidWEIGL_David_M__Tutorial___Collaborative_approaches_to_discou.xml"><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-4151-0499" n="LewisDavid">
                        <surname>Lewis</surname>
                        <forename>David</forename>
                    </persName><affiliation>Oxford e-Research Centre, University of Oxford</affiliation><email>david.lewis@oerc.ox.ac.uk</email></author><meeting><date from-iso="2023-07-10" to-iso="2023-07-14"/><title>Digital Humanities 2023. Collaboration as Opportunity</title><placeName>Graz</placeName></meeting>
                <author n="PageKevinWEIGL_David_M__Tutorial___Collaborative_approaches_to_discou.xml"><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-1668-6540" n="PageKevin">
                        <surname>Page</surname>
                        <forename>Kevin</forename>
                    </persName><affiliation>Oxford e-Research Centre, University of Oxford</affiliation><email>kevin.page@oerc.ox.ac.uk</email></author><meeting><date from-iso="2023-07-10" to-iso="2023-07-14"/><title>Digital Humanities 2023. Collaboration as Opportunity</title><placeName>Graz</placeName></meeting>
                <author n="VanderHartChandaWEIGL_David_M__Tutorial___Collaborative_approaches_to_discou.xml"><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-2055-273X" n="VanderHartChanda">
                        <surname>VanderHart</surname>
                        <forename>Chanda</forename>
                    </persName><affiliation>mdw - University of Music and Performing Arts Vienna,
                        Austria</affiliation><email>vanderhart@mdw.ac.at</email></author><meeting><date from-iso="2023-07-10" to-iso="2023-07-14"/><title>Digital Humanities 2023. Collaboration as Opportunity</title><placeName>Graz</placeName></meeting>
                <author n="WeiglDavidMWEIGL_David_M__Tutorial___Collaborative_approaches_to_discou.xml"><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-1502-1528" n="WeiglDavidM">
                        <surname>Weigl</surname>
                        <forename>David M.</forename>
                    </persName><affiliation>mdw - University of Music and Performing Arts Vienna,
                        Austria</affiliation><email>weigl@mdw.ac.at</email></author><meeting><date from-iso="2023-07-10" to-iso="2023-07-14"/><title>Digital Humanities 2023. Collaboration as Opportunity</title><placeName>Graz</placeName></meeting>
            </titleStmt>
            
            <publicationStmt><publisher><orgName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1137284463">Zentrum für Informationsmodellierung
                    - Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities, Karl-Franzens-Universität
                    Graz</orgName></publisher><date when="2023">2023</date><pubPlace>Graz</pubPlace><availability><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">Creative Commons BY
                    4.0</licence></availability></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title>Digital Humanities 2023: Book of Abstracts</title><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-9256-0958"><forename>Walter</forename><surname>Scholger</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>University of Graz</orgName><placeName>Graz, Austria</placeName></affiliation><email>walter.scholger@uni-graz.at</email></editor><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-1726-1712"><forename>Georg</forename><surname>Vogeler</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>University of Graz</orgName><placeName>Graz, Austria</placeName></affiliation><email>georg.vogeler@uni-graz.at</email></editor><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-3919-993X"><forename>Toma</forename><surname>Tasovac</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>Belgrade Center for Digital Humanities</orgName><placeName>Belgrade, Serbia</placeName></affiliation><email>ttasovac@humanistika.org</email></editor><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-4593-059X"><forename>Anne</forename><surname>Baillot</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>Le Mans Université</orgName><placeName>Le Mans, France</placeName></affiliation><email>anne.baillot@univ-lemans.fr</email></editor><respStmt><resp>Data Management</resp><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0009-0007-9019-8215"><forename>Elisabeth</forename><surname>Raunig</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Management</resp><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-1438-3236"><forename>Martina</forename><surname>Scholger</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Management</resp><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-9116-0402"><forename>Elisabeth</forename><surname>Steiner</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Curation</resp><persName><forename>Johanna</forename><surname>Ofenauer</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Curation</resp><persName><forename>Christina</forename><surname>Burgstaller</surname></persName></respStmt><idno type="DOI">10.5281/zenodo.7961822</idno></seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="DHCONVALIDATOR" version="1.22">
                    <label>DHConvalidator</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc><abstract><p>Participants are invited to explore modelling and annotation through exercises demonstrating music research conducted in Oxford and Vienna. After hands-on ontology design exercises with pen and paper, they are introduced to cutting-edge digital tooling and led through research processes of an ongoing project investigating the Vienna Philharmonic’s New Year’s Concerts.</p></abstract><langUsage><language ident="en">English</language></langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="category">
                    <term>Paper</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="subcategory">
                    <term>Pre-Conference Workshop and Tutorial</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="keywords">
                    <term>Annotation</term>
                    <term>Data Modelling</term>
                    <term>Digital Musicology</term>
                    <term>Multimedia</term>
                    <term>Music Performance</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="topics">
                    <term>annotation structures</term>
                    <term>systems</term>
                    <term>and methods</term>
                    <term>data modeling</term>
                    <term>linked (open) data</term>
                    <term>music and sound digitization</term>
                    <term>encoding</term>
                    <term>and analysis</term>
                    <term>Computer science</term>
                    <term>Humanities computing</term>
                    <term>Media studies</term>
                    <term>Musicology</term>
                    
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div type="div1">
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <p>In the arts and humanities, the evidence on which we
                    build our discourse comes in a multitude of forms and formats – not just text,
                    but a wide range of images, sound and video recordings and specialised
                    information formats. The elements that we discuss are often concepts and ideas
                    that this evidential material may embody and exemplify, but which are not wholly
                    contained by that material. For example, a musical theme can occur multiple
                    times in a piece, in multiple forms and, for each of those occurrences, will be
                    found in recordings and scores made from different versions of the work. </p>
                <p>Traditionally concerned almost exclusively with score
                    study and the deification of the text, musicological analyses increasingly
                    consider a wider set of properties, particularly those of performance. These
                    include musical structures at many different levels of abstraction, including
                    performance study, interpretation, questions of agency, socio-political and
                    historical contexts and other forms of extra-musical evidence (such as reception
                    history and prior musicological scholarship). Current work in musicology shares
                    this need to incorporate broader aspects and contexts into the analysis of
                    objects of interest, beyond the traditional narrow focus on ‘text’, with various
                    branches of the humanities. </p>
                <p>The study of these facets, alongside their complex
                    interactions, is enriched by scholarly collaboration across disciplinary
                    boundaries and requires a suitably flexible, rhizomatic approach to modelling.
                    Where models such as FRBR address issues of abstraction at the level of the work
                    or book, there has been little explicit work on the equivalent for internal
                    musical structures. Building on technical and conceptual standards, we have
                    developed a Linked Data model that supports the annotation of units of musical
                    content at the level of abstraction appropriate to that annotation. Our model
                    was devised in close collaboration between musicologists and digital modelling
                    experts through intensive workshopping, implementation and testing. </p>
                <p>By building this model using Linked Data, we enable
                    both evidence components, as well as scholarly observations and assertions
                    established through music research to be distinctly expressed, addressed, and
                    interconnected. These properties allow the created data to be examined,
                    reassessed, and reinterpreted in an ongoing scholarly conversation, inviting
                    lively collaboration as well as contributions from diverging perspectives.  </p>
                <p>Our development of the Music Annotation Ontology arose
                    from the Beethoven in the House project, which examines music in multiple
                    arrangements – particularly nineteenth century concert music adapted by
                    contemporaries for a home environment. In the first part of our tutorial, we use
                    practical group exercises to explore the semantics of music annotation, based on
                    the project’s use cases. We go beyond models that indicate co-ordination of ‘the
                    same content’ in different media to ask questions about the sorts of
                    relationships and concepts that scholars and performers might want to talk
                    about.</p>
                <p>In the second part of the tutorial, we challenge
                    participants to employ the model in hands-on exercises focussed on recorded
                    music materials from the New Year’s Concerts of the Vienna Philharmonics,
                    providing a glimpse into the methods developed within Signature Sound Vienna, an
                    ongoing research project at the mdw – University of Music and Performing Arts
                    Vienna. During this exercise, participants will make use of software tooling
                    supporting close listening and mark-up of aligned collections of performance
                    recordings. The resulting annotations feed into the Linked Data model introduced
                    in the first half of the tutorial, allowing participants to compare and contrast
                    their discoveries with those of their colleagues, demonstrating how this
                    approach facilitates a collective scholarly discourse. </p>
                <p>Beyond the context of classical music study in which
                    it is demonstrated, the presented model has wider applications to the arts and
                    humanities wherever objects of interest are most appropriately understood in
                    connection with their surrounding layers of discourse and analysis. Having
                    explored the model and its application, the tutorial will close with a
                    discussion of these extended scenarios, motivated by attendees’ own projects and
                    research.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="div1">
                <head>Tutorial audience</head>
                <p>The tutorial will be a practical exploration of Linked
                    Data modelling and annotation as applied to multimedia materials. </p>
                <p>The tutorial will use musical materials describing
                    performances, which are of particular interest to musicologists, but from which
                    general principles can be applied to other fields involving performance and/or
                    using multimedia sources. No specialist musical knowledge is required, although
                    an interest and enthusiasm for music performance is welcomed!</p>
                <p>The tutorial will be viable with a group size up to
                    approximately 20 attendees, based on past experience of modelling workshops at
                    DH and elsewhere. We would expect the number of registrations to be in the range
                    of 15-20.</p>
                <p>Special requirements for technical support: the
                    instructors will require an audio/video setup capable of displaying material
                    from their laptops <hi rend="italic">and</hi> playing music from their laptops
                    through a speaker system to the audience. Attendees should expect to bring
                    laptops <hi rend="italic">and headphones</hi>. The digital tools used during
                    hands on sessions will be web-based, and will be re-usable by participants in
                    other project contexts. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="div1">
                <head>Outline schedule</head>
                <p>This half-day workshop is divided into two parts, with
                    a break in between.</p>
                <div type="div2">
                    <head>Part 1. Modelling music annotation to accommodate multiple versions, media
                        and performances (90 mins)</head>
                    <p>Presentation: Motivation and worked example</p>
                    <p>Group exercise 1: ontology design</p>
                    <p>Group exercise 2: instance data testing</p>
                    <p>Presentation: The music annotation model</p>
                </div>
                <div type="div2">
                    <head>Part 2. Applying the model for studying performance (90 mins)</head>
                    <p>Presentation: Setting out some research
                        questions</p>
                    <p>Group exercise 1: Exploring music performance
                        through recordings</p>
                    <p>Group exercise 2: Exploring musical style through
                        recordings</p>
                    <p>Presentation: Expanding the scope</p>
                    <p>Questions and feedback</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="div1">
                <head>Instructors</head>
                <p><hi rend="bold">David Lewis</hi> is a researcher at the University of Oxford
                    e-Research Centre and lecturer in Computer Science at Goldsmiths, University of
                    London. Trained in historical musicology at Kings College London, he has spent
                    the last 20 years researching on a wide variety of digital musicology and
                    digital humanities projects, currently the ‘Beethoven in the House’ project. He
                    is particularly interested in digital approaches to music that remain sensitive
                    to its historical, theoretical and social context. David has taught on the
                    Digital Humanities at Oxford Summer School since 2015, on DH summer schools in
                    Philadelphia and Bonn, and on workshops and tutorials at the DH and Music
                    Encoding conferences. <ref target="mailto:david.lewis@oerc.ox.ac.uk">david.lewis@oerc.ox.ac.uk</ref></p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Dr. Kevin Page</hi> is a Senior Research and Associate Faculty
                    at the University of Oxford e-Research Centre, where he is the UK principal
                    investigator of the ‘Beethoven in the House’ research project, previously
                    ‘Unlocking Musicology’ and a co-investigator of ‘Digital Delius’. His research
                    on computational methods for the organisation and analysis of music and musical
                    information has, for several years, aligned with an interest in their use for
                    digital musicology. In 2014 Kevin co-founded the international Digital Libraries
                    for Musicology conference, and has led the Digital Musicology course at the
                    Digital Humanities at Oxford Summer School since instigating it in 2015. At
                    Oxford he teaches Digital Musicology and Linked Data courses as part of the
                    Masters programme in Digital Scholarship. </p>
                <p><ref target="https://eng.ox.ac.uk/people/kevin-page/">https://eng.ox.ac.uk/people/kevin-page/</ref> / <ref target="mailto:kevin.page@oerc.ox.ac.uk">kevin.page@oerc.ox.ac.uk</ref></p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Chanda VanderHart, PhD</hi> is a musicologist &amp; pianist
                    working in three departments at the mdw – University of Music and Performing
                    Arts Vienna (Department of Music Acoustics – Wiener Klangstil (IWK); Lecturer
                    Institute for Musicology and Performance Studies (IMI) and Senior Lecturer at
                    the Anton Bruckner Institute of the mdw- University for Music and Performing
                    Arts Vienna. She is currently a research assistant for the FWF project
                    “Signature Sound Vienna”, completing the monograph “Lieder and Performance in
                    19th Century Vienna; Contexts and Perspectives” and teaching graduate level
                    musicology courses focused on music, performance and their shifting cultural
                    currencies at the institute for musicology. VanderHart has four performance
                    degrees from the USA, Italy and Austria and a PhD in historical musicology. <ref target="https://iwk.mdw.ac.at/chanda-vanderhart/">https://iwk.mdw.ac.at/chanda-vanderhart/</ref> / <ref target="mailto:vanderhart@mdw.ac.at">vanderhart@mdw.ac.at</ref></p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">David M. Weigl, PhD</hi> is a Postdoctoral Research Associate at
                    the Dept. of Music Acoustics – Wiener Klangstil at the mdw – University of Music
                    and Performing Arts Vienna, and principal investigator of Signature Sound
                    Vienna, a research project funded by the Austrian Science Fund. With a PhD in
                    Information Studies from McGill University, he has conducted postdoctoral
                    research at mdw and at the University of Oxford e-Research Centre applying
                    semantic technologies in music industry and music scholarship contexts. He has
                    taught on the Digital Humanities at Oxford Summer School since 2015, the Edirom
                    Summer School in 2019, and has (co-)organised and presented workshops and
                    tutorials at the Joint Conference for Digital Libraries, and at the
                    International Society for Music Information Retrieval, Music Encoding, and the
                    Extended and International Semantic Web conferences. </p>
                <p><ref target="https://iwk.mdw.ac.at/david-weigl/">https://iwk.mdw.ac.at/david-weigl/</ref> / <ref target="mailto:weigl@mdw.ac.at">weigl@mdw.ac.at</ref></p>
            </div>
            <div type="div1">
                <head>Acknowledgements</head>
                <p>This tutorial is supported by the following projects:
                    ‘Beethoven in the House: Digital Studies of Domestic Music Arrangements,’ a
                    UK-Germany collaboration funded in the UK by the Arts and Humanities Research
                    Council (AHRC) project number AH/T01279X/1 and in Germany by the Deutsche
                    Forschungsgemeinschaft (DFG, German Research Foundation), project number
                    429039809; 'The UK Software Sustainability Institute: Phase 3', funded by the UK
                    Engineering and Physical Sciences Research Council (EPSRC) project number
                    EP/S021779/1; and, 'Quantifying the signature sound of the Vienna Philharmonic's
                    New Year's Concerts (Signature Sound Vienna),’ funded by the Austrian Science
                    Fund (FWF) (P 34664-G). </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text></TEI>