<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_allPlus.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_allPlus.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Semantic Web and Linked Open Data in Historical Sciences</title>
                <author n="KrgerBrbelWETTLAUFER_Joerg_Semantic_Web_and_Linked_Open_Data_in_Histor.xml"><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7179-6438" n="KrgerBrbel">
                        <surname>Kröger</surname>
                        <forename>Bärbel</forename>
                    </persName><affiliation>Academy of Sciences and Humanities Göttingen, Germany</affiliation><email>bkroege@gwdg.de</email></author><meeting><date from-iso="2023-07-10" to-iso="2023-07-14"/><title>Digital Humanities 2023. Collaboration as Opportunity</title><placeName>Graz</placeName></meeting>
                <author n="StrikoJohannaSophiaWETTLAUFER_Joerg_Semantic_Web_and_Linked_Open_Data_in_Histor.xml"><persName n="StrikoJohannaSophia">
                        <surname>Störiko</surname>
                        <forename>Johanna Sophia</forename>
                    </persName><affiliation>Institut for Digital Humanities. Georg-August University Göttingen,
                        Germany</affiliation><email>johanna.danielzik@stud.uni-goettingen.de</email></author><meeting><date from-iso="2023-07-10" to-iso="2023-07-14"/><title>Digital Humanities 2023. Collaboration as Opportunity</title><placeName>Graz</placeName></meeting>
                <author n="WettlauferJrgWETTLAUFER_Joerg_Semantic_Web_and_Linked_Open_Data_in_Histor.xml"><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-1957-8059" n="WettlauferJrg">
                        <surname>Wettlaufer</surname>
                        <forename>Jörg</forename>
                    </persName><affiliation>Academy of Sciences and Humanities Göttingen, Germany</affiliation><email>jwettla@gwdg.de</email></author><meeting><date from-iso="2023-07-10" to-iso="2023-07-14"/><title>Digital Humanities 2023. Collaboration as Opportunity</title><placeName>Graz</placeName></meeting>
            </titleStmt>
            
            <publicationStmt><publisher><orgName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1137284463">Zentrum für Informationsmodellierung
                    - Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities, Karl-Franzens-Universität
                    Graz</orgName></publisher><date when="2023">2023</date><pubPlace>Graz</pubPlace><availability><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">Creative Commons BY
                    4.0</licence></availability></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title>Digital Humanities 2023: Book of Abstracts</title><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-9256-0958"><forename>Walter</forename><surname>Scholger</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>University of Graz</orgName><placeName>Graz, Austria</placeName></affiliation><email>walter.scholger@uni-graz.at</email></editor><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-1726-1712"><forename>Georg</forename><surname>Vogeler</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>University of Graz</orgName><placeName>Graz, Austria</placeName></affiliation><email>georg.vogeler@uni-graz.at</email></editor><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-3919-993X"><forename>Toma</forename><surname>Tasovac</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>Belgrade Center for Digital Humanities</orgName><placeName>Belgrade, Serbia</placeName></affiliation><email>ttasovac@humanistika.org</email></editor><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-4593-059X"><forename>Anne</forename><surname>Baillot</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>Le Mans Université</orgName><placeName>Le Mans, France</placeName></affiliation><email>anne.baillot@univ-lemans.fr</email></editor><respStmt><resp>Data Management</resp><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0009-0007-9019-8215"><forename>Elisabeth</forename><surname>Raunig</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Management</resp><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-1438-3236"><forename>Martina</forename><surname>Scholger</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Management</resp><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-9116-0402"><forename>Elisabeth</forename><surname>Steiner</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Curation</resp><persName><forename>Johanna</forename><surname>Ofenauer</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Curation</resp><persName><forename>Christina</forename><surname>Burgstaller</surname></persName></respStmt><idno type="DOI">10.5281/zenodo.7961822</idno></seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="DHCONVALIDATOR" version="1.22">
                    <label>DHConvalidator</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc><abstract><p>The workshop introduces participants to the use of Semantic Web Technologies and Linked Open Data in Digital Historical Studies with a special focus on Wikidata. These topics are highly relevant for knowledge representation in the Digital Humanities and especially important for collaborative processes of analyzing and sharing data.</p></abstract><langUsage><language ident="en">English</language></langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="category">
                    <term>Paper</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="subcategory">
                    <term>Pre-Conference Workshop and Tutorial</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="keywords">
                    <term>Semantic Web</term>
                    <term>Linked Open Data</term>
                    <term>Wikidata</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="topics">
                    <term>linked (open) data</term>
                    <term>metadata standards</term>
                    <term>systems</term>
                    <term>and methods</term>
                    <term>semantic analysis</term>
                    <term>Computer science</term>
                    <term>History</term>
                    
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <p>The workshop introduces participants to the use of Semantic
                Web Technologies and Linked Open Data in Digital Historical Studies with a special
                focus on Wikidata <ref target="#WETTLAUFER_Joerg_Semantic_Web_and_Linked_Open_Data_in_Histor.xml_ftn1" n="1"/>. Semantic Web and Linked Open Data are highly relevant for knowledge
                representation in the Digital Humanities and especially important for collaborative
                processes of analyzing and sharing data. </p>
            <p>Since the publication of the first concept of the "Semantic
                Web" as an extension of the World Wide Web (Berners-Lee / Hendler 2001), humanities
                scholars have been discussing the possibilities and limits
                 of modelling their data within “Semantic Web”.
                The Resource Description Framework (RDF) data model and its serialisation in Turtle
                or N-Triples has become the standard in modelling machine-readable semantic
                statements. The RDF data model today forms the basis o f various knowledge bases (DBpedia, Wikidata) and the knowledge graphs
                that are currently emerging in a variety of contexts. For this reason, the Semantic
                Web and the linking of openly accessible data (Linked Open Data) continue to be of
                particular interest to the digital humanities (Beretta 2021, Beretta / Alamercery
                2020, Hiltmann / Riechert 2020, Meroño-Peñuela 2017, Meroño-Peñuela et al. 2014,
                Pollin 2017, Wettlaufer 2018, Wettlaufer et al. 2015). </p>
            <p>This full-day workshop offers an introduction to the topic
                of "Semantic Web and Linked Open Data" with a focus on historical studies. It aims
                at participants without prior knowledge in the field of Semantic Web/Linked Open
                Data. The workshop divides into four parts, with practical exercises taking up about
                two thirds of the time.</p>
            <p>At the beginning of the workshop, the basics of the
                Semantic Web, the Resource Description Framework as well as associated WWW standards
                are taught in an introductory presentation. Special attention will be paid to
                Wikidata and SPARQL <ref target="#WETTLAUFER_Joerg_Semantic_Web_and_Linked_Open_Data_in_Histor.xml_ftn2" n="2"/>, both of which will play a prominent role in the subsequent exercises. The
                following topics are planned for this first, introductory part: </p>
            <p>The idea of the Semantic Web: brief presentation of the
                basic idea, which developed from the core problem
                    Natural Language Processing. The Resource Description Framework (RDF) as a
                foundation for formalised statements. The importance of stable URIs for the
                functioning of the Semantic Web. The basics of the query language SPARQL: namespaces
                and their importance, especially in the Semantic Web. RDF Schema and Ontologies for
                formulating more complex statements. Linked Open Data, Knowledge Graphs and the LOD
                cloud. Wikidata (and DBpedia) as central nodes of the LOD cloud. Overview of
                resources in the Semantic Web and the LOD cloud for the historical sciences. </p>
            <p>In the second part of the workshop, participants will learn
                to use the Linked Data platform Wikidata and the basics of the query language SPARQL
                in practical exercises. Wikidata is not only currently the largest freely available
                knowledge graph, it also offers data under free licences and, just like Wikipedia,
                allows free collaboration on building the knowledge base . This makes it one of the most relevant data sources
                    for the Semantic Web (Jacobsen et al. 2018). In addition, Wikidata's Query
                Service <ref target="#WETTLAUFER_Joerg_Semantic_Web_and_Linked_Open_Data_in_Histor.xml_ftn3" n="3"/> provides a low-threshold introduction to SPARQL that does not require any
                local installations or technical knowledge. Everything needed for the exercise is an
                internet-enabled device (preferably a laptop) and a Wikidata account. The Wikidata
                graphical user interface is also well suited for teaching the theoretical concepts
                of the Semantic Web without requiring any knowledge of computer science. </p>
            <p>The first workshop section therefore explains the data
                structures of Wikidata. Using an example entry, the theoretical concepts from the
                introductory part of the workshop are shown in their application within Wikidata.
                The example entry represents an item that can be linked to other items via
                properties. Such a link creates a statement. This can be described in more detail by
                so-called qualifiers. Qualifiers are particularly relevant for the use of Wikidata
                in the historical sciences, as they make it possible to specify the origin of
                information as well as potential limits to its validity. This also enables the
                modelling of divergent research results. In addition to the structure of Wikidata
                entries, this part of the workshop also covers an introduction to various RDF
                namespaces relevant in Wikidata. Finally, a Wikidata item can be annotated with
                multiple labels that allow it to be described and named in different languages.</p>
            <p>The handling of these data structures will then be hands on
                explored using data sets from the research project Germania Sacra <ref target="#WETTLAUFER_Joerg_Semantic_Web_and_Linked_Open_Data_in_Histor.xml_ftn4" n="4"/>, which investigates ecclesiastical institutions
                    and persons of the Middle Ages and the Early Modern period. The data will
                be prepared for the workshop in such a way that the participants can enter it into
                Wikidata on their own. Entering the data manually deepens the understanding of the
                data structures, but is not feasible with larger amounts of data. As an outlook the
                tools "QuickStatements" <ref target="#WETTLAUFER_Joerg_Semantic_Web_and_Linked_Open_Data_in_Histor.xml_ftn5" n="5"/> and OpenRefine <ref target="#WETTLAUFER_Joerg_Semantic_Web_and_Linked_Open_Data_in_Histor.xml_ftn6" n="6"/> are introduced, which enable the serial import of larger amounts of data. </p>
            <p>The next block of the workshop deals with the basics of the
                query language SPARQL. The aim is to develop an understanding of how research
                questions in the humanities can be translated into SPARQL queries on Wikidata . To do this, they must first investigate how the
                concepts in the question are modelled in Wikidata. Then a suitable query is
                formulated. This always follows the same basic structure with SELECT, WHERE and, if
                necessary, OPTIONAL, which can be supplemented with further, more complex commands.
                These basic building blocks of SPARQL are first practised with simple queries such
                as "Find all records for bishops with a WIAG identifier". The exercise then goes
                into more depth on concatenating query patterns and querying labels from Wikidata.
                These basics of the query language SPARQL will also be linked to the formal basics
                of the Semantic Web by referring back to the theoretical part of the workshop.
                During the workshop, demonstrations of new concepts alternate with work on exercises
                that build on each other. During the exercises, participants are invited to exchange
                ideas with others, compare results and ask questions. In this way, they gradually
                work out how to query the data sets entered in the first part of the workshop.
                Depending on interests and prior knowledge of the group, participants can also
                experiment with more complex queries including qualifiers and data aggregation. </p>
            <p>The technical framework in which Wikidata is embedded
                offers users freely available tools with which queried data can be evaluated and
                visualised. These include an interactive graph, but also a timeline, a map, an image
                gallery and many other visualisation options. The final part of the workshop
                explains and explores these tools. Finally, the result of this hands-on workshop
                part is a visualisation of the data that the participants entered into Wikidata at
                the beginning of the workshop and queried with the acquired SPARQL knowledge.</p>
            <p>In the fourth and final part of the workshop , participants will also learn how historical data
                is modelled in Wikidata. Following on from this, the potential of Wikibase for the
                historical sciences will be discussed. This includes the advantages and
                disadvantages of collecting data through a collaborative process. A critical look
                will be taken at the questions of data quality, data modelling and the completeness
                of the data. </p>
            <p>Alternatives to Wikidata are also discussed in this part of
                the workshop. Wikibase <ref target="#WETTLAUFER_Joerg_Semantic_Web_and_Linked_Open_Data_in_Histor.xml_ftn7" n="7"/>, the technical framework underlying Wikidata, can also be used as a
                stand-alone instance independent of Wikidata. This solution has the potential to use
                the advantages of the system to link data and at the same time build an independent
                data collection curated by the researchers themselves. There are several examples of
                this in the Digital Humanities, which will be briefly presented. </p>
            <p>Smaller pilot projects, which were realised in the context
                of courses at the University of Göttingen, serve as the basis for a subsequent
                practice-oriented examination of independent Wikibase instances. Not only Wikidata,
                but also the Wikibase instance FactGrid <ref target="#WETTLAUFER_Joerg_Semantic_Web_and_Linked_Open_Data_in_Histor.xml_ftn8" n="8"/> operated by the Gotha Research Centre at the University of Erfurt was
                enriched with data by students of the course. The focus was on the bishops of the
                Old Empire, who processed their servitude payments to the papal curia with the help
                of the Florentine banking house of the Medici family. With the knowledge acquired in
                the workshop, the participants can query this data and gain an insight into the
                practical benefits of Linked Open Data in the historical sciences. </p>
            <p>During the workshop, the participants will be provided with
                the exercises including a sample solution. They will also receive an overview of all
                commands used in the exercise. The didactic concept includes an introductory
                teaching of basic knowledge, interactive exercises, group work and hands-on
                examples. After conveying the basic collaborative idea of the Semantic Web and an
                introduction to the underlying technical standards (RDF, RDFS, SPARQL), the focus is
                on imparting skills when using SPARQL on the Wikidata platform. A look at already
                existing applications of LOD in the historical sciences completes the workshop.</p>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="notes"><note n="1" xml:id="WETTLAUFER_Joerg_Semantic_Web_and_Linked_Open_Data_in_Histor.xml_ftn1">
                    <ref target="https://www.wikidata.org/">https://www.wikidata.org/</ref>
                </note><note n="2" xml:id="WETTLAUFER_Joerg_Semantic_Web_and_Linked_Open_Data_in_Histor.xml_ftn2">
                    <ref target="https://www.w3.org/TR/sparql11-query/">https://www.w3.org/TR/sparql11-query/</ref>
                </note><note n="3" xml:id="WETTLAUFER_Joerg_Semantic_Web_and_Linked_Open_Data_in_Histor.xml_ftn3">
                    <ref target="https://query.wikidata.org/">https://query.wikidata.org/</ref>
                </note><note n="4" xml:id="WETTLAUFER_Joerg_Semantic_Web_and_Linked_Open_Data_in_Histor.xml_ftn4">
                    <ref target="http://www.germania-sacra.de">http://www.germania-sacra.de</ref>
                </note><note n="5" xml:id="WETTLAUFER_Joerg_Semantic_Web_and_Linked_Open_Data_in_Histor.xml_ftn5">
                    <ref target="https://quickstatements.toolforge.org">https://quickstatements.toolforge.org</ref>
                </note><note n="6" xml:id="WETTLAUFER_Joerg_Semantic_Web_and_Linked_Open_Data_in_Histor.xml_ftn6">
                    <ref target="https://openrefine.org">https://openrefine.org</ref>
                </note><note n="7" xml:id="WETTLAUFER_Joerg_Semantic_Web_and_Linked_Open_Data_in_Histor.xml_ftn7">
                    <ref target="https://www.wikimedia.de/projects/wikibase">https://www.wikimedia.de/projects/wikibase</ref>
                </note><note n="8" xml:id="WETTLAUFER_Joerg_Semantic_Web_and_Linked_Open_Data_in_Histor.xml_ftn8">
                    <ref target="https://database.factgrid.de">https://database.factgrid.de</ref>
                </note></div><div type="bibliogr">
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Beretta, Francesco</author> / <author>Vincent Alamercery</author>  (2020) : "Du
                        projet symogih.org au consortium Data for History - La modélisation
                        collaborative de l’information au service de la production de données
                        géo-historiques et de l’interopérabilité dans le web sémantique.", in :
                            <hi rend="italic">Revue ouverte d‘ingénierie des systèmes
                            d’information</hi> 1(3):1-15. <ref target="https://doi.org/10.21494/ISTE.OP.2020.0532">https://doi.org/10.21494/ISTE.OP.2020.0532</ref> [26.04.2023] </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Beretta, Francesco</author> (2021): “A challenge for historical
                        research: making data FAIR using a collaborative ontology management
                        environment (OntoME)”, in: <hi rend="italic">Semantic Web</hi> 12: 2. <ref target="https://doi.org/10.3233/SW-200416">https://doi.org/10.3233/SW-200416</ref> [26.04.2023] </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Berners-Lee, Tim</author> / <author>Hendler, James</author> / <author>Lassila, Ora</author> 
                        (2001): “The Semantic Web: a new form of Web content that is meaningful to
                        computers will unleash a revolution of new possibilities.”, in: <hi rend="italic">Scientific American</hi> 284(5), 34-43. </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Hiltmann, Torsten</author> / <author>Riechert, Thomas</author>  (2020): “Digital
                        Heraldry. The State of the Art and New Approaches Based on Semantic Web
                        Technologies.”. in: Balouzat-Loubet, Christelle (ed.):
                        <hi rend="italic"> L’édition en ligne de documents d’archives médiévaux</hi>,
                        Turnhout : Brepols 102-125. </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Jacobsen, Annika</author> et al. (2018): “Wikidata as an
                        intuitive resource towards semantic data modeling in data FAIRification.”,
                        in: Baker, Christopher et al. (eds.): <hi rend="italic">Semantic Web
                            Applications and Tools for Health Care and Life Sciences</hi>.
                        Proceedings of the 11th International Conference Semantic Web Applications
                        and Tools for Life Sciences (SWAT4HCLS 2018), CEUR workshop proceedings Vol.
                        2275, Antwerp, Belgium, 2018. <ref target="http://ceur-ws.org/Vol-2275/">http://ceur-ws.org/Vol-2275/</ref> [26.04.2023] </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Meroño-Peñuela, Albert</author> et al. (2015): “Semantic
                        Technologies for Historical Research: A  Survey.”, in: <hi rend="italic">Semantic Web Journal</hi> 6: 539-564. </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Meroño-Peñuela, Alberto</author> (2017): “Digital Humanities on
                        the Semantic Web: Accessing Historical and Musical Linked Data,”, in: <hi rend="italic">Journal of Catalan Intellectual History (JOCIH)</hi>
                        1(11): 144-149. DOI: 10.1515/jocih-2016-0013. </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Pollin, Christopher</author> / <author>Vogeler, Georg</author> 
                        (2017): “Semantically Enriched Historical Data. Drawing on the Example of
                        the Digital Edition of the ‘Urfehdebücher der Stadt Basel”, in: A. Adamou /
                        Daga, E. / Isaksen, L. (eds.): <hi rend="italic">2nd Workshop on Humanities
                            in the Semantic Web (WHiSe)</hi>, 27-32. </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Wettlaufer, Jörg</author> (2018): “Der nächste Schritt? Digitale
                        Editionen und Semantic Web.”, in: Kamzelak, Roland / Steyer, Timo (eds.):
                            <hi rend="italic">Zeitschrift für Digitale Geisteswissenschaften</hi>.
                        Sonderheft "Digitale Metamorphosen" (= Sonderband der Zeitschrift für
                        digitale Geisteswissenschaften, 2). DOI: 10.17175/sb002_007. </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Wettlaufer, Jörg</author> et al. (2015): “Semantic Blumenbach:
                        Exploration of Text-Object Relationships with Semantic Web Technology in the
                        History of Science”, in: Terras, Melissa et al. (eds.): <hi rend="italic">Digital Scholarship in the Humanities (DSH)</hi>. Special Issue
                        ‘Digital Humanities 2014’, 30 Supplement 1: i187-i198. <ref target="https://academic.oup.com/dsh/article/30/suppl_1/i187/364720/">https://academic.oup.com/dsh/article/30/suppl_1/i187/364720/</ref>
                        [26.04.2023] </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text></TEI>