<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_allPlus.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_allPlus.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Data Problems in the Humanities, or "When everybody is special, no one is"? </title>
                <author n="WoodsNathanDWOODS_Nathan_Data_Problems_in_the_Humanities__or__When_every.xml"><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-1082-2396" n="WoodsNathanD">
                        <surname>Woods</surname>
                        <forename>Nathan D.</forename>
                    </persName><affiliation>University of Lethbridge, Canada</affiliation><email>nathan.woods@uleth.ca</email></author><meeting><date from-iso="2023-07-10" to-iso="2023-07-14"/><title>Digital Humanities 2023. Collaboration as Opportunity</title><placeName>Graz</placeName></meeting>
                <author n="BordalejoBarbaraWOODS_Nathan_Data_Problems_in_the_Humanities__or__When_every.xml"><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-8255-0265" n="BordalejoBarbara">
                        <surname>Bordalejo</surname>
                        <forename>Barbara</forename>
                    </persName><affiliation>University of Lethbridge, Canada</affiliation><email>barbara.bordalejo@uleth.ca</email></author><meeting><date from-iso="2023-07-10" to-iso="2023-07-14"/><title>Digital Humanities 2023. Collaboration as Opportunity</title><placeName>Graz</placeName></meeting>
                <author n="ODonnellDanielPaulWOODS_Nathan_Data_Problems_in_the_Humanities__or__When_every.xml"><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-0127-4893" n="ODonnellDanielPaul">
                        <surname>O'Donnell</surname>
                        <forename>Daniel Paul</forename>
                    </persName><affiliation>University of Lethbridge, Canada</affiliation><email>daniel.odonnell@uleth.ca</email></author><meeting><date from-iso="2023-07-10" to-iso="2023-07-14"/><title>Digital Humanities 2023. Collaboration as Opportunity</title><placeName>Graz</placeName></meeting>
            </titleStmt>
            
            <publicationStmt><publisher><orgName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1137284463">Zentrum für Informationsmodellierung
                    - Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities, Karl-Franzens-Universität
                    Graz</orgName></publisher><date when="2023">2023</date><pubPlace>Graz</pubPlace><availability><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">Creative Commons BY
                    4.0</licence></availability></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title>Digital Humanities 2023: Book of Abstracts</title><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-9256-0958"><forename>Walter</forename><surname>Scholger</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>University of Graz</orgName><placeName>Graz, Austria</placeName></affiliation><email>walter.scholger@uni-graz.at</email></editor><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-1726-1712"><forename>Georg</forename><surname>Vogeler</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>University of Graz</orgName><placeName>Graz, Austria</placeName></affiliation><email>georg.vogeler@uni-graz.at</email></editor><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-3919-993X"><forename>Toma</forename><surname>Tasovac</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>Belgrade Center for Digital Humanities</orgName><placeName>Belgrade, Serbia</placeName></affiliation><email>ttasovac@humanistika.org</email></editor><editor><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-4593-059X"><forename>Anne</forename><surname>Baillot</surname></persName><affiliation><orgName>Le Mans Université</orgName><placeName>Le Mans, France</placeName></affiliation><email>anne.baillot@univ-lemans.fr</email></editor><respStmt><resp>Data Management</resp><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0009-0007-9019-8215"><forename>Elisabeth</forename><surname>Raunig</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Management</resp><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-1438-3236"><forename>Martina</forename><surname>Scholger</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Management</resp><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-9116-0402"><forename>Elisabeth</forename><surname>Steiner</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Curation</resp><persName><forename>Johanna</forename><surname>Ofenauer</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Data Curation</resp><persName><forename>Christina</forename><surname>Burgstaller</surname></persName></respStmt><idno type="DOI">10.5281/zenodo.7961822</idno></seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="DHCONVALIDATOR" version="1.22">
                    <label>DHConvalidator</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc><abstract><p>The contemporary focus on the ‘data problem’ in the humanities centers on the uniqueness of humanities data. We argue this is a mistake. Humanities data are not special because of what they are, but rather because of how they are used. The “problem” with Humanities data lies in the use-case.</p></abstract><langUsage><language ident="en">English</language></langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="category">
                    <term>Paper</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="subcategory">
                    <term>Long Presentation</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="keywords">
                    <term>Humanities Data</term>
                    <term>Data</term>
                    <term>Infrastructure</term>
                    <term>Data Management</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="topics">
                    <term>data publishing projects</term>
                    <term>systems</term>
                    <term>and methods</term>
                    <term>data</term>
                    <term>object</term>
                    <term>and artefact preservation</term>
                    <term>digital research infrastructures development and analysis</term>
                    <term>project design</term>
                    <term>organization</term>
                    <term>management</term>
                    <term>History of science</term>
                    <term>Humanities computing</term>
                    <term>Informatics</term>
                    <term>Library &amp; information science</term>
                    
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <p>That the humanities has ‘a data problem’ is now a common refrain amongst many communities. Humanists often argue that humanities data is a problem because they don’t have or work with data (Borgman, 2010; Posner, 2015). Librarians and information professionals, by contrast, believe that humanists have data, but assume they don’t realize it — meaning that the problem is that they must be trained to appropriately recognize and work with data they most surely have (Flanders, Julia, and Trevor Muñoz, 2012; Ikeshoji-Orlati, Caton, and Stringer-Hye, 2018). Digital humanists know that they (at least) have data, but believe that their data are special, distinct both from those used by scientists and (often) those “not recognized” by traditional humanists — and that these data require special strategies and techniques as a result (Drucker, 2011; Schöch, 2013). In a rough and general way each premise informs a mélange of assumptions, advice and best practices that comprise the emerging literature on research data management (RDM) in the humanities. </p>
            <p>In this paper we argue that this focus on the discovery and definition of what is “special” about the definition or recognition of humanities data is a mistake. Humanities data are not special because of what they are, but rather because of how they are used (Borgman, 2017; Leonelli, 2015). Data are data, in other words, whether they are produced and used by scientists or humanists. The “problem” with Humanities data — and the thing that makes them special — lies in the use-case. Humanities
                data are both designed and structured by systems to meet scholarly or systematic
                ends. While many humanities researchers engage, as users, with designed research
                infrastructure, humanities scholars also innovate, design, and build scholar-led
                research infrastructure that have specific systems requirements, but often without
                clear requirements modeling. We draw out the implications of this argument on two fronts, looking at the issue of research, and the implications for humanities infrastructure development. <lb/>First, we report on the preliminary results of ongoing research examining how
                humanists think about data as they build, navigate, and utilize research
                infrastructure for scholarly purposes. Reported results derive from a series of
                comparative case studies ( Eisenhardt, 1989; Maryl et al. 2020) examining four cases of
                scholar-led projects that deploy digital research infrastructure for scholarly ends.
                Cases were purposively selected using the following criteria: a. Are scholar-driven;
                b. Involve representation of ‘real world’ objects involving small, intensively
                curated datasets; c. Have a documented record of accomplishment and innovation. </p>
            <p>Although humanists have a long history of designing and
                building research infrastructure, both analog and digital ( Abbott, 2012; Bod, 2013) this has been less
                appreciated in the literature on humanities infrastructure design.
                By comparing elements from our case studies, we build
                on previous studies of humanists as both users of information resources (Bates,
                1996a; 1996b; Bates et. al, 1993; Buchanan, Gow, Blandford, Rimmer, and Warwick,
                2006; Palmer,Teffeau,Pirmann, 2009; Stone, 1982;
                    Rimmer, Warwick, Blandford, Gow, and Buchanan, G., 2008; Watson-Boone,
                1994), and digital tools (Gibbs and Owens,2022) to
                    consider issues of use-case construction, both formally and informally, over
                    time.<lb/>Emphasizing the role of scholars as designers (Lamb and King, 2003; Millerand
                and Baker, 2010), we highlight the importance of the ‘use-case’ as a means to
                culturally frame and model system requirements, functional and non-functional, as a
                type of socio-technical fact, mediating between user-agency, the purpose of a
                scholarly project, and the design, development and maintenance of the research
                infrastructures innovated to meet those goals. Originating in software engineering, use-case modeling (Jacobson et al. 1992)
                    is a means of specifying, validating, and eliciting system requirements, where
                    use case models describe, communicate, and facilitate all of the ways a user
                    interacting with a system or product may work to realize a desired end. While
                    there is a robust literature on how to write and design use cases (Kulak, Daryl,
                    and Guiney, 2012) there is little empirical study of use-case development or
                    implementation in software engineering (Anda,2003), and nothing that
                    systematically examines the diffusion of the concept outside these arenas of
                    expert work.<lb/><lb/>By comparing the roles of humanist researchers as designers, we complicate
                    previous research on humanities work practices (Blanke and Hedges, 2013;
                Pachecho, 2022; Unsworth, 2000) and studies of interdisciplinary scholarly
                information practice more broadly ( Palmer, 2013),
                drawing on the notion of ‘infrastructural practices’ ( Baker and Millerand, 2016; Baker, Duerr, and Parsons, 2015; Edwards, 2019;
                    Karasti and Blomberg, 2018) in scholarly information ecosystems ( Altman and Cohen, 2022 ), and hence on the dual
                role of scholars as infrastructure designers-builders and users ( Lamb and Kling, 2003; Millerand and Baer, 2010,
                    Mongili, 2014).<lb/>While we acknowledge a few exceptions for specific tools and technical standards for the Digital Humanities (e.g. Voyant, TEI, IIIF, CIDOC
                CRM ), the Humanities generally lack the proliferation
                    of a robust, distributed, yet centrally networked, ecosystem supporting
                    generalizable infrastructure development process, linking standards with the
                    infrastructure practices central to scholar originated infrastructure projects
                    (c.f. Bosman and Kramer, 2015). Rather, humanities researchers have worked far
                    more improvisationally (Ciula, 2022), and in the absence of a systematic
                    orientation to project requirements, have instead created custom knowledge
                    infrastructure. As a result, the identification of discipline-wide standards for
                    tools and infrastructure is far more difficult.<lb/><lb/>From the perspective of infrastructure design, development, and
                    maintenance, therefore, the “problem of Humanities data” is how to support and
                    interface with scholarly use-cases, the scenarios and problem sets scholars are
                    concerned with, and engage with the custom infrastructural strategies they have
                    developed to speak to them. In our conclusion, we point to some ways where a
                    focus on use case modeling and system requirements planning can complement
                    efforts to refine project development, particularly with reference to
                recent work on ‘data communities’ (Cooper and Springer, 2023) and
                community-oriented frameworks (Lyon, et. al 2012; Jeng and Oh, 2016; Jeng and He,
                2022) to bring researchers and infrastructural partners into structured dialogue
                regarding requirements development. <lb/></p>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliogr">
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <bibl><author>Abbott, Andrew</author>,
                        
                        
                        
                        2011. "Library research
                            infrastructure for humanistic and social scientific scholarship in the
                            twentieth century." Social knowledge in the making, pp.43-88.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl><author>Altman, M., and Cohen. P.N.</author>
                        
                        
                        
                        
                        ,2022. "The scholarly knowledge
                            ecosystem: Challenges and opportunities for the field of information."
                            Frontiers in Research Metrics and Analytics 6 85.</bibl>
                    <bibl><author>Anda, B</author>
                        
                        
                        . 2003
                        
                        
                        . "Empirical studies of
                            construction and application of use case models." University of Oslo,
                            Norway.</bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="bold">Baker, K.S. and Millerand,
                                F.</hi>, 2016. Infrastructuring ecology: Challenges in achieving
                            data sharing. In
                         
                        Collaboration in the new life sciences
                         
                        (pp. 133-160). Routledge.</bibl>
                    <bibl><lb/><hi rend="bold">Baker, K.S., Duerr, R.E. and Parsons, M.A.</hi>,
                            2015. Scientific knowledge mobilization: Co-evolution of data products
                            and designated communities. 
                        International Journal of Digital Curation, 10.2 </bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="bold">Bates, M.J.</hi>, 1996. Document
                            familiarity, relevance, and Bradford’s law: The Getty online searching
                            project report no. 5.
                         
                        Information Processing &amp; Management,
                         
                        32(6), pp.697-707.</bibl>
                    <bibl><author>Bates, M.J.</author>, 1996. The Getty end-user online
                        searching project in the humanities: Report no. 6: Overview and
                        conclusions. College &amp; Research Libraries, 57(6), pp.514-523.</bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="bold">Bates, M.J.,
                                Wilde, D.N. and Siegfried, S.</hi>, 1995. Research practices of
                            humanities scholars in an online environment: The Getty online searching
                            project report no. 3. Library &amp; Information Science Research, 17(1),
                            pp.5-40.</bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="bold">Blanke, T. and
                                Hedges, M.</hi>, 2013. Scholarly primitives: Building institutional
                            infrastructure for humanities e-Science. Future Generation Computer
                            Systems, 29(2), pp.654-661.</bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="bold">Bod, R.</hi>, 2013.
                         
                        A new history of the humanities: The search for
                            principles and patterns from antiquity to the present. Oxford University
                            Press.</bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="bold">Borgman, C.L.</hi>, 2017.
                         
                        Big data, little data, no data: Scholarship in the
                            networked world. MIT press.</bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="bold">Borgman, C.L.</hi>, 2010. The
                            digital future is now: A call to action for the humanities.
                         
                        Digital humanities quarterly,
                         
                        3(4).</bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="bold">Bosman, J. and Kramer, B.</hi>,
                            2015. 101 Innovations in Scholarly Communication: How researchers are
                            getting to grip with the myriad of new tools.
                         
                        Impact of Social Sciences Blog.</bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="bold">Buchanan, G., Gow, J., Blandford,
                                A., Rimmer, J. and Warwick, C.</hi>, 2007, June. Representing
                            aggregate works in the digital library. In
                         
                        Proceedings of the 7th ACM/IEEE-CS joint conference
                            on Digital libraries
                         
                        (pp. 247-256).</bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <hi rend="bold">Ciula, A. and Smithies, J.</hi>,
                            2023. Sustainability and modelling at King’s Digital Lab: between
                            tradition and innovation. In
                         
                        On Making in the Digital Humanities: The
                            scholarship of digital humanities development in honor of John
                            Bradley
                         
                        (pp. 78-104). University College London
                        Press.</bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="bold">Cooper, D. and Springer, R.</hi>,
                            2019. Data Communities: A New Model for Supporting STEM Data
                            Sharing
                        . 
                        Ithaka S+R. 13 May 2019. Web. 14
                            January 2023. https://doi.org/10.18665/sr.311396
                        .</bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <hi rend="bold">Drucker, J.</hi>, 2011. Humanities
                            approaches to graphical display.
                         
                        Digital Humanities Quarterly,
                         
                        5(1).</bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="bold">Edwards, P.N.</hi>, 2019.
                            Infrastructuration: On habits, norms, and routines as elements of
                            infrastructure. In
                         
                        Thinking infrastructures. Emerald Publishing
                            Limited.</bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="bold">Eisenhardt, K.M.</hi>, 1989.
                            Building theories from case study research.
                         
                        Academy of management review,
                         
                        14(4), pp.532-550.</bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="bold">Flanders, J.H., Muñoz, T. and Senseney, M.</hi>, 2012. Digital Humanities Data Curation. 
                        DH Curation Guide: A community
                            resource guide to data curation in the digital humanities.</bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="bold">Gibbs, F. and Owens, T. </hi>2012. Building Better Digital Humanities Tools: Toward broader audiences and user-centered designs. Digital Humanit. Q. 6 (2). </bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="bold">Jacobson, I., Booch, G. and
                                Rumbaugh, J.</hi>, 1999. The UNIFIED Software Development Process·
                            Addison Wesley Longman.
                         
                        Reading, Massachusetts.</bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="bold">Jeng, W., He, D. and Oh,
                                J.S.</hi>, 2016. Toward a conceptual framework for data sharing
                            practices in social sciences: A profile approach.
                         
                        Proceedings of the Association for Information
                            Science and Technology,
                         
                        53(1), pp.1-10.</bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="bold">Jeng, W. and He, D.</hi>, 2022.
                            Surveying research data-sharing practices in US social sciences: a
                            knowledge infrastructure-inspired conceptual framework.
                         
                        Online Information Review.</bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="bold">Ikeshoji-Orlati, V., Caton, M.A.
                                and Stringer-Hye, S.</hi>, 2018. Tiny Data: Building a Community of
                            Practice around Humanities Datasets.</bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="bold">Karasti, H. and Blomberg,
                            J.</hi>, 2018. Studying infrastructuring ethnographically.
                         
                        Computer Supported Cooperative Work (CSCW),
                         
                        27, pp.233-265.</bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="bold">Kulak, D. and Guiney, E.</hi>,
                            2012.
                         
                        Use cases: requirements in context.
                            Addison-Wesley.</bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="bold">Lamb, R. and Kling, R.</hi>,
                            2003. Reconceptualizing users as social actors in information systems
                            research.
                         
                        MIS quarterly, pp.197-236.</bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="bold">Leonelli, Sabina</hi>. "What
                            counts as scientific data? A relational framework."
                         
                        Philosophy of Science
                         
                        82, no. 5 (2015): 810-821.</bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="bold">Lyon, L., Ball,
                                A., Duke, M. and Day, M.</hi>, 2012, October. Developing a Community
                            Capability Model Framework for data-intensive research. In Proceedings
                            of the 9th International Conference on the Preservation of Digital
                            Objects (pp. 9-16).</bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="bold">Maryl, M., Dallas, C., Edmond,
                                J., Labov, J., Kelpšienė, I., Doran, M., Kotodziejska, M. and
                                Grabowska, K.</hi>, 2020. A case study protocol for meta-research
                            into digital practices in the humanities.
                         
                        Digital humanities quarterly,
                         
                        14(3), pp.1-20.</bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="bold">Millerand, F., and Baker,
                                K.S.</hi>, 2010. Who are the users? Who are the developers? Webs of
                            users and developers in the development process of a technical
                            standard.
                         
                        Information Systems Journal,
                         
                        20(2), pp.137-161.</bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="bold">Mongili, A.</hi>, 2014. Designers
                            as users: Blurring positions and theories in creative practices.
                         
                        Information Infrastructure (S): Boundaries,
                            Ecologies, Multiplicity, pp.2-25.</bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="bold">Pacheco, A.</hi>, 2022. Digital
                            humanities or humanities in digital: revisiting scholarly
                            primitives.
                         
                        Digital Scholarship in the Humanities,
                         
                        37(4), pp.1128-1140.</bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="bold">Palmer, C.L.</hi>, 2013.
                         
                        Work at the boundaries of science: Information and
                            the interdisciplinary research process. Springer Science &amp; Business
                            Media.</bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="bold">Palmer, C.L. and Neumann,
                                L.J.</hi>, 2002. The information work of interdisciplinary
                            humanities scholars: Exploration and translation.
                         
                        The Library Quarterly,
                         
                        72(1), pp.85-117.</bibl>
                    <bibl><author>Palmer, C.L., Teffeau, L.C. and Pirmann, C.M.</author>, 2009.
                        Scholarly information practices in the online environment. OCLC Research
                        .</bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="bold">Posner, M.</hi>, 2015. Humanities
                            data: A necessary contradiction.
                         
                        Miriam Posner’s Blog,
                         
                        25.</bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="bold">Rimmer, J., Warwick, C.,
                                Blandford, A., Gow, J. and Buchanan, G.</hi>, 2008. An examination
                            of the physical and the digital qualities of humanities research.
                         
                        Information Processing &amp; Management,
                         
                        44(3), pp.1374-1392.</bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="bold">Schöch, C.</hi>, 2013. Big?
                            Smart? Clean? Messy? Data in the Humanities?
                         
                        Journal of the Digital Humanities,
                         
                        2(3).</bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="bold">Stone, S.</hi>, 1982. Humanities
                            scholars: information needs and uses.
                         
                        Journal of documentation,
                         
                        38(4), pp.292-313.</bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="bold">Unsworth, J.</hi>, 2000, May.
                            Scholarly primitives: What methods do humanities researchers have in
                            common, and how might our tools reflect this. In
                         
                        Symposium on Humanities Computing: Formal Methods,
                            Experimental Practice. King’s College, London
                         
                        (Vol. 13, pp. 5-00).</bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="bold">Watson-Boone, R.</hi>, 1994. The
                            information needs and habits of humanities scholars.
                         
                        RQ, pp.203-215.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text></TEI>